<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The euer-burning lamps of pietie and deuotion Kindled by many excellent and heauenly prayers, deuided into the seuerall dayes of the weeke, and other occasions: To auoide which weake man hath continuall cause to retire into himselfe, and humbly confer with Almightie God. By I.C.</title>
            <author>I. C.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 222 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 147 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17457</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4278</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118322</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853529</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853529</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18914</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17457)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18914)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1197:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The euer-burning lamps of pietie and deuotion Kindled by many excellent and heauenly prayers, deuided into the seuerall dayes of the weeke, and other occasions: To auoide which weake man hath continuall cause to retire into himselfe, and humbly confer with Almightie God. By I.C.</title>
                  <author>I. C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[36], 252 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Purslowe for Richard Hawkins, and are to bee sold at his shop in Chancery-Lane neere Serieants Inne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18914:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18914:1"/>
            <p>THE Euer-burning Lamps of Pietie and Deuotion. Kindled by many Excellent and Heauenly Prayers, Deuided into the ſeuerall dayes of the Weeke, and other Occaſions:</p>
            <p>To auoide which weake Man hath continuall cauſe to retire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelfe, and humbly confer with Almightie God.</p>
            <p>By <hi>I. C.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>George Purſlewe</hi> for <hi>Richard Hawkins,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his Shop in Chancery-lane neere Serieants Inne. 161<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18914:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18914:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOVRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE, EXCELLENT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LY VERTVOVS, and truely Noble, the Ladie VILLIERS, Wife to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, and euery way accompliſht Knight, Sir EDVVARD VILLIERS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Haue not choſen this Text to paint your Vertues, but
<pb facs="tcp:18914:3"/>
cure mine owne infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, who deſperately ill of a ſurfet, and giuen ouer by the beſt Doctor of my fortunes, found no comfort but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiring, and asking counſell of that heauenly, and neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erring Phyſician, who came into the world to cure all manner of Diſeaſes; which euer intending to publiſh for the good, I hope, of others, that dare take ſo much time, to thinke of their ſickeneſſe, and practiſe a recouerie: I did not long labour for a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication,
<pb facs="tcp:18914:3"/>
knowing no La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die (as far be it from arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy, as I know it is from flatterie) that deſerueth tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier and realler, to bee a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron (being the ſubiect of all vertues) then your ſelfe; your life and manners better commending you, then can my pen, who may expreſſe my owne Deuotions, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reach yours: Though to thoſe who onely know, or, to ſpeake properly, haue onely ſeene you, in the colours and attire of the Time, equally
<pb facs="tcp:18914:4"/>
grac'd and behau'd with the beſt of thoſe that affect Court moſt, it may appeare other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, who neuer ſeeking Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, but in rough and wilde places, imagine Solitarineſſe, and Neglect ſurer compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of him, then State and Ceremonie: Yet ſince the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of goodneſſe, (as the Sunne in fouleſt weather) in all Callings, maintaineth her owne perfection, and that in publique and great perſons, ſingularitie and niceneſſe of Attire, would rather boaſt
<pb facs="tcp:18914:4"/>
then forward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertue, you wiſely and moſt Religiouſly, follow that precept of our Sauiours, to waſh your face, and put on your Ornaments, that in your chiefe auſterity and retiring, you may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare not to proclaime it: For thoſe light braines (full of fault-finding, and as faulty) who may accuſe mee to haue giuen good time to ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Muſick, which ſoundeth well in Ladies eares, when I ſhould haue applyed my ſelfe to my ſubiect, in ſetting out
<pb facs="tcp:18914:5"/>
the excellencie, height and reward of prayers: I would hee could vnderſtand, there be ſuch <hi>Myrrors</hi> as I heare ſpeake of, and that your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhips practice can better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deliuer theſe things, then my rude precepts, hauing beene an eye-witneſſe, for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of twelue Months, of your inward and holy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collection, from which dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no buſineſſe, nor other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation had power to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw you, to whoſe holy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirations, and wonder-working
<pb facs="tcp:18914:5"/>
feruour, I leaue your good and great for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, aſſuring my ſelfe, your vertue cannot fall ſo guided, nor your fortune ſo accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, but that you ſhall ſtill remaine a ſweete-ſmelling ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to God, and an attrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue and flouriſhing example to men, amongſt whom, though not onely, I chiefly, at leaſt moſt deſirouſly, remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Vertues honorer and Obſeruer: I. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:18914:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18914:6"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO <hi>THE READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint of all ages, and of all men, that the times are bad, they moſt finding fault with it, by whoſe corruption it decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth and waineth in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: But indeed, if euer
<pb facs="tcp:18914:7"/>
vertue her ſelfe had cauſe to put on widdowed gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and mingle her conſtancie with lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, it is in our daies to ſee her ſelfe thus forſaken and abandoned, being ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome entertained for her reall worth, without ſome ſecondarie reſpect of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular applauſe and prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which though ſhee rarely attaine for her owne ſake, yet great Ones are content in her likeneſſe, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſerue their owne
<pb facs="tcp:18914:7"/>
appetites, then when they appeare nakedly clad in their owne Deformitie; which is the cauſe we miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking the grounds, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of Honours, how they alter, and (as it were) vnnaturize the diſpoſitions and manners of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, when indeed they cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly diſguiſing and hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with falſe ſeemings, their cankred and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous inclinations, ſteale to their aſpired height, which once growne Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb facs="tcp:18914:8"/>
of, they pull off their Viſor, and armed with their greatneſſe, feare not to pleaſe themſelues with the manifeſting their vices. This I thinke, as it moued the Printer to aduiſe me to the publiſhing of theſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations and Prayers, ſo aboue all hee entreated to haue a care, they were not long or tedious, leſt the people (who meaſure it with their eye) might take a ſurfet of it before it came to the ſtomack: Like men,
<pb facs="tcp:18914:8"/>
willing, for their recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to walke a mile to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port themſelues, but if ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily inforced to any longer iourney, growing wearie before they ſet one foote abroad; I haue, I thinke, ſatisfied the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters deſire, and the humour of the people, rather die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them with what is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely neceſſarie, then ouer-charging their weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to a ſatietie, till by theſe they ſhall be enabled (vertue gathering ſtrength
<pb facs="tcp:18914:9"/>
by practice) to feed on lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Diſcourſes for their weale and ſaluation: to which to draw the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more, by ſetting forth the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of prayer, there can be, I hope, nothing better, or more knowingly ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then that often and earneſt precept of our Sauiours, commanding vs to <hi>Watch</hi> and <hi>Pray continually, leſt we enter into temptation:</hi> which ioined with his own exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (made precious by his vnparaleld and vnimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb facs="tcp:18914:9"/>
loue to vs) cannot but melt the moſt frozen and hardened careleſſenes, making it apt to receiue ſo bleſſed an impreſſion. That his life was nothing but a Diuine Rapture, and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Meditation of high and excellent Myſteries, is no way to be doubted; and that he did vſually breathe them forth in zealous and moſt deuoute prayers, the holy Scripture teſtifyeth, how often and humbly in the accompliſhing of his
<pb facs="tcp:18914:10"/>
Miracles, how often and feruently before his Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and at the inſtant of his betraying, and taking, when the bleſſed Apoſtle and follower S. <hi>Peter,</hi> vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently rauiſhed with the extremitie of loue to ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent a Lord, tooke out his ſword, and with it cut off one of the eares of the Miniſters, hee rebuked him, ſaying, <hi>Thinkeſt thou that I cannot now pray to my Father, and hee will giue me more then twelue Legions
<pb facs="tcp:18914:10"/>
of Angels?</hi> euer intimating vnto vs, the excellencie and efficacie of prayer, as the onely meanes to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vertuous purpoſes.</p>
            <p>For the ſet times of vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call prayers (heauenly and ſhort eiaculations being at all houres to be vſed) it hath been thought fit, by many learned and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Fathers, to be diuided into Morning, Noone, and Euening, it being moſt fit to offer the Immortall and high Deitie, our firſt
<pb facs="tcp:18914:11"/>
thoughts, that ſeaſon'd with the knowledge of him, we may with the more care &amp; attention behaue ourſelues the day following; recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling our ſelues at Noone to deſire ſtrength for the continuance and perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in holy and good purpoſes; and cloſing and ſhutting vp all actions and tranſitorie thoughts in the Euening, with thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing for the bleſſings of that day, and an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of our ſins and
<pb facs="tcp:18914:11"/>
tranſgreſsions, committing our ſelues to his Fatherly protection the enſuing night, that awaking in the morning, wee may finde a wel-pleaſing relliſh of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoughts timely and maturely digeſted.</p>
            <p>For the better compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our ſelues at the time of prayer, we ought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, duely and earneſtly to conſider his Greatneſſe and Immenſitie to whom wee pray, the neceſsitie and height of what
<pb facs="tcp:18914:12"/>
we pray for, and our own vnworthineſſe to obtaine a grant &amp; accompliſhment of our petitions, that being truely humbled and caſt down in our ſelues, it may pleaſe the Lord of heauen and earth, to haue the more pitie &amp; compaſſion on vs.</p>
            <p>And if men that appeare to ſpeake before an earthly King, ſeriouſly prepare and examine themſelues, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling euery word to a iuſt weight and meaſure, ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taking care of the leſt
<pb facs="tcp:18914:12"/>
geſture; How ought we in the preſence of ſo great, &amp; aboue all compariſons, infinitely excelling a Lord, be ſollicitous and heedfull, that nothing paſſe from vs vnworthy, or il-beſeeming his Diuinitie &amp; pureneſſe?</p>
            <p>Thus praying, and beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing our ſelues, we ſhall (no queſtion) finde to our ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-dying comfort, the euer-liuingnes of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes in the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our iuſt petitions, being made witneſſes of
<pb facs="tcp:18914:13"/>
the diſſolution of heauen and earth, &amp; the vaniſhing away of all things tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie at the command of his Word, one iot or tittle whereof ſhall not be taken away or diminiſhed, but remaine pure and perfect, in the iuſtification of his Elect, clothing them with eternitie and immortality; to which ſtate of happines our bleſſed Sauiour ſend vs all, for his holy Names ſake.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:18914:13"/>
            <head>A Table containing the ſeuerall Prayers.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>A</hi> Prayer for Munday Morning. <hi>1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer for Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day Noone. <hi>2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Munday Night. <hi>3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Tueſday Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. <hi>4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18914:14"/>A Prayer for Tueſday Noon. <hi>5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Tueſday Night. <hi>6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Wedneſday Morning. <hi>7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Wedneſday Noone. <hi>8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Wedneſday Night. <hi>9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Thurſday Morning. <hi>10</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Thurſday Noone. <hi>11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Thurſday Night. <hi>12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18914:14"/>A Prayer for Friday Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. <hi>13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Friday Noone. <hi>14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Friday Night. <hi>15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Saturday Morning. <hi>16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Saturday Noone. <hi>17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Saturday Night. <hi>18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Sunday Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. <hi>19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Sunday Noone. <hi>20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18914:15"/>A Prayer for Sunday Night. <hi>21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer to our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour for Humility. <hi>22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Another for aſsiſtance in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and troubles. <hi>23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer againſt Pride. <hi>24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer againſt the concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence of the Fleſh. <hi>25</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer againſt Sloth. <hi>26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer againſt Couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An acknowledgement of ſins, with promiſe of amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer in afflictions and
<pb facs="tcp:18914:15"/>
troubles. <hi>29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer for Remiſsion of ſinnes. <hi>30</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer for Chaſtitie. <hi>31</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer to be ſayd in a iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. <hi>32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer againſt Lightening and Thunder. <hi>33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer or Meditation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the benefites after creation. <hi>34</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer againſt vaine At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire. <hi>35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer for a Maid againſt temptations. <hi>36</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Another to the ſame effect. <hi>37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18914:16"/>A prayer for a Maid, not to bee puffed vp with her owne perfections. <hi>38</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer for a Maid to bee directed in her choyſe. <hi>39</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer for a Maid to bee obedient to her Parents. <hi>40</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer before a Iourney. <hi>41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Another for the ſame. <hi>42</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer in afflictions. <hi>43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer for a Marchant. <hi>44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer before Studie. <hi>45</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer for the Fatherleſſe. <hi>46</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18914:16"/>A prayer in afflictions and troubles. <hi>47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Thankeſ-giuing. <hi>48</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer in time of Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. <hi>49</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer in time of War. <hi>50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer for a Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to receiue the fruits of the earth. <hi>51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer for a Widdow. <hi>52</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer for a Wife. <hi>53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer for Maryners. <hi>54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer for Children. <hi>55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer for Seruants. <hi>56</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer for one that is ſick. <hi>57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18914:17"/>A prayer for womens deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. <hi>58</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer going to bed. <hi>59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer againſt idle talke. <hi>60</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Thankeſ-giuing. <hi>61</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer for direction in all the courſe of our life. <hi>62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer for great men ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in places of Honour. <hi>63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Thankeſgiuing for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery of our high and mightie Soueraigne King <hi>Iames.</hi> April. <hi>1619. 64</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Another Thankeſ-giuing. <hi>65</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18914:17"/>A prayer againſt our enemies. <hi>66</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Another prayer for deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from our enemies. <hi>67</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Thankeſgiuing for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow of our enemies. <hi>68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for preſent neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities. <hi>69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Another prayer intreating re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion of ſins, &amp; conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in good purpoſes. <hi>70</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer in ſickneſſe. <hi>71</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer to bee ſaid before any work we go about. <hi>72</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18914:18"/>A prayer for remiſsion of ſinnes. <hi>73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer for perſeuerance. <hi>74</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer in affliction. <hi>75</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer in extremitie of ſickeneſſe. <hi>76</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer in the Spring time. <hi>77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer in Summer. <hi>78</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A payer to bee ſayd in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumn. <hi>79</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer to be ſayd in Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>80</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer in aduerſity and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction. <hi>81</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18914:18"/>A prayer to our bleſſed Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. <hi>82</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer in time of Lent. <hi>83</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer againſt temptation. <hi>84</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer for preparation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>85</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Certaine Eiaculations of the Spirit.</item>
               <item>A ſhort Meditation vpon theſe words of <hi>Pilate; Behold the Man.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Meditation vpon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18914:19"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18914:19"/>
            <head>THE EVER-BVRNING Lamps of Deuotion and Pietie.</head>
            <div n="Monday" type="day">
               <head>MVNDAY MORNING.</head>
               <div n="1" type="morning_prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>1.</hi> Morning Prayer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> ETERNALL and euer-liuing God, what humble and heartie thankes ought I ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy diuine Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, who haſt called me from the image of Death, and ſafely brought me to the beholding of this day; giuing me yet farther time to call
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18914:20"/>
vpon thy holy Name, and to aske forgiueneſſe for my ſinnes and wickedneſſes. Receiue, O Lord, an humble and contrite heart, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe not the voice of a miſerable and deiected ſinner, who can offer thee nothing for theſe and all other thy innumerable benefits, but what muſt graciouſly proceed from thy owne clemencie and mercie; poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing no good, but from thee, and by thee, exerciſing nothing agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to thy will; but through thee, euen at this inſtant, mercifully led by thy power and gentleneſſe, to make my humble ſupplications vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee. Seaſon me, O Lord, with thy Spirit, endue me with thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and holy gifts, that I may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow this day to thy honour and glorie, and my owne comfort and eternall ſaluation. Defend me from the ſnares and ſubtleties of Satan, who howrely watcheth to enter
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18914:20"/>
and ouerthrow me; and vnleſſe, withſtood by thy diuine hand, how can ſo poore a Worme reſiſt ſo mightie an Enemie? Saue me, O Lord, from his Miniſter, the World, who with the glorie thereof ſeeketh to beguile and deceiue me: and let not the fleſh haue any power ouer me; which, ſuggeſted by him, layeth continuall ſiege to me, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſinnes, like fearefull Canons, before me; my owne weakeneſſe deſiring to let him in, and all my ſenſes conſpiring againſt me. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten, O Lord, to my aide; come ſpeedily, and redeeme me: let not the worke of thy hands (how meane ſoeuer) be a prey to thy ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie, who laboureth to win me from thee, and hateth me for thee; that being protected by thy out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtretched Arme, I may goe forward in goodneſſe and vertue. Giue me, O Lord, a heart full of Charitie,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18914:21"/>
Patience, Obedience, Humbleneſſe, without Malice, Vaine-glory, enuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing none, and fixe all my thoughts, actions, and endeuours, to recouer thee, in thy Kingdome; to whom be all honour, power, and glorie, world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>2.</hi> A Prayer before Dinner.</head>
                  <p>ALmightie and euerlaſting God, which haſt created all things for the good and benefit of Mankind, giuing him power and dominion ouer all thy creatures; graunt, O Lord, that I may ſo moderately vſe theſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings thou haſt in thy mercie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for me, as may ſtand with thy good liking and pleaſure: Let me eate, to helpe, not pamper Nature, leſt of a ſeruant ſhe become an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and make me vnfit for thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18914:21"/>
and glorie, which is the onely end of our creation and being: Let Temperance, not my Appetite, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſway me, euer remembring, and with dutifull thankes acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging thy loue and fauour, who haſt vouchſafed to refreſh and comfort me, when many thouſands of my poore brethren, whoſe fearefull ſinnes call not for vengeance like mine, ſuffer vnder the Tyrannie of Hunger: Giue me grace (O Lord) to pitie them, and meanes to relieue them, that we may together glorifie thee in thy Workes, and prayſe thy Iudgements, which are vnſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, ſhewing mercie on whom thou pleaſeſt, chaſtiſing thy children, that being made obedient in their puniſhments, they may come to thee, and be made partakers of that neuer-ending glorie, which thou haſt prepared for thoſe that truly ſerue thee, euen for Ieſus Chriſt his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18914:22"/>
ſake, our onely Lord and Sauiour who with thee and the holy Ghoſt, three perſons, and one God, liueth and raigneth world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="evening_prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>3.</hi> Euening Prayer.</head>
                  <p>MOſt mercifull and louing God, Father of all Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, who in thy infinite wiſedome and prouidence haſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained the night for reſt, by which our bodily ſences, wearied with the dayes labour, might be renewed and refreſhed; wee prayſe and glorifie thy holy Name, in that thou haſt vouchſafed, of thy accuſtomed bountie and goodneſſe, to protect vs from all the bodily dangers of this day, which our Enemie, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, practiſeth for our deſtruction. How many, O pitifull and ſweet Sauiour, hath his ſnares betrayed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18914:22"/>
and vndone, leading them by temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and ſtrong perſwaſion, with their owne hands to be their owne Murtherers? How many haſt thou ſuffered to fall by fire? ſome, by the crueltie of their Brother, Fathers by their Children, Wiues by their Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, ſuddenly, and vnexpectedly, in apparent danger, without thy mercie and benediction, of eternall woe and damnation. How ſhall a heart, loaden and ouercome with theſe thy benefits, expreſſe thy pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and glorie, with his owne ſhame and opprobriouſneſſe? I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and confeſſe (moſt bleſſed and pitifull Lord) that my ſinnes dayly encreaſing, nay howrely growing vpon me, haue deſerued Hell fire, and euerlaſting damnation: I haue knowne thy Commandements, and not followed them; I haue hearke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to thy will, and not obeyed it, purſuing with ſwift feet the vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18914:23"/>
deſires and luſts of my fleſh Giue me grace, O mercifull Lord and Father, that I may with all the power of my ſoule ſtriue and ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to amend and reforme this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and abominable courſe. Be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to call me vnto thee, by what meanes ſoeuer thou ſhalt thinke my vnbridled and ſtubborne diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will be tamed and ſubdued: I refuſe no puniſhment, without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of greatneſſe, or choice of qualitie; Pouertie ſent by thee, ſhall be my chiefeſt Riches; Shame and Contempt, being thy affliction, ſhall be the propagation of my glorie; the neglect of Friends ſhall not trouble me; for in all things, O Lord, let thy will be done, who wiſheth not the death of a ſinner, but that he may repent and liue with thee, in the companie of Angels and Saints, who are filled with thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and continually ſing thy pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18914:23"/>
to whom onely belongeth iuſt prayſe and honour, world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Tuesday" type="day">
               <head>TVESDAY.</head>
               <div n="4" type="morning_prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>4.</hi> Morning Prayer.</head>
                  <p>O Almightie and moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Father, which haſt ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the eyes of thy ſeruant to behold thy glorious and wonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous workes, ſending thy bleſſed and comfortable Light, to baniſh and put to flight the thick and black darkneſſe which couered the face of the Earth; lighten, O Lord, my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, that I may ſee thee in thy reuealed will, and not curiouſly wander farther. Giue me grace to know what is good, and rectifie my will to follow it, that in my life and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18914:24"/>
conuerſation I may glorifie thee and profit others.</p>
                  <p>I confeſſe, O Lord, and humbly acknowledge my ſinnes and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and my tranſgreſſions are euer before me: Pardon, O mercifull Father, and be pleaſed to put away from thy remembrance all my ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities: Let the bloud of thy deare Sonne, and my onely Sauiour, be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileable againſt thy Iuſtice, and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie my miſdeedes in his Sepulchre, that they may neuer riſe vp againſt me.</p>
                  <p>Bleſſe, O mightie and only pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull God, all the labours of this day, and graunt, thou wilt helpe vs to performe what is thy pleaſure wee doe, that euerie ſpeech and action hauing his beginning from thee, may tend to our owne comfort and ſaluation. Let not, O Lord (which art the comfort and ſuccour of all diſtreſſed and afflicted) the greedie
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18914:24"/>
and vnlawfull deſire of gaine and encreaſe, rayſe our hearts to affect falſehood and diſſimulation: Set a watch, O Lord, before our lippes, that wee may ſpeake truly to euery man; in the vprightneſſe and ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of a good conſcience, wee may be at peace with our ſelues.</p>
                  <p>Set ouer vs, thou great and onely Protector, thy holy Angell, to guard and defend vs, that the Deuill, who lyeth in wait to betray vs, may be put to flight and confounded: either take away, O Lord, or giue vs ſtrength to ouercome his ſubtleties and temptations, that endeuouring to ſpend this day according to thy holy Word, wee may reſt in peace, till thou againe ſhalt call vs to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme our dutie; euen for Ieſus Chriſts ſake, our onely Lord and Sauiour.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="midday_prayer">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:18914:25"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>5.</hi> A Prayer at Noone.</head>
                  <p>I Will not ceaſe to crie vnto thee, O Lord, becauſe thou art merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and regardeſt the complaints of thy ſeruant; who, as in a Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, encompaſſed with rauenous beaſts, were it not for thy aſſiſting grace, looketh inſtantly to be deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. My fleſh rebelleth againſt me, and my vnbridled and lawleſſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces would giue me vp as a prey vnto the enemie. Be neere, O Lord, vnto me, and aſſiſt me in the Conflict, leſt I ſhamefully fall, and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded.</p>
                  <p>Inſpire me, O Lord, with vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and holy motions, vnreſiſtable and neuer-yeelding graces, that I may fight manfully vnder thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Standard, following thee, my Captaine and Leader, thorow all
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18914:25"/>
the dangerous and fearefull oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which Satan bringeth againſt me. Giue me, O Lord, an vnwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried courage, that I may neyther faint vnder the heat of my deſires, nor be dulled and benummed with the cold and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>tie careleſneſſe of my lazie and luke-warme deuotion; but with able and luſtie vigor ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming the World, the Fleſh, and the Deuill, I may in ſpirit reioyce with thee, and ſing thy prayſes and glorie, who art the onely bleſſed and gracious Redeemer from all tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and troubles.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="evening_prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>6.</hi> Euening Prayer.</head>
                  <p>O Moſt mercifully louing God, who gathereſt and keepeſt thy beloued vnder thy wings, as the Henne doth her Chickens, defending them by thy
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18914:26"/>
mightineſſe from all the perils and misfortunes which their weakeneſſe and the Deuils ſuggeſtions might bring vpon them. I giue thee moſt humble and heartie thankes, that thou haſt ſafely protected me this day from all bodily dangers and miſchances, from the crueltie of Fire, the mercileſneſſe of Water, the rage of the Sword, the ſpoyle of Sickneſſe, and the vnſparing hand of Death, which hath ſuddenly and vnexpectedly ouertaken many, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and rioting. But now, O Lord, and aboue meaſure, am I to glorifie and prayſe thy euerlaſting goodneſſe, that with thy aſſiſting grace thou haſt bleſſed me from horrible ſinnes and tranſgreſſions, crying vnto thee for Iudgement; Inceſt committed with the neereſt of our bloud, and remoteſt from the bloud of our Sauiour; Murther of mans bodie, with the ſlaughter
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18914:26"/>
of our owne ſoule; Rape of Virgins, with the deflowring of our owne vertue; and many other offences, which thou (vnknowingly) haſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from vs, deliuering vs from the occaſions, which hanging ouer vs, were (vnperceiued) readie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure vs.</p>
                  <p>Continue, O Lord, thy louing kindneſſe, and in the darkeneſſe of this Night ſhoot forth thy beames into our ſoules, that wee may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly behold and meditate vpon thy neuer-ending mercies: Ouer-ſhadow vs with a companie of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, who may watch and guard our ſleeping bodies, leſt the Deuill enter and vnawares ſurprize vs. Keepe from vs, O Lord, all wanton and laſciuious dreames, vaine and idle fancies, that hauing peaceably and quietly obtained an vntroubled and vnpolluted Repoſe, wee may awake in thy feare, to remember all thy
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18914:27"/>
kindneſſes, employing both ſoule and bodie to doe him homage and ſeruice, by whoſe mightie and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing power wee haue enioyed them ſafe, from the oppoſitions of all our enemies.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Wednesday" type="day">
               <head>WEDNESDAY.</head>
               <div n="7" type="morning_prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>7.</hi> Morning Prayer.</head>
                  <p>ALmightie and euer-liuing God, the firſt Beginner, Mouer, and Creator of all things being, I render thy diuine Maieſtie humble and heartie thanks for the quiet Repoſe and Reſt of the paſſed Night; humbly entreating thee, of thy fauour and goodneſſe; by thy holy direction and aſſiſtance, to gouerne and commaund all the actions of this day, that they may
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18914:27"/>
bring forth a Comfort, and Repoſe of a good Conſcience. Giue, O Lord, vnto me thoughts pure and vndefiled, beſeeming the preſence of ſo great and holy a Maieſtie, before whom I continually ſtand; ſpeeches ſparing and modeſt, with the conſideration of an account to be made for them, that my actions ariſing from theſe, may be a warrane to me in the peace of a ſettled mind, a profitable example to my weake brethren, and a neuer-ending glorie and honour to thee, whoſe worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip I am. Take from me, O bleſſed and carefull Father, the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of ſinne, and the oportunitie of committing them: Let no euill companie (the Nets of Satan) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare my weake and fraile determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, ſeducing me by wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or the deſire of vaine-glorie, or what other ſecondarie cauſe ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18914:29"/>
to the forgetting thee, and my owne dutie and ſaluation. Giue me grace and ſtrength, O bleſſed and all louing Creator, to labour in the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation thou haſt ordained for me, and bleſſe, O Lord, the labours of my hand, that I may ſee the comfort and encreaſe of them; for which, let thy holy and euer-comforting Spirit inflame me with a burning deſire of thankfulneſſe, and humble acknowledgement, that I may not loſe thee, for not prayſing, honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and adoring thy holy Name; to vvhich, bee aſcribed all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glorie, world without end.</p>
               </div>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:18914:29"/>
               <div n="8" type="midday_prayer">
                  <head>NOONE.</head>
                  <head>
                     <hi>8.</hi> A Prayer, or Meditation, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging Gods benefits: with an humble Confeſsion of our ſinnes.</head>
                  <p>WHat is Man, O Lord, that thou doeſt ſo much reſpect him? Or the Sonne of Man, that thou giueſt heed vnto him? Why haſt thou ſent thy onely Begotten, who in glorie excelleth all Creatures, to be a Sacrifice for him, and giuen thy Angels charge ouer him? Why hath thy owne hand conducted him, and Miracles made way for him? Is he not, O Lord, ſlime of the Earth, created of nothing, and without thy mercie, ſhould be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie to returne to nothing? Was he
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18914:28"/>
able to helpe thee, when he had no being in thy great Workemanſhip? Or when it was made; vvithout thee, could he diſtinguiſh it? Was he not laſt formed, and all other things for his vſe and ſeruice? And in requitall of all this thy exceeding and infinite bountie, did hee not leaue thee, his onely God and Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and take part with thy enemie againſt thee? And haſt thou yet ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered him to thee, and by thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed Will left him thine heire of all thoſe glorious Poſſeſſions, whoſe Title cannot be queſtioned? Thoſe ineſtimable Riches, which neither Theeues nor Moths can beguile him of, or take away? What ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie is there, O mercifull Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in this thy handy worke, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue ſuch innumerable and vn-imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table benefits? What can hee, O Lord, repay thee for theſe great and vnſpeakable bounties? What
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18914:28"/>
proportion can there be of a finite vncertainetie, with an euerlaſting and infinite Deitie? With what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable, and vnconceiuable Art, doeſt thou faſhion him in the Wombe? How wonderfully, and ſtrangely, doeſt thou bring him forth? How carefully after, and moſt louingly, doeſt thou cheriſh and ſuccour him, his Parents being thy Nurſes; in whom thou haſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired ſuch Nature and Loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, that they account and call that Trouble, a Bleſſing? How moſt prouidently, for this deſpiſed Clay, didſt thou, in the beginning, diuide the great Time, diſpoſing the one halfe for the Reſt and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of this thy Creature, rocking him aſleepe with thy all-powerfull and fauourable hand? And when he comes, in progreſſe of time, to exerciſe and vſe that Reaſon and Vnderſtanding, in which thou haſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18914:30"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:18914:30"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:18914:31"/>
made him lord ouer all thy Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; what, O Father of all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts and Bleſſings, doth he returne thee for this thy care and bleſſings? How does he, in part, and to his power, anſwere theſe thy exceeding great and high benefits? Doth he walke in the Way which thou haſt inſtructed him? Or is his delight in ſeeking after thy Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? Doth he not leaue the knowne Path, reuealed in thy Word, and wander after Vanities, ſearching for their footſteps, which lead vnto deſtruction? O all mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull and louing God, whoſe Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and Bountie doth well expreſſe thy Godhead and Power! ſince it is not in Mortalitie to loue ſo abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, ſo feruently: ſo, cauſeleſſely, graunt, I beſeech thee, euen for the bowels of thy mercie, to inflame my heart with the like deſires and affections, that I may loue thee aboue
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18914:31"/>
my ſelfe, with all my ſoule, with all my heart, all my vnderſtanding; deſpiſing all things, in reſpect of thee: ſince there is nothing great, glorious, and high, nothing of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Beautie, euerlaſting Maieſtie, vnſpeakable Charitie, but God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone; who hath filled euery thing with his Bleſſing, with his Being, with his Preſence; who confines all things, without being confined; who is, was, and euer ſhall be, of endleſſe power, honour, and glorie. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="evening_prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>9.</hi> Euening Prayer.</head>
                  <p>LEt me neuer be vnthankfull, O Lord, that thou haſt yet continued thy fauourable and commanding hand ouer me, in placing me before thee, reſeruing me, and redeeming me from the continuall aſſaults of Satan, who
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18914:32"/>
awaiteth to make a prey on me: mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully, O Lord, forgiue the euill which I haue committed; and the good which I haue had meanes to lay hold of, and ouerſlipped, be pleaſed not to remember againſt me, who am nothing but pollution and vncleaneneſſe, vncapable, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thee, of goodneſſe, and vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, by my owne negligence and careleſneſſe to be called vnto it. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue, O Lord, my cuſtomarie and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious taking thy Name in vaine, my wandering and idle ſpeeches, pride of my ſelfe, or towards others detraction, for my owne glorie; Enuie, or whatſoeuer, in thought, word, or deed, this day committed; diſpleaſeth thy diuine Maieſtie; that my ſoule, vnloaded and vnburde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the deadly and condemning weights of ſinne, may comfortably take the refreſhing of this Night, thou in thy mercie haſt ordained
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18914:32"/>
for me, euen for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, thy onely and well-beloued Sonne, and our onely Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Thursday" type="day">
               <head>THVRSDAY.</head>
               <div n="10" type="morning_prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>10.</hi> Morning Prayer.</head>
                  <p>AS out of my graue, O Lord, by thy mightie hand and out-ſtretched arme, haſt thou this day called me, rayſing me from the depth of ſleepe, wherein many haue beene vnexpectedly and ſuddenly for euer buried, and called me to the beholding of thy glorious and all-comforting Light, and in that, the admirable worke of thy hand; and more eſpecially and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly, taking away the darke and thicke clouds of ſinne and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18914:33"/>
haſt illumined my inward ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit with thy mercifull beames, to thinke and meditate vpon thy holy Name and neuer-ending kindneſſes, opening with the day, my eyes, as thou didſt to <hi>Hagar,</hi> that I might be comforted in beholding (deſperate of helpe and ſuccour) the bottome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Well-ſpring of thy fauour and prouidence, wherewith thou cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheſt and maintaineſt all things crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, taking care, by thy eternall wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, of the pooreſt things in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And ſince (O Lord) one haire cannot fall from the head, without thy fore-ſeeing knowledge, merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and louingly ſuſtaine and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold me this day, and euer, that I ſlide not and fall from thee, the head and author of my being and well-being, without whom I was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and ſhould be happie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to nothing. Plant in me, O Lord, the timely fruit of Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18914:33"/>
and water it with thy heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dew, that ſeriouſly and carefully ſetting before my eyes the end of my Creation, the dreadfull account I muſt render, in not applying my ſelfe to it, with the glorious certaine promiſed Rewards, belonging to Goodneſſe and Vertue, I may now and euer, in all my thoughts, words, and deedes, ſo carrie and behaue my ſelfe, that I may be thought, in the precious bloud of thy onely Sonne, worthie to be made capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of that eternall Sacrifice hee hath long ſince offered for all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:18914:34"/>
               <div n="11" type="midday_prayer">
                  <head>AT NOONE.</head>
                  <head>
                     <hi>11.</hi> A Prayer or Meditation for Patience.</head>
                  <p>WHither wilt thou goe (O my Soule) to find a Patterne of all Vertues? Where wilt thou enſample this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and diuine Patience, of which thou ſtandeſt in need of? Get vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy wings, and flye to Bethleem, ſacred by the birth of our Sauiour; thence, trace him through the whole courſe of his bleſſed and innocent life, where thou ſhalt behold it ſo rarely pourtrayed and ſet forth, ſo ſweetly and modeſtly deſcribed, that thou canſt not, if thou haſt any feeling of Goodneſſe, but be ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moured with her beautie. Did euer this bleſſed and meeke Lambe, for
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18914:34"/>
all his deſpightfull and baſe vſage, grace a frowne with his Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance? Did euer an angry word dwell vpon his well-formed lippes? Did hee ſo much as rebuke thoſe which contemned him, reſiſt thoſe which buffetted him? nay, gaineſay thoſe which ſpat in his reuerend Countenance? Art thou oppreſſed with Pouertie? Conſider, that the Lord of Heauen and Earth had not wherein to hide his head. Art thou wronged with ſlanderous and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracefull Speeches? Was not this temperate, and all-vertuous Man, tearmed a Glutton and a Wine-bib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber? Doth Shame and Ignominie compaſſe thee in, on euerie ſide? See, ſee, my Soule, the King of Kings, and Lord of all Lords, who rayſed the dead to life, lying vpon the Croſſe; and he, who by his Mightineſſe and Power exalted ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to be glorious Saints, hanging
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18914:35"/>
betweene two Theeues, condemned as a foule Offendor. Marke his mild and louely Countenance, his ſober and demure Speeches, the modeſt glance of his Eyes, and the compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his whole Bodie, caſt in ſo Noble a Mould of vnconquered Patience, that they ſooner wanted occaſions to tyrannize, then he ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue meekely to ſuffer them. Here fixe thy ſelfe, kneele at the Root of the Croſſe, and with all thoſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Women, and Saints, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied him, reuerently ſay vnto him: O thou eternall and moſt bountifull Sauior, who vouchſafedſt to deſcend from the Throne of thy glorie, and putting on our fraile and weake humanitie, didſt for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of Mankind, vvander ſo many yeeres hungrie and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, contemned, and deſpiſed, ſuffering intolerable Paines and Torments, without being moued
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18914:35"/>
or troubled; graunt, I beſeech thee, by thy precious Death and Buriall, that I may willingly embrace thoſe croſſes thou pleaſeſt to lay vpon me, that I may, run to meet them, as thou didſt the betraying Kiſſe of <hi>Iudas.</hi> Giue me (O Lord) power and ſtrength, moſt meekely and patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to vndergoe and abide all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, Tribulations, Wants, Shames, Sickneſſes, Hurts, Maimes, vvithout inwardly repining, or grudging, outwardly murmuring, or ſpeaking againſt them; let me freely goe, not violently be drawne to entertaine them. Did not thy glorious Martyr and Souldier, Saint <hi>Stephen,</hi> whileſt they ſtoned him, prayſe thee, and pray for them? Could he begin this Worke, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thy grace, or finiſh it, without thy Power? No, no, my moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull and gracious Lord, it is thy Spirit which quickeneth, for the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18914:36"/>
fleſh profiteth in nothing, but repi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth againſt it. Be liberall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vnto me (O Lord) of thy ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne and precious Balme, which healeth and cureth all ſorts of Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; anoint my rancorous and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie fleſh (big-ſwolne with Malice) that the ſting being drawne out, it may appeare white and faire: let me drinke (O Lord) a large draught of this Cordiall, to confirme &amp; ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then me againſt all the poyſons and infirmities of Nature. For certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (Lord) who is perfectly patient, obeyeth thy will, and who is obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, humbleth himſelfe to all diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantagious loſſes, or what diſhonour elſe the World can inflict: Which Humilitie bringeth vs to that height and glorie, which onely they ſhall enioy, that haue patiently endured and expected this their reward to the end.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="evening" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:18914:36"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>12.</hi> Euening Prayer.</head>
                  <p>TVrne not thy face away from me (O Lord:) incline thine eare, and bow downe vnto me: Heare me for thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſake, and according to the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of thy bounties, blot out all my iniquities: for what fleſh is righteous, or who dare ſtand vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee? Doe not the Hills flye before thee, and Mountaines melt at thy indignation? Doth not the Sunne loſe his light, and the ſtarres, when thou commandeſt them, hide their glorie? Be mercifull (O Lord) and gracious to thy ſeruant, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring thy promiſe, humbly proſtrates himſelfe before thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Maieſtie, confeſſing all his ſinnes, and acknowledging all his iniquities. Remember not (O Lord)
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18914:37"/>
our offences, nor the offences of our fore-fathers, neither take thou ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of our ſinnes: for who dare abide thy Iudgements? Caſt me not away from thy face, but ſay vnto my ſoule, I am thy ſaluation. Haue mercie vpon me (O Lord) haue mercie vpon me, and let my crie come vnto thee; for my ſinnes are heauie vpon me, and threaten to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow me; yea, they ſay vnto my ſoule, Where is now thy God? Turne vnto me (O Lord) and they ſhall be turned; ſpeake vnto me, and they ſhall be ſcattered. Be vnto me a ſure Rocke in the time of my trouble, that I fall not vnder it, for I have hoped in thee: Oh forſake not thy ſeruant. Forgiue (O Lord) all the paſſed errors of this day; pardon my irreuerence in thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, my negligence at prayers, my faintneſſe in good purpoſes; and what euill I haue committed, or
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18914:37"/>
what good, through frailetie and my owne heedleſneſſe, I haue omitted, be pleaſed not to remember; euen for thy owne Names ſake, who art God moſt mightie, one, and the ſame, world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Friday" type="day">
               <head>FRIDAY.</head>
               <div n="13" type="morning_prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>13.</hi> Morning Prayer.</head>
                  <p>O Moſt mercifully louing Lord and Sauiour, the glorie and brightneſſe of thy Father, who deſcendedſt from all thy Ioyes, taking on thee humane frailetie, to recall and recouer the ſinner, and thoſe which were diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the vncurable plagues of ſinne and wickedneſſe; vouchſafe, of thy infinite goodneſſe, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable loue, to be aiding and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18914:38"/>
to me this day, and by thy might and power, defend me from all temptations, which may ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw my vnſettled, though well-directed, reſolutions. Preſerue me (O Lord) from all bodily dangers, which, without thee, continually hang ouer me, threatening my ruine and deſtruction. Make good (O Lord) to me my determinations and purpoſes, which may be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to thy holy and bleſſed inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and graunt me patience (O Lord) meekely and contentedly to ſuffer, whatſoeuer I ſhall faile or be hindered in, referring my ſelfe with all humilitie and ardencie of deſires, to thy diuine will and pleaſure; which be done (O Lord) in Earth as it is in Heauen. Take away all rancour and malicious imaginations, that I may neither by reuiling de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame my brother, or ſwell and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment my ſelfe with any diſgracings
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18914:38"/>
he ſhall lay vpon me, but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging my baſeneſſe and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as worthie of all reproches and diſhonours, calling to mind, the Seruant is not aboue his Maſter, in the comfort of thy example, who aboue the meekeneſſe of a Lambe, vnderwenteſt all kind of paines and reuilings; I may behold a timely Euening, reioycing my anger hath not awaited the Sunnes ſetting; euer endeuouring and labouring againſt my fraile concupiſcences and deſires, euen for thy holy Names ſake; Which whoſoeuer ardently and continually calleth on, ſhall not faile to obtaine vnſpeakable happineſſe and felicitie world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:18914:39"/>
               <div n="14" type="midday_prayer">
                  <head>AT NOONE.</head>
                  <head>
                     <hi>14.</hi> A Prayer to our bleſſed Sauiour, asking him forgiueneſſe for our ſinnes which cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified him.</head>
                  <p>O Bountifull Ieſu, O ſweet Ieſu, O Ieſu the Sonne of the liuing God; how dare I, wretched and deteſtable ſinner, approch before thy diuine Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie? How can I, ouercome with ſinne and ſhame, ſtay any longer in thy preſence? Did euer the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer and ſlaughterer of his Lord and Maſter preſume to offend him with his ſight, whileſt yet the wounds were freſh and bleeding, whileſt his bodie was cruelly man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled and torne, and his head with an vn-vſed crueltie pained and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18914:39"/>
tormented? leſt the ſmart and rage of his wounds, the ſhame and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour of his vſage, ſhould take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all hope and pitie of pardon, deliuering him in his furie to the Iudge, and he to the Executioner, to carrie him where is continuall wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and gnaſhing of teeth. But conſider (O my Soule) how this mercifull and meeke Sauiour beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth himſelfe towards his bloudie and tyrannous perſecutors: behold him dropping with bloud, buffetted by the wicked miniſters, ſcorned of the people, forſaken of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, hoyſted into the ayre, cruelly nayled on the Croſſe, not curſing, not reuiling, but praying, not for himſelfe, but thoſe that perſecuted him. Amongſt whom, running with the formoſt, mayeſt thou, in thy eternall Prouidence, O glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Patterne of all Sufferings, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold me, with more crueltie laying
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18914:40"/>
on thee with my ſinnes, then the ſtonie-hearted Iewes vvith their weapons, tearing thee, if it were poſſible, peece-meale with my hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible and blaſpheming Oathes; my looſe and laſciuious thoughts woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thy faire Head with more ſpight and rigour, then the ſharpe-pointed Thornes; my Malice, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, Pride, Drunkenneſſe, Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence, with innumerable other ſinnes and tranſgreſſions, flaying thy reuerend Bodie. All this (O Lord) haue I done, all this commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, knowing thee, and confeſſing thee to be Ieſus, the eternall Sonne of God, and only Redeemer of the World. Pray for me, moſt gentle and mild Lord, ſpeake for me to thy eternall Father; without which, moſt abominable and wretched ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, I ſhall for euer be condemned. Forſake me not now, O Lord, goe not away from me, but renew in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:18914:40"/>
me a cleane heart, and create a right ſpirit within me, that I may plainely ſee the deformitie of ſinne, and the ouglineſſe of my miſdeedes. Giue me grace earneſtly to ſeeke thee, and hauing found thee, ardently to loue thee; ouercome with which, I may imploy all my actions, ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, and labours, wholly to ſerue thee: which if I faithfully and truly doe, I ſhall at the end of my yeeres, hauing ſo indulgent and louing a Maſter, be made a Free-man of Heauen; and thoſe vnconceiuable Ioyes, which no eye hath ſeene, eare hath heard, or tongue can tell, they onely know them, that enioy them: Which, O benigne and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Lord, graunt all thy ſeruants to inherite, for thy holy Names ſake, which ſhall be honoured and prayſed world without end.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="evening_prayer">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:18914:41"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>15.</hi> Euening Prayer.</head>
                  <p>GRaunt me (O Lord) after the many and wild diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this day, a holy and inward recollection, that I may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne into my ſelfe, with due care and examination, how I haue ſpent and imployed my faculties of ſoule, and functions of bodie, which thou haſt lent me, for thy vſe and ſeruice; and giue vnto me a true compuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſorrowfull feeling for all the paſſed errors and tranſgreſſions of this day, that I may heartily lament and bewayle my ſinnes and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſes, with a full reſolution and conſtant determination of my a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment. And graunt me (O Lord) this Night, I beſeech thee, by thine incomprehenſible Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and Maieſtie, chaſtitie of mind,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:18914:41"/>
cleaneneſſe of heart, ſimplicitie of ſpirit, and moſt ſincere puritie of ſoule and bodie, that I may earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeeke after thee, and in thee alone take my reſt; ſince whatſoeuer is without thee, is onely vexation and trouble of mind: that hauing en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed a comfortable and peaceable Repoſe both of ſoule and bodie, I may awake with much alacritie and cheerefulneſſe of ſpirit, to prayſe and honour thee in all my workes and labours, which the following day ſhall call me to; for his onely ſake, in whom wee are enabled to exerciſe whatſoeuer is good and vertuous. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Saturday" type="day">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:18914:42"/>
               <head>SATVRDAY.</head>
               <div n="16" type="morning_prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>16.</hi> Morning Prayer.</head>
                  <p>BE mercifull vnto me, O Lord, and let thy holy hand be ouer me: Let my firſt Meditation be of thy goodneſſe, and my Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thoughts imployed about thy fatherly care and protection, which hath from my infancie ouerſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, preſeruing me from the vile and ſhamefull fires of Luſt and Rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, recalling me ſtill to a fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and diſlike of my paſſed ſinnes and offences. Rectifie (O Lord) my ſinfull will, and ſtrengthen my frailetie, that with the burning wings of filiall pietie and humble deuotion for ſo many and thoſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable gifts and graces, I may
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:18914:42"/>
flye, by prayers and thanks-giuing, to the Throne of thy Diuinitie, where fixing all my aymes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, I may change my proneneſſe and inclination to ill and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, with vertuous and feruent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of louing and honouring thee for thy ſelfe, who art onely and all goodneſſe, without the reſpect of my dependance or being from thee; that reuerencing thy greatneſſe, and rauiſhed with thy goodneſſe, I may, with a loue full of awe and feare, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chew thoſe wayes which may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe thee; euer carefuller of thy anger, then my owne hurt or diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage: to which height of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, graunt me (O Lord) to attaine, for the merits of thy onely Sonne, who alone is able to deſerue ſo infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite a bleſſing for ſo infinite and vile a ſinner. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:18914:43"/>
               <div n="17" type="midday_prayer">
                  <head>AT NOONE.</head>
                  <head>
                     <hi>17.</hi> A Prayer againſt Drunkenneſſe.</head>
                  <p>GIue to me the water of Life, (O Lord) and I ſhall neuer thirſt; but ſay the word, and I ſhall be ſatisfied. Send downe thy heauenly dew, to aſſwage and coole my diſordered and vnlimitted deſires, whoſe burning heat and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging fire runnes me into ſinne and exceſſe. In vaine haue I laboured, without thee, to ſtay my intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; in vaine oppoſed my ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my wild and lawleſſe ſences. Strengthen (O Lord) my weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and confirme me againſt the temptations of the Deuill; who fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a breach in me, hath entred and made prey, baniſhing all things good and vertuous, which thou haſt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18914:43"/>
placed to keepe me, and hath peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled me with ſtrong and ſinfull thoughts, mortall and well-armed Offences, who dare iuſtifie their Rapine and Extortion, Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Whoredome, readily commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting more ſinnes, then I haue names to cloath them in. Haſten (O Lord) and helpe me, for I am wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of their tyrannie; caſt them out of me, and plant thy grace, that they returne not, and multiplie. Whole Dayes haue I pleaſed my ſelfe in diſpleaſing thee, and broken many Nights to breake thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements; ſore longing for their companie, whoſe feet run to Iniquitie; abuſing thy Creature, prouided by thy care and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for the refreſhing and ſuſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of our naturall bodies, to our ruine, and without thy great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, vtter damnation. Did not thy ſeruant <hi>Lot</hi> (O Lord) a iuſt and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18914:44"/>
righteous man, in his drinke abuſe his owne Daughter? What ſinne hath Hell in ſtore ſo horrid, that it dare not act, and glorie of the deed? O moſt mercifully louing Lord and Father, who deſireſt not the death of a ſinner, but rather that he ſhould liue and repent; I requeſt thee, by the bowels of thy Mercie, thy bitter precious Paſſion, thy glorious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection and Aſcenſion, thou wilt take away from me this Monſter and Hell-borne wickedneſſe, which hath ſubtilly perſwaded me to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thee, my Lord and Maker, and ſtealingly ſurprized me, and giuen me vp to all manner of ſinnes and tranſgreſſions, taking away all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, blinding the ſences, that being wholly in his power, he might car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie me headlong to all perdition. Preſerue me (O Lord) by thy might and power, from all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which may bring me to him,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:18914:44"/>
for I am fearefull of him, and dare not, without thy gracious aſſiſtance and mercie, endure his ſlye and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull perſwaſions. No age is war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted from him, hee adulterateth both ſexes, he vnſanctifieth the moſt religious, and creepeth into the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uateſt and moſt retired places, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching all ſorts with his cunning and alluring charmes. Stand, O my Redeemer, at the gates of my eares, and ſhut out all his faire-ſeeming treaties, which would conclude a peace betweene my frailetie and the Deuill. Cleare (O Lord) my eyes, and take away the myſt from them, that I may plainely ſee and perceiue his ouglineſſe and deformitie, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in beaſtlineſſe and ſenſuali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: mercifully touch my heart with thy illumining Spirit, that I may hate and deteſt him, ſhun his friends and companions, and flye from the place of his abode and entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:18914:45"/>
within whoſe Circle, no ſoule is ſafe, no thought pure, no ſence perfect. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="evening_prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>18.</hi> Euening Prayer.</head>
                  <p>LAy thy bleſſed hands vpon me (O Lord) as thou didſt on thy ſeruant <hi>Lot,</hi> delaying his owne ſafetie, and conduct me out of this ſinfull and euerie-way polluted Sodome, that I may quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly flye from it, leſt vnquenchable fire and brimſtone ouertake me, whileſt I protract and refuſe thy heauenly inſpirations. Let no day paſſe me, without ſome progreſſe in goodneſſe and vertue: and euerie houre, O mercifull Father, graunt I may determine a full amendment and deteſtation of my former lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and miſſe-ſpent behauiour. Let me account my ſelfe an vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:18914:45"/>
Scholler, when I haue not learnt and aſpired to ſome higher meaſure of vnderſtanding thee; an vnthriftie and riotous worldling, when I haue not gathered and laid vp ſomewhat to maintaine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend me in the day of trouble. Touch (O Lord) my heart with thy heauenly Spirit, that I may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme this life, in his full value, onely a Pilgrimage and Thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare to another Land, where I muſt truly liue for euer; and accordingly deſpiſing all the lets and hinderan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, be neither tempted with the gawdie pleaſures, nor terrified with the rough paſſages of my Iourney; but in thy holy feare making way through them, I may at laſt arriue to thee, the promiſed Land, where euer-continuing and flouriſhing content and happineſſe abideth. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Sunday" type="day">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:18914:46"/>
               <head>SVNDAY.</head>
               <div n="19" type="morning_prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>19.</hi> Morning Prayer.</head>
                  <p>O My moſt mercifull Lord and Redeemer, how ſhall a guiltie and ſinfull ſoule ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the preſence of an inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and vnſpotted Deitie? or what hope of Pitie, or Pardon, when he ſhall be my Iudge, who may onely accuſe me; bearing about him wide and gaſtly wounds, which my ſinnes haue giuen him; by which his moſt glorious Paſſion, and admirable Reſurrection, he as this day finiſhed that great and neuer to be forgotten benefit of the Redemption of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; which I, as much as in me lyeth, by my horrid and abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble luſt and deſire, haue ſought to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:18914:46"/>
fruſtrate and annihilate? Who ſhall take me from his Iuſtice, or reſcue me from his Omnipotencie? I haue ſinned (O Lord) I haue ſinned, and am no more worthie to be called thine: I haue riſen with the Sunne to meditate on vanities, and all the day long haue I followed my owne wayes; at the going downe of the ſame, I haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten thy Bleſſings, and ſate in darkeneſſe, without remembring thee, the Light and Guide of thoſe that goe aſtray; I haue forgotten thy Lawes, and thy Statutes haue beene farre from me; my thoughts haue beene buſied in vncleaneneſſe, and my lippes acquainted with lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and vaine ſtories. O be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull vnto me, and enter not into Iudgement with thy ſeruant: for how ſhall Duſt and Aſhes ſtand vp before thee? or the worke of thy hands contend with his Creator?
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18914:47"/>
Haue pitie on me (O Lord) accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy great goodneſſe, and in the multitude of thy mercies, blot out all my Iniquities. Saue me, and be neere vnto me in the day of trouble, that I may magnifie thy Name, and giue all honour, power, and glorie to thee, who art the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Fountaine of all comfort and conſolation. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="midday_prayer">
                  <head>AT NOONE.</head>
                  <head>
                     <hi>20.</hi> A Prayer concerning the benefit of Creation.</head>
                  <p>I Am amazed (O Lord) to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of thy wonderfull mercie: my ſoule is loſt in the depth of thy neuer-ceaſing goodneſſe; and like the wiſeſt of Philoſophers, the more I learne, the leſſe I may truly profeſſe to know; ſo bottomeleſſe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:18914:47"/>
and vnſearchable is thy loue and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour. When I was Nothing (O Lord) why thoughtſt thou of me, and calledſt me to be Something? which, hauing any ſubſiſtence of Beaſt, or Plant, is better then not to be at all: but thou haſt created me according to thine owne Image, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing me a reaſonable ſoule, like the Angels, endued with noble faculties and powers, enabling me to reach the height of thy myſticall Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and diuine Myſterie, and made me capable of euerlaſting and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite glorie. O Lord, before thee, and in compariſon of thy Maieſtie, I am iuſt Nothing; and how waſt thou then mindfull of me, to create me? Alas, my ſoule, thou waſt hidden in the Abyſſe of Nothing, and in this Abyſſe of Nothing ſhouldſt thou haue remained vntill this preſent, if God had not drawne thee forth from thence: and what
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:18914:48"/>
couldſt thou haue done within this Nothing? O my great and good Creator, how infinitely am I indeb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto thee; for that thou haſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken me out of this Nothing, to make me, by thy mercie, that ſomething which I am? What ſhall I euer be able to doe, worthily to bleſſe and magnifie thy Name, and to render thankes to thine exceeding Bountie? But alas, my Creator, in ſtead of vniting my ſelfe vnto thee by pure loue and loyall ſeruice, I haue alwayes beene rebellious, by vnruly affections ſeparating and withdrawing my ſelfe from thee, to ioyne and vnite my ſelfe vnto ſinne and iniquitie; doing no more to thy Goodneſſe, then if thou hadſt not beene my Creator. What wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath there beene (O Lord) that I haue not had a thought rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to put in, a mind apt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triue, and a hand willing to execute
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:18914:48"/>
it? Wherein haue I teſtified my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, in following thy Lawes and Precepts? Wherein my truth and loyaltie, in reſiſting thy vowed and knowne enemies? But, O my ſoule, know that our Lord is thy God, it is he that hath made thee, and not thou thy ſelfe. O God, I am the worke of thy hand; I will then no more henceforth take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in my ſelfe, ſince in my ſelfe, and of my ſelfe, I am truly No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Bleſſe thy God, O my ſoule, and let all thy bowels prayſe his holy Name; for his Bountie hath drawne me forth of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſſe of Nothing, and his Mercie hath created me. O my God, I offer vnto thee, with all my heart, the eſſence and being which thou of thy Bountie haſt beſtowed vpon me, and moſt willingly doe I dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and conſecrate it to thee. O my God, ſtrengthen me in theſe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:18914:49"/>
affections and reſolutions, and giue me perſeuerance to the end.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="evening_prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>21.</hi> Euening Prayer.</head>
                  <p>I Humbly confeſſe and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, O mercifull Lord and Sauiour, that I haue not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed and beſtowed the bleſſed Time of this hallowed Day, ſo deuoutly and religiouſly as I ought and am commanded to doe; I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, of thy infinite mercie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to forgiue and pardon ſo weake and frayle a Creature, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not entertaine the leaſt good thought one moment, vvithout thee; and vouchſafe, of thy accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed goodneſſe and clemencie, continually to viſit, nay, my moſt bleſſed Sauiour, to inhabite and dwell with mee, that ſo I may doe the things which pleaſe thee.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:18914:49"/>
Giue vnto me (O Lord) a kindly relenting, and remorſe for the ſinnes I haue this day committed againſt thy diuine Maieſtie, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my Neighbour, by thought, word, and deed, and by omiſſion of thoſe things thou haſt left me in charge to haue done. Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate (O Lord) my ſleepe, and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh from me all vaine and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering fancies, vncleane and idle illuſions, that I may awake in thee, and to thee offer my Morning thoughts, who art onely worthie of all; that onely haſt created, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, ſanctified, and preſerued me; for which, be thou euer prayſed and honoured world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayers_for_other_occasions">
               <div n="22" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:18914:50"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>22.</hi> A Prayer to our bleſſed Sauiour and Redeemer.</head>
                  <p>PRoſtrate thy ſelfe, O my ſoule, before the Lord of all Maieſtie and Glorie, ſitting at the right hand of his Father, crowned with Mightineſſe and Power, richly adorned with a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land of all Vertues, brightly ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, in the companie of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Angels, holy Saints, and blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die Martyrs, honouring and ſeruing him without ceaſing, or intermiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſinging Hymnes of his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Mercie: and hauing thus beheld him in this great Pompe and Triumph, caſt thine eye vpon this bleſſed Sauiour, poorely lying in the Manger, hauing ſcarce any thing to couer his tender and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Bodie, or ſaue it from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:18914:50"/>
of the Ayre: Conſider well and ſeriouſly, how he which giueth heat and motion to the Sunne, is here contented (as vnable to helpe himſelfe) to take warmth and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from the breath of the Beaſts, whom he there diſdained not to be his Chamber-fellowes. O wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full example of all humilitie! How dareſt thou from henceforth, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned Duſt and Aſhes, ſwell in thy Vaine-glorie; and decked with a few gay Ragges, forget thy Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, who is cloathed with Eternitie? Humble (O Lord) my high and proud thoughts, abaſe and bring downe my loftie and rebellious imaginations, make me abiect in my owne eyes, that walking with my poore Brethren (who wander naked and hungrie, lying vpon the bare &amp; cold Earth) I may with them prayſe and glorifie thy holy Name, who wert the firſt founder and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginner
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:18914:51"/>
of this poore and contemned Order. Why ſhall we, from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, ſo highly eſteeme Honour and Riches, when thou, the Lord of both, didſt ſo contemne it; volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie, for our inſtruction, ſubmitting thy ſelfe to ſo great and miſerable Pouertie? Happie are wee, if wee be diſtreſſed, and patiently ſuffer it; happie, if wee be contemned and neglected for thy ſake. Teach me, O Lord, the way to deſpiſe all worldly preferment and promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that hauing my thoughts only fixed vpon thee, I may paſſe forth theſe tranſitorie &amp; ſhort miſeries, to dwell in eternall reſt and felicitie in thy Kingdome, which is promiſed to all thoſe which ſerue thee; to whom be aſcribed all honor, power, and glorie, world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:18914:51"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>23.</hi> Another Prayer for aſsiſtance in dangers and troubles.</head>
                  <p>COmplayneſt thou, diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented and vngratefull Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that thy enemies lye in wait to take thy life from thee, and thinkeſt thy ſelfe not well dealt with, to be ſo perſecuted and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, when thou mayeſt behold the Creator of Heauen and Earth hauing no piece of Earth to abide with ſafetie in? Doeſt thou value thy ſelfe aboue thy Maker? and canſt wiſh a ſhare in his Glories, but to be no partner with him in his Troubles? O bleſſed Sauiour, is it not thy owne ſaying, that who will enioy thee, muſt take vp his Croſſe, and follow thee? How ſtrictly liued thy fore-runner? how impriſoned? how died? how
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:18914:52"/>
poorely, and dangerouſly, thy followers glorifying thee in hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, in ſtripes, in death? Crowne me (O Lord) in this life with Thornes, that I may hereafter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a Crowne of Glorie: Let me be here impriſoned, ſcourged, and reuiled, ſo I may be hereafter releaſed, acknowledged, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: And graunt, moſt mercifull and louing Redeemer, that as thou didſt in thy Godhead ſhew vs the fraileties of Man in thy Suffering, ſo thou wouldſt in our Manhood ſhew vs the power of thy God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, manfully to reſiſt and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all feare of Dangers, nay, Death it ſelfe, which Satan and our weake fleſh painteth out ſo hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible to vs, that cowardly flying the Combate, wee may loſe the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Reward. Strengthen vs (O Lord) and be vnto vs a ſure ſhield in the day of Battaile: Let the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:18914:52"/>
fight for vs, and ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues mightie in the deſtruction of our enemies: Let them be ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as Chaffe before the Wind, and not be able to ſtand in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition with thy ſeruants, who put their truſt in thee. Let them (O Lord) be ruined and confounded, that wiſh euill to them that feare thee, and deſire to be perfect imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators of thy life and doctrine, that wee remaining Conquerors, may prayſe and glorifie thee, the giuer of all Victorie. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>24.</hi> A Prayer againſt Pride.</head>
                  <p>DId Almightie God, who is iealous of his Honour, throw downe the Heauens for their Preſumption? and thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thou, fond Man, he will exalt baſe Earth for his Pride? Doth he
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:18914:53"/>
pull downe the mightie and the lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and aduance the humble and meeke, and dareſt thou yet reare vp thy proud head in his preſence? Was not the great King <hi>Nabucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donozor</hi> turned for his arrogancie into a Beaſt, for that in the ſhape of a Man hee liued like a Beaſt? And did not the Wormes feede vpon <hi>Herod,</hi> vn-coffind, and aliue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he did proudly aduance him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of his naturall gifts and graces? Who dare contend with the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, which darteth Lightning; and holdeth Thunder? Or what canſt thou boaſt of, preſumptuous fleſh, that is thine owne? Thy ſoule is heauenly, thy bodie earthly, both from God; the one inſpired, the other faſhioned in the Wombe, lent thee for a ſeaſon, and to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called at his pleaſure. Why doeſt thou therefore lay vp Honours and Preferments for many yeeres? Why
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:18914:53"/>
doeſt thou purſue and ſearch for glorious Armes and Titles, forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thy Father <hi>Adam,</hi> becauſe a Gardener, and deriuing thy Pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree from ſome great and Noble Conqueror; hauing not certainely ſo much time here, as the Herald muſt neceſſarily require to perfect thy gawdie Coat: For this Night may God ſay vnto thee; O foole, thy ſoule ſhall be taken from thee? Let me not therefore, O mercifull Father, come vnprepared, like the fooliſh Virgins, and be ſhut out, hauing ouer-ſlept my houre: Giue me grace to repent, whileſt there is time; for in Death, who acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thee? or who findeth pardon in Hell? Graunt, that I may ſeriouſly ponder and conſider thy manifold and manifeſt benefites, that I may with all humilitie and thankfulneſſe prayſe and glorifie the giuer. Lay before me the haynouſneſſe and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:18914:54"/>
multitude of my offences, that ſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken downe with ſhame and ſorrow, I may fall at thy feet, and with the abundance of my teares waſh away the ſtayne and guilt of my aſpiring ſoule. Let the greedineſſe of my Ambition ſatisfie it ſelfe in ſeruing of thee, being the higheſt Honour the Earth can glorie of: and when it euidently perceiues, how little of his owne it is able to bring, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge thoſe offices which are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily required, my towring thoughts will fall, and breake their owne necke. Endue me (O Lord) with ſpirituall knowledge and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, to retyre into my ſelfe, and take a ſuruey of my owne ſoule, how ſhee is garniſhed, how decked, with what vertues adorned, with what heauenly gifts and graces ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrelled; and let me be confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and aſhamed, to find her, the Miſtreſſe and Queene of this frayle
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:18914:54"/>
and corrupted bodie, naked, or worſe apparrelled, and to imploy all my ſtudie and endeuours to gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh and ſet out her ſeruant. Let ſelfe-baſeneſſe (O Lord) attained by a certaine knowledge of my weakeneſſe and vnworthineſſe, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh away all ſelfe-affection, vainely gotten by a falſe conceit of my owne graces. Health, vigour, ſtrength, and luſtineſſe of bodie thou giueſt, and takeſt away at thy pleaſure, by ſickneſſe, hunger, wants, and torments; Proportion, and Beautie, but thy all-making Hand, who can to the life faſhion; which are ſpoyled and defaced by Age, the neceſſarie ſeruant of Time, and Decrepitneſſe, the diligent fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower of Age? Be it therefore farre from me to glorie, but in the Croſſe of my Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt: Let me take pride in his Sufferings, and boaſt of his Wounds, whoſe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:18914:55"/>
precious bloud hath conquered Hell and Sinne, leading Captiuitie captiue, and redeeming the loſt Sheepe, reducing them againe to their louing and carefull Shepheard; who will recall them wandering, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold them ſliding, and ſaue them e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally from the rauening Wolfe, which goeth about roaring, to ſeeke who he may deuoure.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>25.</hi> A Prayer againſt the concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of the fleſh.</head>
                  <p>WHo ſhall enter into thy Tabernacle, O Lord? Hee that hath vndefiled hands, and a pure heart, ſanctified and vnpolluted members, as worthie Veſſels to receiue the holy Ghoſt: The houſe muſt be cleane ſwept by Confeſſion, purified and perfumed by good purpoſes and prayers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:18914:55"/>
it can be made a fit habitation for our Lord and Sauiour. Thoſe be the ſweet-ſmelling ſauors, which laid vpon the Altar of our heart, enflamed and ſet on fire by perfect Charitie, are acceptable Sacrifices vnto him. Were not the people (O Lord) commanded by thy Seruant and Prophet <hi>Moſes,</hi> to put off their ſhooes, becauſe the ground where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they trod was holy? How ſhall they enter then before thee, whoſe feet are ſwift to defile their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Bed, whoſe hands haue beene employed in rauiſhing young Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, and whoſe tongues haue ſpent all their force and Oratorie, to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and betray honeſt thoughts to wicked and looſe deſires? Didſt thou ſo ſeuerely rebuke and puniſh thy Seruant <hi>Dauid</hi> (a man, as the Scripture teſtifieth, according to thy owne heart) for one Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that neither his Contrition,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:18914:56"/>
Penance, Faſting, Almes-deedes, could diuert or turne away thy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger? And ſhall I, miſerable and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prous ſinner, who haue all my life worne my heart in my eyes, luſting after euery obiect, hope to eſcape thy furie? What Woman haue I not coueted? What Complexion hath not beene the fuell of my lewd thoughts? Pardon, O mercifull Lord and Sauiour, an humble and penitent ſinner, who confeſſeth and acknowledgeth his hainous ſinnes and offences, and much ſorroweth and lamenteth to haue miſ-imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his time and bodie in the laſciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous acts and concupiſcences of the fleſh; infinitely deſiring thee, of thy grace and fauour, to cleanſe and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie my polluted and vncleane ſoule, knowing, that no Adulterers or Fornicators ſhall inherite thy Kingdome. Giue vnto me (O Lord) ſpotleſſe and innocent Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:18914:56"/>
being the Lilly among all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, whoſe ſparkling luſtre is ſeene a farre off. Bridle with thy holy hand, all wanton and looſe deſires, which runne after their owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. Let the delight of mine eyes bee thy miraculous Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: the obiect of mine eares, the ſtory of thy Paſſion: the ſubiect of my thoughts, the remembrance of the Croſſe: the foode of my vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, thy wonderfull and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceiueable Conception. Let mee with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Thomas</hi> thruſt my fingers in thy wounds; that all faculties and functions of body and ſoule, beeing buſied and employed, in and about thy workes and wonders, I may bee deliuered, and bring foorth holy thoughts, reuerent and gentle ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, pure and immaculate actions, worthy the honour and glory of ſo pure and innocent a Lord, borne of a ſpotleſſe and immaculate Virgin.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:18914:57"/>
Grant this, O ſweet Ieſus, the beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of all goodnes, and vertue, that deſiring to draw out this ſhort and tranſitorie life, purely and honeſtly, wee may, after we ſhall be warned to giue it ouer, dwell with thee in thy euerlaſting habitation, where a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth all purity, ſanctitie, cleanneſſe &amp; glory, world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>26.</hi> A Prayer againſt Sloth.</head>
                  <p>WHen thou calledſt thy ſeruants to account, (moſt mercifull &amp; gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Sauiour) what reward had he, that fearing thy hardneſſe and his owne weakneſſe, laid vp thy talent and employed it not? was he not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conuiction ſentenced, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered to the Sargeant? Are wee not commaunded by thy neuer-erring Word, to worke our ſaluation: to
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:18914:57"/>
watch and pray continually, becauſe wee know not at what houre our Lord and Maſter will call vpon vs? which are no effects of Sloth and Idleneſſe: For to baniſh ſleepe and due repoſe, doth require a vvhole mind, not a ſurfetted and lazy ſoule, buried in fleſh and bloud: and to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vp with humble feruencie, and ardent deuotion, pure and earneſt prayers, asketh due conſideration, much trouble, and a great conqueſt ouer the outward man, not to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained without many aſſaults, and labour. The ſlothfull man, ſaith the holy Ghoſt, ſhall not eate. Can we not then attaine bodily foode, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out dayly care, much ſhift, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times hard and extraordinarie paines? and doeſt thou flatter thy ſelfe, O my ſoule, that either heauen will ſtoope to thee, or our bleſſed Sauiour fetch thee, without mouing or helping thy ſelfe thither? Imitate
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:18914:58"/>
the greedy Merchant, who with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard-of fauours ſeeketh vnknown countries, expoſing himſelfe to the certaine dangers of the Sea; vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſickneſſes, to purchaſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne laden with wealth, which hee can neither keep at his pleaſure, nor will vſe at his pleaſure. Quicken me, O Lord, with thy holy Spirit, that mounted on the wings of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, I may flye to thee. I will riſe duely in the morning, ſaith the holy King, and glorifie God: I will eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry night waſh my couch with my teares. Giue mee, O Lord, the care and reſpect of this holy Prophet his vigilancie, ſtoutneſſe in labours, perſeuerance in good purpoſes, and continuance to the end. This life, O my ſoule, is a warfare wherein we muſt not ſtand idle, but take vp our weapons, and fight manfully. We muſt preuent the day with our diligence, and out-watch the Sunne
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:18914:58"/>
with our carefulneſſe, leſt the enemy take vs vnawares and ſlaughter vs: We muſt haue our Lamps ſtill ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and be euer ready, that wee may be taken in, and made partakers for our ſhort trauels of eternal and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting reſt and repoſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>27.</hi> A Prayer againſt Couetouſneſſe.</head>
                  <p>SInce it is eaſier, O Lord, for a Cammel to enter the eye of a needle, then for a rich man to inherite the Kingdome of Heauen. Let mee (O Lord) wander naked, and hungry, cloathed with ſores and botches, rather then with <hi>Diues</hi> his portion, to take poſſeſſion of his puniſhment. For what auayleth it to gaine the whole world, and loſe my owne ſoule? Yet if it pleaſe thee, bountifull Father, to leaue and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath to me a plentifull eſtate, and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:18914:59"/>
great riches, giue me grace ſo to vſe and beſtow them, that I come not behinde hand with thee in my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count: Let mee ſo diſpoſe them, as thou haſt by expreſſe words ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, that my poore Brethren put not vp a Bill againſt me. Set not my heart on them, O Lord, but as things without mee: when either thou pleaſeſt by fire, water, or any other caſualtie to call them from me, let mee thankefully ſurrender them as a Reeue, not an Owner; yeelding thee immortall and vnfained thanks that I haue had them ſo long, not inwardly grudging and repining that I haue loſt them ſo ſoone. For who placeth al his content on them, can neither poſſeſſe them long, nor ſafely. Giue me, O Lord, pouertie of ſpirit, in the middeſt of all abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, that I may faſt, hauing all plenty, taking the delicates from my Table, and with my owne hand ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:18914:59"/>
the poore and needy, who are bought at as dear a rate as the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt, and whoſe ſoules are as preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to thee as the greateſt. Let me euer remember that ſaying of the bleſſed <hi>Iob: Naked came I out of my mothers wombe, and naked ſhall I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe; Praiſed bee the Lord for all:</hi> Leauing to my children the prayers of the poore, not the curſes of ill-gotten riches; the praiſes of good men, not that heauy ſentence of, Wo be vnto thee, at my depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: that at that great and terrible day, when all accounts ſhalbe exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and laid open, bringing in my Bils of cloathing the naked, feeding the hungry, and giuing drink to the thirſtie, I may receiue that ſoule-comforting diſcharge of, <hi>Come yee bleſſed, and ſeat you on my right hand, for vnto you belongeth the Kingdome of Heauen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:18914:60"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>28.</hi> A Prayer humbly acknowledging our ſins, with promiſe of amendment.</head>
                  <p>I Wretched ſinner, heere perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally appearing and ſtanding in the preſence of God euerlaſting, &amp; of al the Court of Heauen, hauing conſidered the exceeding mercy of his diuine goodnes toward me, moſt vnworthy &amp; miſerable caytife, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath created of nothing, preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, ſuſtained, and deliuered from ſo many dangers, &amp; endowed with ſo many benefits: But aboue al, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehenſible ſweetnes, &amp; clemency wherwith this moſt good God hath ſo bountifully tolerated me in my iniquities, and ſo louingly inſpired me, inuiting mee to amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo patiently expected my repentance &amp; conuerſion, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all my vnthankfulneſſe, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty &amp; infidelity, whereby defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:18914:60"/>
my Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſion, &amp; deſpiſing his graces, I haue ſo impudently offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him: hauing moreouer conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that at the day of my chriſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, I was ſo happy and holily vowed, and dedicated vnto my God to be his child, and that contrary to the profeſſion, which then was made in my name, I haue ſo many and ſundry times, ſo execrably and deteſtably profaned and violated my ſoule, imploying it, and oppoſing it againſt his diuine Maieſtie. At length recalling my ſelfe, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrating my ſelfe in heart and minde, before the Throne of his diuine iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, I acknowledge, confeſſe, and yeeld my ſelfe lawfully attached, and conuicted of high Treaſon againſt his diuine Maieſtie, and guilty of the death and Paſſion of Ieſus Chriſt, by reaſon of the hainous ſinnes which I haue committed, for which he dyed; and ſuffered the torment
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:18914:61"/>
of the Croſſe: ſo that conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I am worthy to be caſt away and damned for euer. But turning my ſelfe towards the Throne of the infinite mercy of the ſelfe-ſame eternall God; hauing deteſted from the bottome of my heart, and with all my force, the iniquities of my life fore-paſſed, I moſt humbly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire and craue pardon, grace and mercy, with entire abſolution from my cryme, through vertue of the Paſſion, and death of the ſame Sauiour and Redeemer of my ſoule; vpon whom relying, as vpon the onely foundation of my hope, I confirme againe, aduowe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new the ſacred profeſſion of loyall ſeruice and fidelitie, made in my name and behalfe, vnto my GOD at my baptizing; renouncing the Diuell, the Fleſh, and the World; abhorring the execrable ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, vanities, and concupiſcence,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:18914:61"/>
for all the time of this preſent life, and for all eternitie, and conuerting my ſelfe vnto my moſt gracious and mercifull God: I deſire, delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, purpoſe and fully reſolue irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocably to honor him, ſerue him, &amp; loue him, now and for euer: giuing him for this end, and dedicating and conſecrating my ſpirits with all his faculties; my ſoule with all her functions; my heart with all his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections; and my body with all his ſences: proteſting neuer more to abuſe any one part of my beeing or nature, againſt his diuine will, and ſoueraigne Maieſtie: To whom I offer vp, and ſacrifice my ſelfe in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to be to him a loyall, obedient, and faithfull creature for euermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:18914:62"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>29.</hi> A Prayer to be ſaid in Afflictions and Troubles.</head>
                  <p>O Eternall and euer-liuing God, the Father of all Conſolation and Mercies, the giuer of all things good and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, who art vnto vs as a Nurſe vnto a childe, a Shepheard vnto a wandring Lambe, a Guide of our wayes, a Guardian of our perſons, a Counſellour in doubts, a Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in troubles, a Patron in our needes, and an aſſured Friend in all afflictions; graciouſly aſſiſt vs in all our tribulations and aduerſities, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an aſſured tryall of thy ſeruants; For whom thou loueſt, thou chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt. Suffer me to bee tempted, O Lord, not ouercome; rebuked, not forſaken; bruiſed with thy rod, not broken; for my ſoule is heauy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:18914:62"/>
me, and my enemies haue preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt me; yea, my Spirit repi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, and my fleſh grudgeth, that thy hand is ſo heauy on mee: I goe like one that hath loſt his way, ſhoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting my eyes into the earth, as deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to be buried in my miſfortunes: All my friends haue left me, and my company is my owne thoughts, which are diſpleaſing vnto me: My eyes are great with teares, my tongue laboureth with my miſ-for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, ſo that I ſeeme to others a piece of earth wrapped in woe and calamity. Comfort me, O Lord, and I ſhall be comforted; ſhoote thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit into me, and I ſhall bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burdened; lighten the beames of thy mercy vpon me and I ſhall ſhine in proſperity: for it is my ſinnes, O Lord, which haue confounded mee: it is the multitude of my wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, which haue drowned the multitude of thy ioyes; it is my
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:18914:63"/>
guilt which baniſheth thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Turne backe, O Lord, and mercifully looke vpon me, as thou didſt vpon thy holy Apoſtle, and faithfull ſeruant S. <hi>Peter,</hi> that I may not onely weep, but bitterly lament my miſdeeds and offences, who haue denyed my onely Lord and Maſter all the dayes of my life, ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring as one that knew him not, and blaſpheming, as certainely neither beleeuing, nor fearing the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which haue ouer-growne me. But if alas, through ſuggeſtion of mine enemy, or through humane frailty, I chance any time to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe in any thing whatſoeuer, giue me grace, O Lord, by the aide of the Holy Ghoſt, to ariſe againe ſo ſoone as I ſhall perceiue my fall, and ſo to returne anew to the Diuine Mercy, without any ſtay or delay whatſoeuer. Let it pleaſe thee, O my eternall God, Almighty and all
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:18914:63"/>
good Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, to confirme and ſtrengthen mee in this reſolution of my amendment, and to accept this Cordiall, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Sacrifice in the odor of ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. O my God, thou art my God, God of my heart, God of my ſoule, God of my ſpirit; and for ſuch doe I reuerently, thankfully, and louing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledge, honour and adore thee, now and for euer.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>30.</hi> Another Prayer for remiſsion of ſinnes.</head>
                  <p>O Benigne Ieſu, the onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge of deſolate and afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſoules, the comfort and ſuccour of thoſe that are laden and oppreſſed, mercifully heare, and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully receiue the prayers and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications of one conceiued and borne in ſinne, who acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:18914:64"/>
and confeſſeth, before the Throne of thy Diuine Maieſty, that hee is too baſe, and altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to ſpeake, nay, looke, and much leſſe to be heard and regarded in this his extremity, who in time of health hath contemned and neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Phyſicion; in time of iollity and proſperity, hath neither thrifti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prouided, nor wiſely preuented the daies of horror and deſolation, who being cruelly accuſed by his owne conſcience, of many high and deteſtable treaſon, againſt the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, his thoughts and ſenſes bearing witnes againſt him, hath neither treaſure to ranſome him, nor friend to pleade for him, wealth preuaileth not with him, who is infinite in Riches: Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles and Honours are momentany ſhadowes in his preſence, who ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanceth and degradeth whom hee pleaſes. Kindred and friends dare
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:18914:64"/>
not bee ſeene before ſo pure and iuſt a Iudge, in ſo foule and vniuſt a cauſe. What wilt thou then doe, O my ſoule, in theſe ſtraights and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities? Whither wilt thou flye for ſuccour? Heauen is his dwelling place, the earth his foot-ſtoole, the Mountaines hee will remoue, and his iuſtice diues into the bottome of the Sea: Fall then before him, and all proſtrate, lift vp thy voyce, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore his mercy, deſire his pardon, ſue vnto him, kneele before him, lay hold of him, and let him not depart, O my ſoule, till hee hath, at leaſt, granted thee a Reprieue for thy horrible and lewd tranſgreſſions: which obtained, whilſt his wrath is a little ſlackened, thy teares may mollifie, and get betweene thee and his definitiue ſentence. Conſider duely what friends thou canſt make, and due conſideration will make contrition a ſpeciall fauorite of our
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:18914:65"/>
Sauiours, pleade heartily for thee, who in thy behalfe, promiſing a deteſtation of thy former offences, with an aſſured purpoſe and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of amendment, ioyned with a continuance and progreſſe in good workes and holy exerciſes, may (for our Sauiour delights to heare him) purchaſe thee an abſolute pardon. Grant me therefore, moſt ſweet and amiable Lord, to imploy the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of my life in ſtudying to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with theſe thy holy friends and fauorites. Giue, O Sauiour, a fountaine of teares vnto my eyes, that I may continually lament and bewayle my daily and haynous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences; breed in mee a loathing, and horrid deteſtation of all my ſinnes, that I may flye from them, and ſhun the wayes and occaſions which leade vnto them, being ſtricken with an extraordinary ſorrow and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction for hauing dared to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:18914:65"/>
a Lord of ſuch height and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ouercome with ſhame and ingratitude, repent the iniuries offered to ſo louing and carefull a Maſter, who hath ſhed his Bloud, to ſaue ſo vnprofitable a ſeruant; that being by feruent charity reconciled vnto him, I may in the day of ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour lawfully claime part of him, and being ſhrowded vnder his wings, eſcape the malice and fury of my accuſers; euen for thy bleſſed names ſake, which ſhall in that time of trouble, bee a ſure defence to all thy Choſen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="31" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>31.</hi> A Prayer for Chaſtity.</head>
                  <p>O Almightie and bleſſed Lord and Sauiour, the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of thy Father, the brightneſſe and ſpotleſſe ſinceritie of Men, who delighteſt and viſiteſt
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:18914:66"/>
thy cleane and vnpolluted mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; ſanctifie, O Lord, and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie mee that I may not bee a ſhame and reproach to ſo immaculary and chaſte a Head; that I may appeare a ſonne, ſome way worthy ſo holy and heauenly a Father. Mortifie and kill in me the looſe and powerfull deſires of the fleſh, which borne in me are kindled and inflamed by the diuell and my owne frailtie. Fixe my eyes, O Lord, vpon thy immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, glorious, and neuer-fading beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that I may contemne and deſpiſe all earthly and tranſitorie paintings: Strike me in loue wlth the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of vertue, that my heart ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and wholly taken with ſo faire and worthily beloued a perfection, there may be no roome left for Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Idleneſſe, the wel-ſprings of wanton affection. Buſie mee, O Lord, about the day of Iudgement, and my Account; the torments of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:18914:66"/>
hell, and their euerlaſtingneſſe: that all my ſtudy and labour may bee how to auoide them, and bleſſe thee that haſt not left me to the world, and corrupted tyrannie of man, but mercifully laid thy hand vpon me, and conducted me to the meanes of my ſaluation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="32" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>32.</hi> A Prayer in Iournying.</head>
                  <p>O Mercifully louing Lord, which gouernedſt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendedſt thy people <hi>Iſrael</hi> from all the vniuſt oppreſſion and mercileſſe fury of their enemies, guiding them in all their wayes and trauailes; and graciouſly viſitedſt thy ſeruant <hi>Iacob</hi> in his way, and powredſt thy bleſſing on him: bee neere at this time to thy vnworthy and ſinfull ſeruant, and bleſſe mee, I beſeech thee, in this my trauell and
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:18914:67"/>
iourney, from any violence of ſinne, or outward Spoylers and Robbers. Proſper, O Lord, and bring to good end, as it ſhall pleaſe thee, the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe I trauell and wander about, and vouchſafe to direct mee in it, that I do that which ſhall bee to thy glory, and my owne behoofe and profite, euen for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>33.</hi> A Prayer to bee vſed in any ſtorme of Lightning and Thunder.</head>
                  <p>O Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord God of Sabbath, Heauen and earth are full of the Maieſtie of thy glorie; the flouds lift vp their voyce and ſpeake thy wonders, the Heauens flie before thy Anger, and the vnnaturally mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Earth trembleth at thy Voyce: All which ordained for the vſe of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:18914:67"/>
Man, vpon thy word prooue their ſcourge and puniſhment: The fire from aboue, at the cry of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, eateth vp his Scorners: the Sea rageth and deuoureth the people and Chariots of the Egyptians; yea, the earth gapeth, and buryeth men aliue at thy command: Preſerue vs, gentle and infinitely louing Father, from this violent and dreadfull ſtorme, which raiſed for our ſins, threatneth our deſtruction. Put out the lightning, O Lord, and diſſolue the horrid and fearefull ſtone, leſt it paſh thy people to aſhes, and we be ſeene no more. Caſt thine eye vpon the Merites and Paſſion of our Sauiour, and let his Bloud come betweene thy Iuſtice and our guilt, that we may reioyce, and lift vp our voyces with the holy Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> I will not feare, though the earth bee mooued and throwne into the heart of the Sea; for the Almightie
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:18914:68"/>
is our refuge and ſtrength, and hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth vs in all our trouble. Praiſed be the name of the Lord.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="34" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>34.</hi> A Prayer or Meditation, concerning the benefits after Creation.</head>
                  <p>COnſider, O my ſoule, with reuerence and thankſgiuing, how Almightie God placed thee heere of his owne bountie and nobleneſſe, not for any need hee had of thy helpe or ſeruice, but to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow vpon thee his grace, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath hee enriched thee with vnderſtanding to know him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance to be mindefull of him, will to loue him, imagination to repreſent his benefits vnto thy thoughts, eyes to behold the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of his workes, and a tongue to praiſe him. Wherefore being crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſet in the world for this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:18914:68"/>
reiect and caſt away all acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which prooue contrary to this end. For alas! what did I buſie my thoughts vpon, O my God, when I placed them not vpon thee? What was I mindefull of, when I forgot thee? What did I loue, when I did not loue thee? Aye me, I ſhould haue fed my ſoule with the veritie, and I haue fil'd it with vanitie; and haue ſerued the world, which was not made but to ſerue mee. I defie you vtterly, O vaine cogitations and vnprofitable fancies. I abhorre and abiure you, O deteſtable and friuolous Imaginations: I renounce you, vnfaithfull and diſloyall loues, miſerable and loſt ſeruices, vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full gratifications, cumberſome and vnpleaſing pleaſures. And thou, O my God, and my Lord, thou ſhalt bee, for the time to come, the onely obiect of my thoughts; and I will neuer more apply my ſpirit to any
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:18914:69"/>
cogitations which may be offenſiue or diſliking to thee. My memorie all the dayes of my life, ſhall be filled with conſideration of thy exceſſiue goodneſſe, ſo louingly declared in my behalfe; thou ſhalt be the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſſe of my heart, &amp; the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my affections: Hence therefore from my ſight, for euer, all vaine and idle paſtimes, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to I haue vainely applyed my mind; all gameſome and toying exerciſes, in which I fondly ſpent my dayes; and all looſe and idle affections, which entangled my heart, ſhall henceforth bee a horrour vnto my thoughts, becauſe thou haſt made me, O Lord, for thy ſelfe, to enioy euerlaſtingly the immenſitie of thy glorie. O when ſhall it bee, that I ſhall bee worthie, and when ſhall I praiſe thee according to thy deſert, and my dutie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I offer vnto thee, O my deare Creatour, all theſe good
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:18914:69"/>
affections and holy reſolutions, with all my heart and all my ſoule, and beſeech thee, O God, to accept theſe my deſires and vowes, and to giue my ſoule thy holy bleſſing, that ſhee may faithfully accompliſh them through the merites of the Bloud of thy bleſſed Sonne our Sauiour, ſhed for me vpon the Croſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="35" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>35.</hi> A Prayer againſt vaine Attire.</head>
                  <p>DOth it beſeeme mee, moſt mercifull and bleſſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, to bee decked and attired in rich and ſumptuous Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, when the ſcornefull and diſdainefull Iewes apparell thee in a coate of folly, to bee laught at and contemned of the people? Doe Iewels and Fethers become my head, when I inwardly behold thee crowned with Thornes? And ſhall
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:18914:70"/>
my wriſts be guarded with precious Bracelets, where thine were bound with cords? My fingers gliſtring with Diamonds, and thine iewell'd with thine owne Bloud ſtarting out, with the vnmercifull vſage of thy perſecuters? O my moſt ſweet and gentle Sauiour, let my ſorrowfull and wofull thoughts, for my deadly and horrible offences, bee to my head a torment, like thy merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Thornes; my vaine and idle behauiour, more deſpiſed then that many-coloured coate; and the awe and reuerence of thy iuſtice (terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to offenders) chaine my hands harder, and with more crueltie then the whipcord; that I may in ſome meaſure haue a feeling and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of thoſe vnheard of, and new-inuented Tyrannies laid vpon thee for my tranſgreſſions. Let the memorie of thy wounds pierce my heart with true compunction, ſo to
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:18914:70"/>
haue iniured a Lord of ſuch great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Maieſtie, for my ſake wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, aboue the meekneſſe of a Lambe, vndergoing thoſe baſe and vnworthy diſgraces, the fore-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of thy cruell death. Giue me, O Lord, ſince we muſt bee perfect imitators of thee, obedience to yeeld and ſubmit my ſelfe to thy diuine Will and Pleaſure, in all ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and torments, a noble patience to beare them manfully, and charitie inflamed like thine, to bleſſe my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuters, praying for their amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and conuerſion, that ſuffering with thee obediently, patiently and louingly, I may enioy with thee that happie reward, fore-promiſed to all thoſe that take vp their Croſſe and follow thee; euen for thy precious and vnvaluable bloud; which ſhed vpon the Croſſe, is an vndenyable Sacrifice for all ſinnes and offences.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="36" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:18914:71"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>36.</hi> A Prayer for a Mayd againſt Temptation.</head>
                  <p>GIue vnto God the firſt fruits, ſaith the Prophet. And our Sauiour commandeth vs to offer him thoſe things that are his. Thou haſt planted me here, O Lord, and opened the gates of heauen to water mee: Thou haſt made me flouriſh, ſpreading like a faire Vine, and my luſſious and ſwelling fruite haue tempted vnholy hands to ſteale away what belongeth to thee. Strengthen mee, O Lord, againſt their violence, and let their ſubtile perſwaſions come to nothing, the Pit which they haue digged for others, proue their own Sepulchre, and let their nets bee ouerthrowne and broken, that glorifying thee, I may ioyfully ſay, The Lord hath
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:18914:71"/>
beene my deliuerer, I need not feare what men can do to me: he hath hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and ſaued his hand-maiden out of the hands of his enemies. Bleſſed bee the name of the Lord, now and for euermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="37" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>37.</hi> Another Prayer for a Maide, to the ſame effect.</head>
                  <p>O Almightie GOD, Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of heauen and earth, who glorifyeſt the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with Starres, the Sun with a great light; the God of all beautie, all proportion, all order, holding in thy hand the motion and being of all things created: I humbly offer vp vnto thy Diuine Maieſtie, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is good and vertuous in me, whatſoeuer beautifull or proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, entreating thee, of thy infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite mercie, to take into thy cuſtodie
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:18914:72"/>
an innocent &amp; vnexperienced Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, to direct and gouerne me by thy neuer-erring wiſedome, leſt my youth, betrayed by frailtie and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcretion, ſhould traiterouſly yeeld mee vp to the lewd ſuggeſtions and temptations of the diuell, who appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled in fleſh and bloud, waiteth hourely for my deſtruction, leauing no meanes vntryed to captiuate my weake ſoule: Suffer him not, O Lord, to haue the vpper-hand; giue me not into his power, vnleſſe thou place a guard of Angels with mee, holy &amp; vnreſiſtable thoughts within me, that in thy name, putting on my Sauiour Chriſt for my Armour, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancing the glorious Croſſe for my Banner, I may put my enemies to flight, and triumph in the Conqueſt which thou haſt gotten for me, to my owne, and all their eternall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort which put their truſt in thee. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="38" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:18914:72"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>38.</hi> A Meditation, or Prayer for a May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, not to be proud of her owne perfections.</head>
                  <p>DID not thy hand, O Lord, giue thoſe many excellent and indiſtinguiſht colours to the Raine-bow? Didſt not thou, O Lord, giue glorie to the Sun, and apparell the earth in all her beauties? And doth not the Raine-bow at the with-drawing of the Sun, diſcolour it ſelfe, the Sunne at the interpoſing of the Moone, hide his glorie, and the earth, in the abſence of the Sun, loſe all her gay and flouriſhing Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments? O momentanie and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding painting, waſht away with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſickeneſſe, and blowne off by the rough breath of a violent wind! Shall I for thee, abandon my Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and to keepe thy friendſhip, fall
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:18914:73"/>
out with Almightie God? Will the wormes forbeare thy excellency and perfections, and ſtrucke with reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, fall off and retire into their Cabins? Is ſickneſſe afraid of it, or dare not death venter vpon it? No, no, my ſoule, they will breake thorow thy Coffin, and as a daintie diſh, eagerly deuoure it: the Lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie will make a prey on it, and too well we know that death feareth no colours. If the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou beeſt bewitched to this outward gloſſe and ſhining, ſeeke the waies to make it perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent; apply thy ſelfe to vertue, whoſe raritie and luſtre ſtrikes a far off, and all men will call thee beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Let modeſtie ſit on thy cheekes, and thy bluſhes will out-laſt the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; Truth vpon thy lips, and they will exceed the Rubies; Mildneſſe in thy eyes, and they will out-ſhine the Diamond; Innocencie on thy breſt, and thy whitneſſe will ſurpaſſe
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:18914:73"/>
the Lillies; thou ſhalt bee beloued of men, at peace with thy ſelfe, and acceptable to Almightie GOD. Away then all artificiall and ſophiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate drugs, idle and beſotting wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: neuer more will I meddle with you. O my ſweete Sauiour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, let nothing ſeeme beautifull but thy mercie; nothing louely but thy bountie: enamored on which, let me woo, intreate, ſigh, zealouſly proteſt, and vſe all meanes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie to obtaine them. For all other exterior &amp; formall beauties, the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies of fleſh and bloud, let me onely acknowledge them, as thy glorious workemanſhip; loue them, as badges of thy fauour; admire and praiſe thee for them, from whoſe euerlaſting ſtore-houſe they proceed, thy ſelfe being all beautie, all excellencie, all perfection, &amp; more to be deſired the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> much gold or precious ſtones, in whoſe companie all things are fill'd
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:18914:74"/>
with perfection and glorie world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="39" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>39.</hi> A Prayer for a Maid, to be directed in her Choyſe.</head>
                  <p>SInce thou, O Lord, in thy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting wiſedome, haſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained Marriage honourable amongſt men, as the meanes for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion and propagation: Giue mee (O Lord) an vnderſtanding heart, that I bee not euilly ſeduced to my ouerthrow. Grant that I may ayme at no other end, but the fulfilling thy commandement, not my owne luſts &amp; wilfull deſires: let me chooſe by the aduice of my friends, and the eyes of my Parents, leſt blinded with affection, I fall into thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences, which I may too late feele, without meanes of remedying. Grant (O Lord) a pure and vnſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:18914:74"/>
loue may be the cauſe of our ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and a peaceable and vndiuided amitie the effect. Let the feare of diſpleaſing thee, make vs pleaſe one another; the obedience to thee, teach vs obedience in our ſelues; that wholly ſubmitting our ſelues to thy will, we may labour together in this tranſitorie life, to come to thee the life euerlaſting, with whom dwelleth vnſpeakable loue, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-ending charitie, world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="40" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>40.</hi> A Prayer for a Maid, to be obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to her Parents.</head>
                  <p>O My moſt mercifull Lord and Redeemer, ſubdue and bridle my head-ſtrong and vntamed affections, who delighting in their owne wayes, repine at the direction of my Superiours. Let
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:18914:76"/>
mee euer remember thy holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement: <hi>Honour thy Father and Mother, that thy dayes may be long in the land of the liuing.</hi> Giue me grace to vnderſtand it truely, leſt forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thy precept, I be baniſhed into that wilde and barbarous Country, where to liue is terribler then death, and dying, the onely comfort of the liuing. Let their reprehenſions bee the cauſe of my amendment, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pining their iuſt and lawfull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, an vndeniable practice of all my actions. Let me reuerence their age, lending them my youth to help them; pray for their imperfections, and in them remember humane weakneſſe; that in my obedience, I may receiue the vertue of their bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, which thou alwayes granteſt to them that endeuour to fulfill the leaſt of thy commandements.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="41" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:18914:76"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>41.</hi> A Prayer before a Iourney.</head>
                  <p>O Almightie and euerliuing God, which by the hand of thy ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Moſes</hi> broughtſt the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and the crueltie of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and madeſt them walke ouer the Red-Sea, kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping back with a mighty winde the raging waters, who returning in their Furie, ouer-whelmed all that great Hoſt, and after went'ſt before them, and conducted them thorow the vaſt and wilde Deſert, feeding them in their extreme Famine with Manna ſhowred from Heauen: Be pleaſed (O mercifull Father) at this inſtant to accompany mee in all my iourneyes and trauailes, and with thy louing and mightie protection defend me from all dangers of thoſe that lye in awaite to murther and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:18914:75"/>
ſpoile thy Liege people. Bee vnto mee (O Lord) a guide in my going out, a ſafeguard and defence vpon the way, a ſhaddow in heat, a ſhelter in raine &amp; cold, a waggon in weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, an helper in time of extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, a ſtay in ſlipperie paſſages, a Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in ſhipwracke, that vnder thy ſafe and ſure conduct, we may march quietly and peaceably to our iourneyes end, and vnder the couer of thy wings, ioyfully and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly returne to our homes againe; for his onely ſake, who was a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall Pilgrime heere vpon earth, to make all our prayers acceptable vnto thee. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="42" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>42.</hi> Another ſhort Prayer for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>O Almighty God, which haſt made this our life, as it were a ſhort Pilgrimage to
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:18914:75"/>
viſit holy places, and doe penance by thee appointed for mans firſt tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion; giuing vs as in an Inne, a ſpace to refreſh our wearied bodies, not to dwell and ſettle our ſelues: Grant mercifully, thy aſſiſtance, in theſe my iourneys and remouings, and with thy holy Spirit bleſſe and comfort me on the way, that I be not left alone to the crueltie of thoſe that would aſſaile mee: but hauing thy Angell for my guide and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I may not feare the oppreſsion of the Wicked, but happily arriue at the deſired Hauen, where I vvill magnifie and praiſe thy holy name, for thy mightie ayde and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection.</p>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:18914:77"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:18914:77"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
               <div n="43" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:18914:78"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>43.</hi> A Prayer in Afflictious.</head>
                  <p>WHy art thou ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, my ſoule, and why doeſt thou trouble mee? Why doeſt thou hang ſleepe vpon mine eye-lids, and faſten heauineſſe on my foot-ſteps? Doth not God regard the prayers of the afflicted? or doth he not from his high holy place looke downe to the earth, that he might heare the gronings of the fettered, and thoſe that are perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and afflicted? Can thy eye ſee into heauen, or is thy vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of counſell with God, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue how neere his holy hand is to deliuer thee? Euery inſtant is time enough for his Omnipotency: and impoſſible occaſions, eaſie to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitenes of his Deitie: Put thy truſt in him, my ſoule, and thou ſhalt not
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:18914:78"/>
be confounded. Say with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Dauid,</hi> Though a thouſand fall on my right hand, and ten thouſand on my left, yet I will not bee afraid, becauſe God hath beene my helper. Bee comforted by the mercifull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples which he hath ſhewed to his people. Did not Almighty God with a ſtrong hand &amp; puniſhments, enforce the Prophet <hi>Ionas</hi> to preach deſtruction to the <hi>Niniuites,</hi> limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them a ſhort time, that within three dayes their Citie ſhould bee deſtroyed? and yet vpon their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, humbling themſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him with prayers, &amp; faſting: did he not moſt mercifully remit their puniſhment, and take them into his grace and fauour? Fall therefore proſtrate before him, and with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect reſignation of thy owne will, yeeld thy ſelfe into his hands, to do what it pleaſe him with thee: en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate him of his loue and fauour,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:18914:79"/>
who neuer abſenteth himſelfe to thoſe that ſeeke him: relye vpon his mercy, who ſo much loued his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that he ſent his onely begotten Sonne, to dye for the Redemption of mankinde: Aske him forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thy ſinnes and offences, by reaſon of whoſe guilt, thou ſuffereſt theſe light and temporary puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which haue in iuſtice deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued euerlaſting damnation, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burdened of which, the yoke will be eaſie, and the waight light: yea, thy miſeries wil be pleaſing like wounds honourably gotten in a glorious conqueſt: and then maiſt thou ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſing vnto the Lord; Mine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies that troubled me, themſelues are weakened and falne. One thing yet I haue asked of our Lord; this will I ſeeke for, that I may dwell in the houſe of our Lord, al the daies of my life.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="44" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:18914:79"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>44.</hi> A Prayer to be ſaid by a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, for the ſafe returne of his goods.</head>
                  <p>IN the time of my trouble who ſhall I flye vnto? what power can fetch me from the bottome of the Sea? or whoſe arme reacheth to the end of the world? O moſt merciful and gracious Lord, the Sea is thine, and thou madeſt it, and thy hands prepared the dry land: with thy Word thou calmeſt the raging waters, and with a beck layeſt the furie of the winde. Grant, of thy accuſtomed clemencie and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſuch ſeaſonable and temperate weather, that they may ſafely arriue at the appointed Port. Bee vnto them, O Lord, their Pylote, leſt the hidden Rocks, or vnknowne Sands deuoure them. Be their defence and
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:18914:80"/>
ſafegard, leſt their enemies make prey on them: that relying on thy fauour, aboue the vertue of their Load-ſtone, they may ioyfully and merrily touch the deſired Land, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging thy goodneſſe and might, to whom alone that merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe element obeyeth at thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, yeelding vp all her treaſure. Grant this, O my ſweet Lord and Sauiour, euen for thy tender mercy, which refuſeth no Petitions, that are offered with a pure and vnfained zeale. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="45" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>45.</hi> A Prayer before Study.</head>
                  <p>O Vnſpeakable Creatour, which in the Treaſure of thy Wiſedome haſt ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned learning, as a ſecondary meanes to raiſe our declined ſoules, wrapt
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:18914:80"/>
by the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> in ſinne and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, to a perfected and ſurer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of thy diuine goodnes: Enlighten, O Lord, our vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and with the rayes of thy brightneſſe, baniſh away all miſts and darknes, by which wee are dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and diſabled. Thou (O Lord) which raiſeſt thy glorie out of the tongues of Infants, powre into our lips eloquence and vtterance, that we may reueale thy will, and ſing praiſes of thy goodnes. Quicken (O Lord) our vnderſtanding, ſtrengthen our memorie, and recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our will; that wee may truely know, faithfully keepe, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently performe thy precepts and commandements. Giue vs (O Lord) grace in our entrance, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance in our progreſſe, and humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie at our going forth, that we may alwaies acknowledge thee, the giuer and beſtower of what height ſo
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:18914:81"/>
euer we attaine to, euen for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="46" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>46.</hi> A Prayer for the fatherleſſe.</head>
                  <p>O Almightie God, which art a Father to the Orphans, mercifully aſſiſt vs poore &amp; comfortles children, left as a prey to them, who are left to diſpoſe of vs. Behold (O Lord) how they contend for what we haue, enuying one another for a ſhare, wherin they can challenge no part. But thou (O Lord) ſhalt pleade our cauſe. Thou ſhalt bee our Aduocate and Helper: Thou ſhalt take the prey out of their mouthes, and lay that ſhame vpon them, which they haue laid vp for others. For vnto thee (O Lord) we commend our ſoules, our bodies, our ſubſtance, deſiring to be diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by thee, and to receiue from
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:18914:81"/>
thee what thou ſhalt thinke in thy wiſedome will be neceſſary for the attaining thy loue and fauour, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, in vaine wee doe heape vp for after-times; in vaine doe we build and riſe early, bee ſollicitous and take care, ſith who buildeth without thee, pulleth downe; who ſoweth without thee, ſcattereth; and who gathereth without thee, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth woe vpon himſelfe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="47" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>47.</hi> A Prayer in Afflictions and troubles.</head>
                  <p>COmfort thy ſelfe (O my ſoule) in theſe Afflictions and troubles, praiſe and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie thy holy Name, that hee hath not giuen thee vp to thy owne af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and deſires, letting thee wildely runne as a beaſt, to all ſenſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie: but gently chaſtiſing thee as one of his children, hath recalled
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:18914:82"/>
thee into thy ſelfe, to know thy owne weakneſſe and frailtie, making thee one of the honourable Order of the Croſſe, whoſe badge all his Saints &amp; Seruants weare vpon their breſt; for it is better for thee that thy members here languiſh and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, then thy whole body to bee caſt into euerlaſting fire: yeeld thy ſelfe vp to all torments for his ſake, being heartily ſorrie, that thou art not able to vndergo more in his ſeruice, who in his owne example hath out-gone all tyrannie for thee. Triumph when thou art perſecuted, and glorie in the bonds of our Sauiour. Bleſſed are they that mourne, for they ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce: Bleſſed are they that are hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with miſeries and misfortunes, for they ſhall be exalted and aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. Bleſſed are they that are perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted for righteouſneſſe ſake, for to them belongeth the Kingdome of Heauen, where thou ſhalt eternally
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:18914:82"/>
reioyce and triumph with the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Saints, and Martyrs, who haue beene ſharers with thee in this vale of teares, and miſerie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="48" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>48.</hi> A Prayer of thanksgiuing.</head>
                  <p>SIng vnto the Lord a new ſong, becauſe hee hath done mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous things, with his owne right hand and his holy arme, hath hee gotten himſelfe the victory. Who is like vnto our God? or who dare compare with his mightineſſe? He hath remembred himſelfe of his promiſe to his ſeruant, that he would not leaue him for euer: He hath not ſuffered my enemies vtterly to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile againſt mee, nor left me in the hands of thoſe that hate mee. Hee hath onely ſhewed me the Rod, and taken it away againe: early in the morning will I recount thy praiſes,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:18914:83"/>
and meditate all the day long vpon thy mercies, which haſt giuen me to taſte of thy bleſſings, and filled me with good things. I was naked, and thou haſt cloathed me: I was hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and thou haſt refreſhed me: I was thirſty, &amp; thou haſt graſped the Cloud, and powred downe thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly deaw: I was weary, and thou haſt eaſed me; I was loaden, &amp; thou haſt ſtrengthened me: I was oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and thou haſt reſcued me. O what tongue is able to ſtory thy lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing kindneſſes! or what vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding conceiueth thy wondrous works! I will ſhew mercy (ſaith our Lord) vnto thouſands of them that loue me, &amp; keep my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements. But how aboundantly ought I to ſpeake of thy gracious fauour, who haue rebelled againſt thy motions, ſpurned at thy precepts &amp; ſtatutes; and haue yet been embraced, recalled home againe, cloathed richly, and ſet
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:18914:83"/>
at thy owne Table! I haue riotouſly conſumed, &amp; thou haſt louingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored: I haue in lauiſh cups, dis-ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and laſciuious company, proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; vain-gloriouſly throwne away my ſaluation: &amp; thou haſt by ſtripes, buffetings, &amp; moſt tormenting and cruell death, redeemed it againe. I haue tranſgreſſed (O Lord) and thou art puniſhed: I being a low, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned vaſſaile, haue offended and miſ-done; and thou the Son of the mighty King, art beaten. It is not ſo (O Lord) with the ſonnes of men, who afflict their ſubiects for their miſ-demeanours, and make them ſmart for the Princes offences. Who is like vnto our God, whoſe mercie endureth from generation, to gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: Praiſe our Lord, ye children: Praiſe ye the name of our Lord. The name of our Lord be bleſſed, from henceforth, now and for euer.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="49" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:18914:84"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>49.</hi> A Prayer in time of Peſtilence.</head>
                  <p>FAmine, Plague, and Warre, are thy ſcourges (O Lord) and thou throweſt them vpon the people for their offences: We haue repined, mercifull Father, in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance of health, and employed our ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth in diſhonoring thy holy Name. Our members ſanctified for thy vſe and ſeruice, haue beene the preyes of Harlots, and officers of Satan. The very breath thou gaueſt vs to praiſe and tell thy wonders, hath mis-ſpoken, and blaſphemed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee; iuſtly therefore doth thy conſuming Peſtilence ſnatch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way our health, turne our ſtrength into nothing, rot all our members, killing vs by the infection of the ayre taken into our bodies, who haue continually breathed out of our
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:18914:84"/>
bodies all blaſphemie &amp; corruption.</p>
                  <p>Yet ſtay (O mercifull Father) and hold thy reuenging hand, heare the cryes of thy ſeruants, groning vnder the tyrannie of this murdering diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, and be pitifull to vs. Remember (O Lord) that we are conceiued and borne in ſinne, poore and vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble creatures, vnable without thee to deſerue the leaſt drop of thy fauour: Mercifully aſſiſt vs with thy grace, and enrich vs with thy holy and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall vertues, that our prayers may come vp before thee, and bee accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, that hauing taken away this heauy perſecution and plague, wee may for euer praiſe thy clemencie, and enioying thy louing mercy, feare againe to diſpleaſe thee, who haſt had ſo great compaſſion on vs; euen for thy Sonnes ſake, who gaue himſelfe vp to all torments, to keepe vs vnpuniſhed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="50" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:18914:85"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>50.</hi> A Prayer in time of Warre.</head>
                  <p>O Lord God of Hoſts, that fighteſt the battels for thy ſeruants, girding thy ſelfe with power &amp; ſtrength, to ouercome and put to flight the enemies of thoſe that put their truſt in thee.</p>
                  <p>Be preſent (O Lord) with the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, which are gone foorth to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thoſe who labour our ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw. Leade (O Lord) their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and conduct him through the midſt of their enemies: Giue him wiſedome and diſcretion, warily to foreſee all diſaduantages; inuincible courage, to oppoſe all dangers; and truth and loyalty, that he ſell not the faith &amp; bloud of the people. Be at their counſels (O Lord) and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine for them. Bleſſe their ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems, that vnpreuented they may
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:18914:85"/>
take effect, and ſo order all the ſtate of this Warre, that they may returne with conqueſt and victory.</p>
                  <p>Giue vnto the ſouldiers (O Lord) ablenes of minde &amp; body, to be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling &amp; ſtrong to vndergoe al labours and aſſaults, concord and vnanimity, that obediently labouring for the weale of their Country, they may be made fit inſtruments of the others ouerthrow.</p>
                  <p>Bleſſe the Seaſon of the yeere vnto them; moderate the extremitie of heate &amp; cold, that they bee neither diſabled by the one, nor diſtempered by the other. Let the Sunne and the Winde (O Lord) fight for them; the aduantages and inconueniency of place be on their ſide; that by thee, &amp; through thee, being made co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>querors of their enemies, they may triumph in thy goodnes, and boaſt of thy lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing kindneſſes which endure from generation to generation. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="51" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:18914:86"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>51.</hi> A Prayer to be ſaid by a Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, for the fruits of the earth.</head>
                  <p>O All prouident and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Creator, which haſt giuen charge and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the heauenly Powers, to apparell and adorne the earth with varified and many coloured beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, for the ornament and glory of this great All: and haſt likewiſe bleſſed her wombe with a fit diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to receiue the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans ſeede, comforting and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing it with her natiue vertue, and the generatiue power of the Sunne, till it re-deliuer it againe with great increaſe and profit, for the refreſhing and ſuſtentation of all mankinde: Powre downe, wee beſeech thee, with thy heauenly
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:18914:86"/>
and timely ſhowres, maturitie and fruitfulneſſe into her barren and ſterrill wombe. Giue her (O Lord) a timely Conception, and let the moderate fals of heate and water, deliuer her of plenty and aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, that all nations may reioyce and be glad. Send farre from vs that monſter Famine, the abortiue iſſue of her vntimely labour. Shut vp the Lightning (O Lord) and hold backe the Thunder; graſpe the Clouds, that ſhee periſh not with exceſſe of drought, and ſtay the waters in their fall, leſt ſhee miſcarry by drinking too much. Keep from her vnwholeſome ayres, deſtroying Mil-dewes, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring Caterpillers, which car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on the wings of the vvinde, eate vp the fruits of our labour. Giue vs (O Lord) a timely Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, that wee may with ioy and comfort carrie into our Barnes
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:18914:87"/>
what we haue with much labour and expence carefully ſowed. Bleſſe (O Lord) our ſtore like the Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, for that giuing out of our neceſſary prouiſion to our poore Brethren, we may finde thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing left behinde; that neither ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall fire, malice of our neighbours, nor the exceſſe of immoderate ſhowres deſtroy our Garners and Store-houſes: but holding our wealth as thy gift to bee recalled at thy pleaſure, wee may receiue thy bounteous largeſſe here, and full harueſt hereafter to thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, that haue beene carefull Stewards in thy Vineyard, euen for Ieſus, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="52" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:18914:87"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>52.</hi> A Prayer for the Widdowes.</head>
                  <p>HOw often, O Lord, haſt thou inuited me by thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Word to come vnto thee? How often haſt thou called, Come vnto me, all yee that are laden and oppreſſed, and I will eaſe you? Behold me here, O Lord, a poore and deſolate Widdow, depriued of my Husband, vnder thee, giuen to bee my onely ſtay and comfort; ſhut vp in my houſe, vnuiſited, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comforted, vncounſelled, left in a ſea of troubles, and in a wilderneſſe of buſineſſe; vnskilfull how to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, and vnexperienced which way to wade thorow them, my children hungrie after my goods, and my kindred gaping after their Legacies; my ſtate vncertaine and litigious, called by contentious and euill,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:18914:88"/>
minded perſons into queſtion of Titles and Tryals, meaning by op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and might to teare from mee what belongeth not to them. In all theſe my troubles and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, heauineſſe of minde, ſad and continuall griefes, I neither expect nor deſire comfort but from thy holy Tabernacle: Looke downe from thy high and holy place, O Lord, vpon thy carefull and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe ſeruant, and inſtruct her which way to take, in ſo many and confuſed miſeries. Touch the heart, O Lord, of ſome honeſt and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man, one who hath thy feare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eyes, that hee may helpe and direct me in my vncertaine and doubtfull buſineſſes: and if it be my right, O Lord, that they would violently pluck from mee, bee neere vnto me, for thy mercie ſake, and raiſe vp thoſe that are skilfull in the Law, to deale faithfully with me:
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:18914:88"/>
faſten the Iudge, O Lord, vnto me, and open his eyes that hee may ſee my right, and deale according vnto equitie.</p>
                  <p>Bleſſe my children, and teach them obedience to thee, and dutie towards me, that I may be comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in them; and giue mee grace, O Lord, to dedicate the remainder of my dayes to thy vſe and ſeruice, ſtrength to reſiſt and ouercome all contrarie motions and oppoſitions; that hauing faithfully obeyed thee in taking my husband; ſince thou haſt pleaſed to take him from me, I may liue onely to thee, ſo that death nor hell be able to diuorce me from ſo bountifull, ſo bleſſed, and all-pittying a Lord and Father. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="53" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:18914:89"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>53.</hi> A Prayer for a Wife.</head>
                  <p>O Lord God, moſt mightie, which haſt inſtituted and ordained Marriage for the holy vniting and ioyning together of one ſoule in two bodies, which ſhould gouerne and direct all their actions to one end, mutually ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying each others eare, ioyntly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring through the cumbers and aduerſities of this tranſitorie world, together bearing all troubles and diſcomforts, together partaking of all ioyes and ſolaces: Grant, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, for the loue which thou beareſt thy holy Church, a type of which thou pleaſeſt to make vs, that we may together faithfully ſerue &amp; obey thy commandements, loue thee aboue our ſelues, and feare thee aboue all things.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="137" facs="tcp:18914:89"/>Bleſſe, O Lord, I beſeech thee, my husband in all his buſineſſe and vndertakings, and giue him grace to call vpon thee for aide and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell in all his enterpriſes; accept his labours, O Lord, and proſper the workes of his hands, that endeuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring painefully, and honeſtly to earne our refreſhings, we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye vpon thee for the good ſucceſſe.</p>
                  <p>Grant vs, O Lord, a competent eſtate to maintaine our ſelues with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ingagements to others, and to bring vp our children in thy feare; ſanctifie vs with thy holy Spirit, that a vertuous and heauenly loue may dwell betwixt vs, in all ſorrowes and miſ-fortunes, whatſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe thee to lay vpon vs, ſtill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting one another.</p>
                  <p>Forgiue, O Lord, and remit all our ſinnes, and giue vs both grace to attend thy Diuine Will and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure for the perfecting and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:18914:90"/>
of whatſoeuer wee ſhall deſire, that being made one by thee, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing one in thee, we may vndeuided enioy thy eternall company, world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="54" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>54.</hi> A Prayer for Mariners.</head>
                  <p>I Haue ſeene and beheld thy wonderfull workes, and am ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed: I haue conſidered, O Lord, and meditated on thy vnheard-of mercies, and am aſtoniſhed: Thou haſt giuen vs a paſſage in the midſt of the foming waters, the raging Seas haue incompaſſed vs on euerie ſide, and thou haſt ſaued vs: The Rockes haue hidden themſelues, awaiting our deſtruction, and the Shelfes haue prouided a graue for vs; terrible and dreadfull Tempeſts haue ſnatched away our Maſt from vs, the deuouring Maine hath eaten
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:18914:90"/>
vp our Anchor; Darkeneſſe hath ouer-ſhadowed the heauens, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the guide of the Starres from vs, and the confuſion and imminent danger ſo amazed our Pilot, that he hath forgotten the vſe of his Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone: and yet, O mercifull and all pittying Father, haſt thou ſafely conducted and brought vs to our deſired Hauen.</p>
                  <p>Thy mightie and out-ſtretched Arme hath ſupplyed the defect of our Maſt; thy Mercie ſtands vs in ſtead of our Anchor; thy euer-ſhining goodneſſe made way for vs through the midſt of all darkneſſe; and thy eternall Prouidence, our neuer-fayling Load-ſtone, merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully directed vs in the vnknowne waies of the wilde Ocean.</p>
                  <p>Praiſe the Lord, all yee waters, and let all the fiſhes of the Sea praiſe the LORD, and all yee that haue ſeene his wonders in the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:18914:91"/>
deepe bee confounded and aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</p>
                  <p>For my part, O Lord, write them, I beſeech thee, in the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of my heart, that I may conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually remember them with feare and trembling, euer acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging with praiſe and thankeſgiuing, that thou haſt taken mee from the mouth of the graue, and ſnatcht me out of the iawes of death; for which I will alwaies ſing, There is none like vnto our God, who hath ſaued his people in the midſt of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, hallowed be his name for euermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="55" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>55.</hi> A Prayer for Children.</head>
                  <p>O Lord God, from whom the moſt aged receiue their comfort, and the wiſeſt their inſtruction; guide, I humbly
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:18914:91"/>
entreate thee, my parents in the way of ſaluation; bee a ſtaffe, O Lord, vnto their weakeneſſe, and a guide vnto their ſteps; renew their minds in the decay of their bodies, and giue them inward eyes to behold what their dim and fading ſight can neuer attaine to, that they may walke in truth and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe all the dayes of their life. And graunt, I earneſtly beſeech thee, louing and gentle Father, that I may bee obedient to their holy and iuſt commandements, louing and carefull in performing, to my power, their precepts and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, requiting their former care of me, with my dutie and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe.</p>
                  <p>Bleſſe me, O Lord, in my tender and vnexperienced yeeres, from all euill and lewd company, which may accuſtome me to idle and vnthriftie courſes, invre my mind to labour for
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:18914:92"/>
the attaining learning and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: and graciouſly, O Lord, beſtow vpon mee, as the ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke of all other vertues, the gift of humilitie, being fitteſt for my yeeres, and moſt conuenient for grace to build vpon, euen for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, who hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded all little ones to come to him. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="56" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>56.</hi> A Prayer for Seruants.</head>
                  <p>O Lord God, which haſt bought vs all with thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Bloud, ranſoming at as deare a price the Begger that fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth on Almes, as Kings, that clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in gold and purple, fare deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly: Giue me grace, O Lord, to be contented with the eſtate thou haſt placed me in, and let mee not repine at the lowneſſe of my place,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:18914:92"/>
but keeping heere my ſtation, and carefully watching for the time of my freedome, I may at laſt obtaine eternall libertie.</p>
                  <p>Proſper, O Lord, of thy accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med bountie and goodneſſe, my Maſter and Miſtreſſe: bleſſe them with thy feare, and endue them with thy holy Spirit, that they may true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obey and honour thee. Humble me, O Lord, before them, and giue me grace, faithfully to execute what they ſhall lawfully command: Let mee neuer entertaine a thought to wrong them, but deale truely and vprightly in whatſoeuer they ſhall commit to my charge, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that thou art a ſeuere and All-ſeeing Iudge, who wilt one day call mee to account for all my offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: let me be ſtudious and diligent to diſpatch what they ſhall appoint mee to do, not miſ-imploying my time to their loſſe and preiudice.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="144" facs="tcp:18914:93"/>Saue me, O Lord, from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of thoſe who delight in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, and vnder whoſe tongues lyeth guile and deceit: Preuent me, O Lord, by thy neuer-erring wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and aſſiſt me with thy grace, that I may truely ſerue thee, and them whom thou haſt appointed ouer mee, that I may at length be preferred to thee, in thy eternall Kingdome, who liueſt and raigneſt, world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="57" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>57.</hi> A Prayer for one that is ſicke.</head>
                  <p>WIth what face, O Lord, ſhall I approach before thee? How ſhall I dare to lift vp my voyce vnto thee? What can I ſay for my ſelfe, or what ſhall I offer? Shall I entreate health of thee, who in the fulneſſe of it haue dedicated it to thy ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie?
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:18914:93"/>
Shall I proffer to ſerue thee, that am vnable to helpe my ſelfe? Shall I requeſt thy loue and fauour, who haue euer beene thy profeſſed enemie, and now come onely to beg it, when I am vnder thy wrath, readie to receiue damnation for my hainous and horrid tranſgreſſions? I confeſſe, eternall and euer-liuing God, that I am not worthy that a thought of thy goodneſſe ſhould enter into ſo polluted a manſion: I acknowledge my ſelfe to haue deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued more puniſhment then hell can lay vpon me, who haue daily, houre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nay knowingly, ſo grieuouſly offended thy Diuine Maieſtie, now onely offering my ſelfe to thee when ſin can make no vſe of mee: Yet, O mercifull Father, conſider I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, what my ſubſtance is, how mightie my enemies, and how fraile my owne condition: Forſake me not, I beſeech thee,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:18914:94"/>
though I come ouer-late vnto thee; thy mercy I know, O Lord, is able to forgiue more then I am able to commit: By that bottomeleſſe wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring, I beſeech thee, haue pittie on me, and comfort me, leſt I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire and dye: For my ſinnes are terrible vnto me, and appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me clad in their deformitie: the deuill, whom I haue thus long ſerued, now puts me in minde, and repreſenteth the horrour of hell vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee: O ſweet Ieſus, haſten vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me; and ſince thou didſt vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to put on Humanity for our Redemption, forſake me not now a miſerable and afflicted creature, lying at the feet of thy mercy, who determineth neuer to riſe, till thou ſay vnto him, Thy ſinnes are forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thee. Lend me, O Lord, if it bee thy holy pleaſure, a little more reſpit to call vpon thy Name: Lengthen my daies that I may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:18914:94"/>
mee, and winne thy fauour by ſeeking after thee: But if other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe thou determine, make me, O Lord, readie for thee, and let my humble confeſſion, hearty and true contrition, with the acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thy infinite and boundleſſe Deitie, as it did the Thiefe vpon the Croſſe, ſaue me from prepared ruine and deſtruction, ſweet Ieſus. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="58" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>58.</hi> A Prayer for Womens Deliuerance.</head>
                  <p>VNſearchable, O Lord, are iudgements, and wonderful the workes of thy hand; thou haſt made &amp; faſhioned a Lump of fleſh in my wombe, thou haſt giuen it life to grow, to feed and be nouriſhed; thou haſt adorned and beautified it with limbes and ſenſes; thou haſt, in thy mercy, inſpired a
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:18914:95"/>
liuing ſoule into it, whereby it may hereafter be capable of thy loue and euerlaſting felicitie: Now the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod, O Lord, draweth neere, and the time appointed for the deliuery &amp; giuing vp this burden; be neer, O merciful Father, vnto thy ſeruant, &amp; ſtrengthen me in this my ſore labour and trauell: comfort me, O Lord, in my agony, that I faint not vnder the throwes and dreadfull pangs of the approaching &amp; neere-enſuing birth: let no vaine feares affright me, or the thoughts of what I muſt ſuffer, be terrible vnto me; Let me be comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, O Lord, in thy promiſe, and the bleſſing that muſt proceed from my Ioynes; hearten me, patiently to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure my torments: haſten, O Lord, my deliuery, and giue the fruite of my womb an eaſie paſſage, that with the ſight of a well-formed childe, I may be made a ioyfull mother: grant it, O Lord, right ſhape, and keepe
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:18914:95"/>
the life which thou haſt giuen vnto it, that it may be borne anew of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and the holy Spirit, to be made partaker and heire of thy euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Kingdome.</p>
                  <p>But if, O Lord, thou in thy eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Wiſedome, haſt otherwiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for me, appointing me in the neuer-againe dying birth, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored vnto thee, mercifully aſſiſt me in this my laſt paſſage, that confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in thy promiſes made to all, I may ioyfully giue my ſelfe as a well-pleaſing ſacrifice, awaiting thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Pleaſure, and commending and committing my ſelfe into thy hands, patiently expect the bleſſed houre to be deliuered from the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full priſon of this tranſitory world, into that euerlaſting Habitation, where dwelleth infinite ioy, world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="59" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:18914:96"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>59.</hi> A Prayer to bee ſaid when you goe into your bed.</head>
                  <p>BLeſſe me, O Lord, preſerue and keepe mee, from all the dangers of this night: Saue and deliuer me from the ancient enemie, who through immoderate ſloth &amp; negligence hopeth to betray me: Viſite, O Lord, my ſoule, though farre too meane to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſo royall a Gueſt; yet ſending thine owne prouiſion before thee, holy vertues, chaſte and ſimple thoughts, thy lodging may be the better prepared for thee. Settle and gouerne, O Lord, my phantaſie, that it range and forme not wilde and vnlawfull apparations; ſtay my memorie, that it ſearch not after vaine and idle pleaſures; fill my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding with thy goodneſſe and
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:18914:96"/>
mercy, that being wholly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly buſied with thee, I may eſcape the ſnares and nets of Satan, and wake to my owne comfort, and thy glorie, ſweete IESVS. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="60" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>60.</hi> A Prayer againſt idle Talke.</head>
                  <p>SEt a watch, O Lord, before my lips, that I defile not my mouth with diſhoneſt and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemely ſpeeches, betraying the hearers, to ſinne and vncleanneſſe: Keepe me from their companie whoſe delight is in wicked talke, leſt I periſh with them: Let my tongue deliuer forth thy prayſes, and be the Trumpet of thy neuer-ending mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies: grant me a ſingle and vnpol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted heart, that I may reuerently adore thy Myſteries, and bee the honorer of thy Glorie and
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:18914:97"/>
Maieſty: Keepe my eyes from wandring after the concupiſcence of my deſires, that I bee not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken and made priſoner to ſinne and death. Place my thoughts vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy bitter Paſſion, whoſe mournefull acts may put away all idle delights and pleaſures, and faſten mee vpon thy Croſſe, to weepe and lament my paſſed offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for that ſweete Name of IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS, in whoſe merites all fleſh muſt be ſaued.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="61" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>61.</hi> A Thankeſ-giuing.</head>
                  <p>O God, moſt high, moſt mightie Creator of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, which out of Nothing, haſt made and formed this beautifull All, createdſt the glorious Firmament fretted with Starres; the euer-ſhining Sunne to
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:18914:97"/>
giue light by day, and fireſt the Moone to baniſh the nights darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: giuing life to the Fowles of the Aire, the Beaſts feeding on the Earth, and the Fiſhes whoſe dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is in the waters below, for the vſe and ſeruice of man, making him according to thy owne Image, ennobling him with Vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, Will, and Memorie, to conceiue and apprehend the glorious workes of thy hand; Redeemed him with an vnparalell'd example; preſerued and kept him with an vnimitable care and prouidence: How ſhall hee render thee condigne and worthie prayſes, for theſe thy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable and vndeſerued bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites? How ſhall hee tender to thy diuine Maieſtie, thankes equall and befitting ſuch infinite and innumerable graces? How many, O LORD, haue dyed in the womb! How many neuer attained
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:18914:98"/>
the bleſſed regeneration of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme? How many reconciled, and entred into the ſtate of grace, haue, through their owne corruption, frailtie, and the ſuggeſtion of the diuell, loſt it, and falne away from the faith of thy neuer-erring Word? How often, O Lord, haue I tranſgreſſed and ſinned, ſpurned at thy ſecret Callings, and refuſed to entertaine them? and yet, O Lord, haſt thou patiently expected my conuerſion, giuen me further time to repent me of my careleſneſſe and back-ſliding, ſending thy holy grace to enable me to call vpon thee for mercy and forgiuenes. Prayſe God, O my ſoule: for his louing kindnes endureth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> generation vnto gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; he hath not dealt ſo with eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man, nor ſo aboundantly ſhowred his fauor to all his people. I wil mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie him from the riſing of the Sun, vnto the going downe of the ſame,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:18914:98"/>
who hath raiſed me from death, and not ſuffered mee to goe downe into the Pit; who hath forgotten my wickedneſſe, and remembred himſelfe of his goodnes: glorie be vnto thee on high, and praiſe vpon earth, who hath giuen charge to his Angels to keepe vs in all our wayes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="62" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>62.</hi> A Prayer for direction in all our affaires.</head>
                  <p>GIue me grace (O merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and truely louing Lord, that I may with all ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, ardency and earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſpirit, wiſely and carefully ſearch after thoſe things which may be pleaſing vnto thee. Order and ſo diſpoſe of me, that I may faithfully and truely performe thoſe things, which thou requireſt of me, and
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:18914:99"/>
giue me knowledge (O Lord) to doe it as it ought, and is moſt expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient for my owne ſoule. Grant (O Lord God) that I neither grow preſumptuous, ſeated in Proſperity, nor be caſt downe, deſpairing with the frownes of Aduerſitie. Let thy fauour be my onely delight, and my diſcontent thy diſpleaſure. Let me endeuour to pleaſe none, nor be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to diſpleaſe any but thy ſelfe. Let all tranſitorie things be baſe in my ſight, and what belongeth to thee, be onely acceptable, and thou, O God, aboue all. Let the paines (O Lord) which are for thee, be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue any pleaſure, and pleaſure with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thee, ſeeme tedious, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome. Grant me often to deſire the accompliſhment of good things, and in my relapſe, to ſpring vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, with full purpoſe of amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Make me (O Lord God) obedient, without grudging; poore,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:18914:99"/>
without quailing; chaſte, without pollution; patient, without murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; humble, without diſſembling; merry, without diſſolutenes; ſad, without deiection; graue, without auſteritie; pleaſant, without light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; fearefull, not deſpairing; true, not doubling; doing good, without preſumption; admoniſhing my neighbour, without arrogancie; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difying him by word and example, without diſſimulation. Giue vnto me (Lord God) a watchfull heart, that no curious cogitation may draw me from thee: a noble one, that no vnworthy affection may triumph o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it: a ſincere one, that no euill intention may bend it from thee: an inuincible heart, that no perſecution may glory in his ouerthrow: a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous one, that no peruerſe and violent paſſion may challenge rule ouer it. Beſtow on me (O Lord) an vnderſtanding, knowing thee: a
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:18914:100"/>
diligence, ſeeking thee: a wiſedome, finding thee: a conuerſation, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to thee: a perſeuerance, faithfully expecting thee: a confidence, finally embracing thee; to be pierced with thy puniſhments through repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; to vſe thy benefits in this way fare by grace, and at length by glory to enioy thy ioyes in thy countrey, who liueſt &amp; raigneſt, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="63" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>63.</hi> A Prayer for great Perſonages.</head>
                  <p>O Moſt mighty, high and euerliuing God, King of all Kings, Lord of all Lords; the onely gouernour, Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour and aduancer of mankinde, which haſt pleaſed to call me to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and promotion, making me a Ruler and directer of thy people: Teach me (O Lord) the way to bee
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:18914:100"/>
humble in mine owne eyes, that I may louingly and courteouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine any poore brethren, as great and noble in thy ſight, and bought at as deare a rate as the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt. Giue me (O Lord) ſingleneſſe of heart; cleanneſſe of hands; truth of tongue; meekenes of Spirit; that I may in all affayres and buſineſſes of the generall State, reſpect aboue all things thy glory; next, the weale of the publique; and laſtly, my own peace and content, which in the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightnes of a good conſcience, make O Lord, firme vnto me. Take from me, I earneſtly beſeech thee, the fire of Ambition, leſt dallying with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy flames, I returne to in-glorious Aſhes. Quench in mee (O merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly louing Father) the longing thirſt of new Titles and Dignities, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging it a bleſſing aboue any deſert of mine, to be thy Creature, and fearing the charge and burden
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:18914:101"/>
already impoſed vpon me, endeuour with all lowlineſſe to render thee a iuſt account. Grant that my power may be a ſhelter, not oppreſſion to the weaker: and the nobleneſſe of my birth, a continuall remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer how to bring forth vertues and actions, worthy and beſeeming that height and ſuperioritie, that in all things ſquaring the line of my life, and ordering all my thoughts, actions and endeuours, by thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and inſtructions, I may leaue my example as a holy practice to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and die in thy fauour, that I may liue eternally with thee, world without end.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="64" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:18914:101"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>64.</hi> A Thanksgiuing for the recouerie of our High and Mighty Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, King <hi>IAMES. April 1619.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I INcline thine eare vnto vs (O Lord) and mercifully heare our ſupplications and prayers that we make before thee, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſpeedily and happily deliuered our moſt gracious King, thy hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Seruant; redeeming vs, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing him from the many trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and vncertaine dangers, which any alteration may bring vpon vs. Keepe him (O Lord) to thee for vs, from the bloudy hand of home-bred Treaſon, which endeuoureth vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently to ſpoile him, and ſaue him by thy mighty power, from the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious deſire of Forraine inuaſion, which vnlawfully plotteth and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth about to gripe into their hands
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:18914:102"/>
the rule and ſtate of this Kingdome, ouer which by thy ordinance and eternall prouidence he is made chiefe Lord and Ruler. Defend him (O merciful and all-louing Father) from the Tyrannie of ſicknes, which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to deſtroy nature, and ſteale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way life from him, and what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther infirmities the weakeneſſe of nature, want of digeſtion, diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perateneſſe of Ayre, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther naturall cauſe may bring vpon him. Be pleaſed (O Lord) to eaſe and cure him by thy all-reſtoring hand, who cameſt into the world to heale all maner of diſeaſes, that wee may perfectly enjoy him in his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous gouernment, with the bleſſed fruits and increaſe of it, to thy eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall glory, his owne ſaluation, and our comfort, peace and tranquillitie, euen for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, our onely Lord, Mediator and Sauiour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="65" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="163" facs="tcp:18914:102"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>65.</hi> Another.</head>
                  <p>A A Wake vs (O Lord) from ſinne and iniquity, that we deſerue not thy Scourge and Rod, in vntimely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuing vs of thy faithfull Seruant, our moſt gracious King, whom thou haſt mercifully placed ouer vs. Giue vs loyall &amp; obedient hearts, that we may truely and humbly vnder thee, loue, honour and obey him: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly vnite our ſelues to him, and vnperſwadably become his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers and liege Seruants. Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue (O Lord) thy care and fauour to him, that he may as hitherto reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procally tender &amp; reſpect the good and weale of vs his poore &amp; vnder-Subiects, eſteeming vs helping and neceſſarie members of himſelfe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to execute and vndergo what
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:18914:103"/>
he ſhall in thy feare and Religion charge and command, that we ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and endeuouring to become perfect Imitators, and Types of thee and thy Church in vnanimitie and tranquillitie, may with one conſent labour the ſetting forth of thy honour and glory, with our owne well-doing and eternall happineſſe. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="66" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>66.</hi> A Prayer againſt our Enemies.</head>
                  <p>M MAke vs (O Lord) mighty and ſtrong, armed in the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of thy all-preſeruing and powerfull Arme. Stretch it foorth (O Lord) and ſcatter our enemies, who haue conſpired, and are combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt vs. Behold (mercifull Father, the infinite and innumerable troupes they haue gathered and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:18914:103"/>
together, to ſpoile and ruine thy people, who haue no hope nor truſt, but in thy mercies. Their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies couer the face of the Land, and their Ships haue not Sea enough to weild their huge bodies: they glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the deſire and aſſuredneſſe of bloud and ſlaughter, and meditate all the day long, on Rapine and Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie. They haue in their thoughts the murdering of Sucklings and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, and the deflowring of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins is euer before their eyes: they ioy in repreſenting to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the Ranſacking the ſubſtance of poore mens labours, and feeding their Ryots with the ſweat of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers browes, determining to leaue no barbarouſnes vnpractiſed, or vn-attempted. Smite them (O Lord, in the height of their pride, and bring their mightineſſe and ſtrength to nothing. Let the Sea (O Lord) which they haue inhabited,
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:18914:104"/>
ouerthrow their proud buildings, and deſtroy them: The Sunne and winde (O LORD) vndoe and put to flight their Land-Souldiers, with tempeſts and heate; that wee thy ſeruants being deliuered from the feare of our enemies, may ſerue thee all the dayes of our life, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying and magnifying thy holy name, who art the giuer of all victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="67" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>67.</hi> Another Prayer for deliuerance from our Enemies.</head>
                  <p> E EVermore will I cry vnto thee, and all my life long meditate on thy mercies, who wilt not ſuffer the ſcornefull and proud to preuaile againſt thy ſeruants; nor the miſchieuouſly-min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to haue the vpper hand ouer them. The Enemies (O Lord) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:18914:104"/>
and ouer-daring in the ſtrength of men, and Chariots, haue prouided whips and torments for thy people, not ſeeking vvhich way to ouercome; but to torment, as aſſured to ouercome. They come (O Lord) not to fight, but ouer-runne; not to giue battaile, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction vnto thy ſeruants. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent (O Lord) their malice, and vndoe their ſubtill, and well-labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Stratagems: Make them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge thee the beſtower, and man with all his Engines, but thy Miniſter, to bee ordered as it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thee. Let them ſee (O Lord) their Chariots ouer-turned vvith their owne guiders, their Horſes made a ſlaughter by the ill directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their owne maſters, and the Souldiers in the day of Battell cruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the weight of their owne Armour, that they may not be able to lift vp their hands againſt thoſe,
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:18914:105"/>
who put their whole truſt and hope of victory in thee. Grant this (O Lord) for the precious bloud of thy onely Sonne; in whoſe name we are aſſured to obtaine all our iuſt petitions. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="68" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>68.</hi> A Thanksgiuing for the ouerthrow of our Enemies.</head>
                  <p>S. SIng vnto the Lord a new Song, for hee hath done maruellous things, with his owne right hand, and with his holy arme, hath he gotten himſelfe the victorie. This is the day where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Lord redeemed vs, and hath taken vs from the hands of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: let vs proclaime it to all gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and let the fartheſt Nations heare of his louing kindneſſes. When our Souldiers were amazed, our Lord comforted them, and in the
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:18914:105"/>
multitude of their enemies was a ſtay and Bulwarke vnto them: He guided their ſhot, and gaue might and power vnto their armes, to beat and diſperſe the growing Hoſt, which threatened in their fury to ouerwhelme them: he diſcomfited them, and tooke their heart from them, returning them with greater feare, then they marcht on with aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurednes. When our Captaines, confounded with the danger of the fight, and confuſed with the tumult of their Souldiers, forgat their skill in leading, he conducted &amp; brought them on againe, ordered them, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing life and ſpirit to the fainting and fearefull troupes, that they fell vpon their enemies as enraged Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſcattered them, and purſued them to a ſhamefull retyring, and dis-honourable yeelding. This is thy worke (O Lord) and it is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull in our eyes, and ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:18914:106"/>
thy goodnes in the confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe mis-beleeuing people that doe not acknowledge thee. But giue vnto vs (O Lord) that haue receiued this bleſſing at thy hands, to vs that haue mightily ſeene thy euerlaſtingneſſe and power in our owne vnexpected ſafety, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought of ruine to our enemies, humble and obedient hearts, fired and inflamed with this thy high and vndeſerued bounty, that wee may neuer forget the Day of our Deliuerance, but leaue it holy to all ages, magnifying and extolling thee the giuer of all conqueſt. Let no ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie take from our eyes the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and ouer-paſſed danger; no laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or confirmed peace, the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of this fierce and cruell battaile fought by thee, and obtained by thee; but hauing it freſh and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent before vs, continually praiſe and laud thee who haſt preſerued vs,
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:18914:106"/>
euen for thy owne honour and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which bee euerlaſting, world without end. So be it. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="69" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>69.</hi> A Prayer for preſent neceſsities.</head>
                  <p>O Gracious and euer-louing Lord, which out of thy bounty &amp; infinite fauour, haſt promiſed to heare the Petitions of thoſe that aske in thy Sonnes name, to whom our neceſſities are knowne, and our wants manifeſt. Grant (we beſeech thee) moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Father, that we may by thy eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall prouidence, be relieued and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coured, miſerably languiſhing and groning vnder the waight of our low and deſperate extremities: put it into the hearts of ſome of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, to call vs to them, and giue vs employment, that we may by the ſweat of our browes labour to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:18914:107"/>
and keepe our ſelues and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and aboue all, let vs patiently endure and vndergoe what calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhal euer fall vpon vs, wel know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they are impoſed for our ſinnes, and farre ſhort of their deſert and due, ſtill expecting thy mercifull hand to redeem and deliuer vs from them. Thou (O Lord) which takeſt care of the Flowers of the field, and enrobeſt the Lilly aboue the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of Kings, wilt not I (know) leaue thy Children and Seruants for euer; nor giue them ouer to bee an ignominie and ſhame to their deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, but that they ſhall at laſt reioyce and ſing vnto thee; Our Lord hath heard our prayers, and mercifully conſidered the Petitions, and earneſt requeſts of his ſeruants: he hath ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled his promiſe, and graciouſly ſuccoured and ſuſtained them: prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the name of the Lord, now and for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="70" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="173" facs="tcp:18914:107"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>70.</hi> Another Prayer entreating Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinnes, and conſtancie in good purpoſes.</head>
                  <p>GIue mee leaue (O Lord) to ſpeake vnto thee, and in thy preſence to vnloade the griefe and troubles of mind, which burden and diſquiet mee, taking away my ſleepes, and laying vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent hands on the comfort and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent I ſhould enioy in thee. Why am I (O moſt mercifull Father) for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken, and giuen vp to the wilde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and concupiſcences of my fleſh? Why am I left a prey to Satan, and laid open to his ſubtill and ſecret temptations? Why hath the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſinnes as a Sea growne vpon mee, and the number and dayly practice of my offences taken away almoſt hope of my ſafety and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerie.
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:18914:108"/>
Am I (O Lord) markt for a veſſell of diſ-honour, and ſhall thy Omnipotencie be ſeene in my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction? Though theſe things are worthy the hainouſneſſe of my tranſgreſsions: yet are they not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming thy exceeding and infinite loue and mercy: and though it may well accord with my rebellious and traiterous diſpoſition, daring to breake and violate thy lawes and commandements; yet can they no way ſute and agree with thy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded and vnlimited Charitie, which left'ſt Heauen, and mingledſt Humanitie with thy Deitie, to ſaue and recall ſinners and offenders. In the bowels therefore of thy mercie, I beſeech thee, by thy vnſpeakable and vnexpreſſible bounty, which gaue thee vp to death, euen to the Death of the Croſſe, and all thoſe fore-running, ſpitefull and torturous agonies and abuſes, not to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:18914:108"/>
thy grace from me, nor leaue me to my ſelfe, who am nothing but pollution and vncleanneſſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine what way to take, yet cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to runne into looſeneſſe and deformitie, without thee, being, O Lord, taken as it were with a dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or at leaſt a forgetfulneſſe of thee, rather careleſſely neglecting, then violently drawne away from thy holy inſpirations, growing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible, and as it were, ſtupid in all things which belong to thy honour, and my owne ſaluation: which of all others and is the moſt terrible fearefull back-ſliding and Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie: For were I carried away with other delights, or onely bewitched with ſenſualitie, I might well hope, when time, and ſacietie had ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently diſplaied their vanity, at laſt to retire &amp; grow weary of them: but from this ſtupidnes &amp; cold numnes of my careleſſe conſcience. Without
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:18914:109"/>
thee (O Lord) who can reuiue me? from this heauy &amp; death-like ſleepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but thy almightie voice, what can awake me? To thee (therefore) I humbly ſubmit my ſelfe, and peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tently proſtrate my ſelfe before thee; deſiring thee, for that eternal and all-comforting name of thy ſweet Son Ieſus, to giue mee a feeling of my owne deſperate and dangerous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, to take away the dead and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtume vices, which haue ouer-growne goodnes and vertue, ſo that I may perceiue, what is wicked or ſinfull, made the ſame with me by a long cuſtome. Grant me (O boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull and louing Lord) conſtancie and perſeuerance in the good deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, wherewith thou ſhalt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire, leſt I fal into a relapſe, &amp; periſh vnſuccourably; euen for thy owne mercies ſake, which from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world was intended to ſaue ſinners. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="71" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="177" facs="tcp:18914:109"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>71.</hi> A Prayer in Sicknes.</head>
                  <p>NOw I am weakeſt (O Lord) in eſtate, be thou ſtrongeſt, and inlighten and comfort my Soule in this darknes and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of my Body. Satan hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed me on euery ſide, and as aſſured of victory, hath laid aſide all his faire and eye-pleaſing diſguiſes, pulling off his beautifull viſor, and in his owne horrible and dreadfull deformitie, telleth me plainely I am his. There is no ſinne (my moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull and euerlaſting Redeemer) which hee is not in the vglieſt and deſperateſt manner ready to lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, more carefull now to call them to my memory, then he was before, to baniſh them for euer. He telleth me it is thine own Doctrine, that the wages of ſinne is Death, and
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:18914:110"/>
that euerlaſting, world without end. But ſhall hee (O iuſt and righteous Iudge) be my accuſer and witnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mee? Shall he betray me to a ſinne, and be rewarded for reuealing it? I proteſt before the Throne of thy diuine Maieſtie, that he alone, ioyned with the world and the fleſh, hath wrought vpon my frailtie, and ſubtilly ſeduced mee to all kinde of ſinne, and enormitie: that he alone hath perſwaded mee to offend thee my Lord and Maker, laying thy heauy diſpleaſure, and terrour of thy iudgements before me; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king either to draw me to deſpaire, or an vnwillingnes to enter into the due conſideration of my hainous miſ-deeds. I doe therefore wholly abiure and deteſt him, abandoning for euer his friendſhip and ſeruice, and relying on thy powerfull and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailable Paſſion, in the preciouſneſſe and value of it, offer vp my ſelfe vnto
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:18914:110"/>
thee, beſeeching thee for thy owne merits and goodnes, to accept a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorne and deſpayring ſinner, who (without thy mercy) is readie to bee ſwallowed vp by the eternall gulfe of hell fire. Moderate, O Lord, my ſickneſſe and paines, that I may the freelier haue recourſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee; ſtrengthen and confirme my fainting and decaying voyce, that I may the earneſtlier cry vnto thee: And aboue all, O my moſt ſweete and amiable Lord, comfort and aide my drooping and fearefull heart, that I may continually medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on thee; that if it bee thy will and pleaſure, I may eſcape the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance prepared for thoſe that dye out of thy fauour; and if thou ſhalt pleaſe to call mee forth of this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall life, I may liue with thee, &amp; put on immortality, euen for thy holy Names ſake: to which be all honour &amp; glory, world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="72" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="180" facs="tcp:18914:111"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>72.</hi> A Prayer to be ſaid, before any worke wee goe about.</head>
                  <p>IN vaine, O Lord, riſe wee earely, and ſit vp late, eating the bread of carefulneſſe, turmoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and tormenting our ſelues with great labour and weariſomneſſe vnleſſe thou, O Lord, giue a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: In vaine toyleth the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, plowing and ſowing, vnleſſe thou water it, and giue the increaſe: In vaine endangereth himſelfe the Marchant, furrowing and turning vp the waters, vnleſſe thou proſper and guide his Ship. Since thou fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt euery thing with bleſſing, be pleaſed at this time onely, Lord and Sauiour, to looke mercifully and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourably on the induſtries and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of thy ſeruant, and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply them as thou didſt the old wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:18914:111"/>
Iar, who gaue of it to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet: grant that wee may proſper and haue, giuing of our abundance to thoſe poore brethren that want it, rather then to bee driuen to aske it: Yet in all, O Lord, thy will bee done, to the extremeſt pouertie, nay, death it ſelfe. Giue me, O Lord, a true feeling of my ſelfe, that I may rather reſpect goodneſſe, then gaine; and aime rather to liue honeſtly, then richly; affecting a mediocritie, not aboundance, leſt I be puffed vp with the vaine and gawdy ſhew of vncertaine wealth: Grant, O bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord and Sauiour, that I may in all my courſes and enterpriſes haue before my eyes the end whereunto they ſhould be directed, which is, onely in this warfare and pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, to prouide me neceſſaries for my voyage to that holy Land, wherein al thy children and ſeruants haue before the beginning of the
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:18914:112"/>
world, a portion and inheritance laid out and reſerued, that I may with that prouidence and care ſo furniſh and ſtore my ſelfe, that I be neither forced with <hi>Eſau,</hi> for want and indiſcretion, to ſell my birth-right for fading and tranſitory re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, nor with the proud and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, exalted with the infiniteneſſe of their treaſure, deſpiſe and grow careleſſe of it; but in all things ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king my ſelfe obedient to thy will, be found worthy to take poſſeſſion of it. Grant this, O ſweete Ieſus. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="73" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>73.</hi> A Prayer for Remiſsion of ſinnes.</head>
                  <p>I Humbly confeſſe (O Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and euer-liuing Lord) that I am vnworthy the bread thou in thy mercie beſtowedſt on me; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:18914:112"/>
to infect the ayre with my breath, who ſpend it to thy diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and my owne defamation; moſt vnworthy the leaſt of thy bleſſings which I haue plentifully receiued of thee; and that I trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to come into thy preſence, my ſinnes ſtriking horrour and terrour to my heart, leſt I be ſwallowed vp for my offences, and wickedneſſes daily committed, and yet vnrepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: But, O moſt mercifull and all-louing Father, take thy Eye, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, from them, leſt thou in thy iuſtice bring me to deſtruction, and fixe it on the bitter Paſſion of thy deare Sonne; behold him, O Lord, ſcourged, buffeted, reuiled, ſpet vpon, and deſpitefully crucify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the hainouſneſſe of theſe my tranſgreſſions; and in the preciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this ſatisfaction, be pleaſed, (O Lord) to giue eare to the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſorrowing lamentation of a
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:18914:113"/>
deſpiſed and contemned ſinner, who is heartily and truely ſorry for theſe his miſdeeds and treſpaſſes; deſiring thee of thy infinite boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to inſpire him with thy grace, that hee may for euer hate and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt the guilt and monſtrouſneſſe of them. Strike mee (O Lord) with a true feare, not onely of thy migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe and iudgements, but of thy mercies and louing kindneſſe, that I may bee vtterly aſhamed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded to offend ſo fauourable and indulgent a Father, who hath not diſ-inherited, nor caſt off ſo noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and diſobedient a ſonne, but in his mercy reſerued a portion for mee: which (O bleſſed and all-louing Lord) make me worthy of, that I may euer praiſe, and glorifie thy clemencie, world without end.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="74" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="185" facs="tcp:18914:113"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>74.</hi> A Prayer for Perſeuerance.</head>
                  <p>SInce, O Lord, not hee that attempteth the courſe, but he that continueth to the end; not thoſe Virgins who came late, but they that watched continually, haue the promiſed and expected re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; giue me aboundantly of thy bleſſing, that I may not onely ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour well, purpoſe good things, and perhaps beginne a reformation and vertuous amendment, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue (O Lord) and perſeuer all my life long, that by the practice of a holy and religious life, I may bee weaned and with-drawne from the tranſitory and ſeducing pleaſures which gawdineſſe and cuſtome haue made ſtrong in mee, and awaite the ſubuerſion and rooting out of all things good and vertuous: ſettle
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:18914:114"/>
firme in me (O Lord) an vnwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried determination of a daily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe and going forward in thy ſeruice, ſince to ſtand ſtill, is to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the enemie: and bridle and take from me the feeds and bloomings of vice, that I deceiued with their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing, yeeld not to them, but perfectly and zealouſly labouring to follow the ſteps of ſo good and great a Maieſtie, may at laſt receiue the hire which thou haſt reſerued for thoſe that diligently employ themſelues in thy Vineyard.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="75" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>75.</hi> A Prayer in Affliction.</head>
                  <p>MOST gracious Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, which art alwaies mercifull, alwaies a preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, whether thou ſend vs ioy or ſadneſſe; for great is thy mercy which by outward afflictions, as by
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:18914:114"/>
a ſharpe medicine, heateſt the inward man; and by temporary troubles prepareſt vs for euerlaſting ioy: euen as thy ſelfe haſt opened the way for vs to true felicitie, by thy owne ſteps: Grant that I may drinke this cup patiently and obediently, as gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of thee. But theſe troubles, O bleſſed and meek Sauiour, fall heauy on me, my proud and enuious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition grudging and repining at them: Giue me (O Lord) in cure the happie and heart comforting ſpectacle of thy precious Paſſion, that beholding thee ouer-flowed with bloud and ſweate, cruelty ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vſed ſeuerall torments to let it forth, I may account my ſelfe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie in ſo ſweet a ſocietie, and my rancour and ſwollen deſires ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly puffed vp with malicious and aſpiring thoughts, may at this ſight fall low, and bee aſſwaged, the vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and poyſoning ſting of the
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:18914:115"/>
ſubtill ſerpent, bee drawne and caſt from me, by beholding thee the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of all patience and gentlenes. Endue me, O Lord, with an abſolute contempt of all theſe vaine and gawdie ſhadowes, whoſe pompe and outward glorie are rated at ſo high an eſtimation: Let me look in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly onely, and all my care be to be richly and ſumptuouſly attired within; Let mee aime at no peace but that of a good conſcience, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring onely thy rebuke and diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but for thy ſake highly eſteeme all the contempt the world can throw vpon me, the ſcoffes, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine and baſe regard they can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict me with, the reuilings, ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, imputations, which enuie and ill tongues can lay vpon me; ſince promotion and high reſpect are no badges of thy ſeruants commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and gracefull language no ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of thy followers, nor ſecurity
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:18914:115"/>
and worldly felicitie, any teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of thy loue and fauour; to which onely (O glorious example of all vertue) let me ambitiouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire, thorow the burning Furnaces, the Lyons Den, the Axe, Stones, or what new crueltie ſoeuer Tyrants, witty onely in miſchieuous inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, can for the profeſſing thee, inflict vpon mee; ſince to loſe all the world, and win thee, is a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe vnualuable, &amp; vnſpeakeable; which grant, for thine owne Names ſake, I may happily attaine, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="76" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>76.</hi> A Prayer in extremity of ſickneſſe.</head>
                  <p>O Ieſu Chriſt, the onely hope of them that liue, and eternall life of them that die, I wretched ſinner, ſubmit my ſelfe wholly to thy Diuine Will,
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:18914:116"/>
whether it pleaſeth thee my ſoule ſhall longer remaine in the priſon of this my bodie to ſerue thee, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of this world, I am ſure what is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to thy mercy, can neuer periſh: I wil lay down this my fraile and miſerable body, with a willing minde, namely, in hope of reſurrection, which renders it to me againe much more happie. Strengthen, O truely-mercifull and all-louing Sauiour, my ſoule with thy grace, againſt all temptations, againſt all the aſſaults of Satan. Inuiron me with the ſhield of thy mercy, by which in times paſt, thou reſtoredſt thy Martyrs vnconque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, againſt grieuous torments and cruell deaths. I ſee nothing in my ſelfe which can bee a help vnto me: all my hope is in thy ineſtimable goodneſſe: I haue no merits or good workes to alledge to thee; but alas, I behold on euerie ſide, many wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:18914:116"/>
and ſinfull offences, many mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and enuious tranſgreſſions, many lewde and laſciuious acts, which are here readie to accuſe and condemne, and as much as their exclamations can further, deſirous to throw me to euerlaſting hell, and perdition. What Aduocate ſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull as thy ſelfe? Who ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full? And who more willing and readie? Who can better deliuer what muſt at this time preuaile for me, being a ſtory of thy owne loue and mercy? Who can ſhew the skars of thoſe honourable wounds which were gotten in the redemption of mankinde, but thy Almightie ſelfe? Who the print of thoſe laſhes which all ouer skarrified thy inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent fleſh, for the painting and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificiall diſcolouring ours? Who with fortie dayes Faſting, expiated our riotous and ſuperfluous Feaſts, but thy moſt mercifull ſelfe? Waſh
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:18914:117"/>
away (O Lord) with thy preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Bloud, the contagious ſpots of my hainous offences, and let thy neuer-failing Iuſtice anſwere in iudgement for my preſumptuous iniuſtice; thy great and mightie merites be an acceptable propitiato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for the multitude of my miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeds: and grant (O louing and all-gracious Lord) that thy grace may increaſe aboue my ſickneſſe: let not my faith faile, my hope faint, my charity waxe cold, nor humane infirmity, ioyned with the feare of death, caſt mee into the bottome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe gulfe of deſpaire, but that when the eyes of my body are ſhut and cloſed vp, the euer-waking eye of my minde may looke vp and bee comforted in thee; and that when the vſe of my tongue ſhall be taken from me, my ſoule may then inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly and continually cry vnto thee, O Lord, into thy hands I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:18914:117"/>
my ſpirit: to whom bee ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glorie, world without end.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="77" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>77.</hi> A Prayer in the Spring time.</head>
                  <p>O Almightie and euer-liuing God, the powerfull Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of heauen and earth, ordaining them with their ſeuerall Lights and Ornaments, for the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie vſe of mankinde, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them in their diſtinguiſht ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to yeeld food and ſuſtenance for the maintenance of thy People; Wee giue thee humble and heartie thankes for this moderate and time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spring, refreſhing the decayed earth, with the kindly heate of the Sun, and temperate falls of raine and water, renewing in vs a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable expectation of our Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, in beholding how thy mercifull and All-able hand hath
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:18914:118"/>
freſhly apparelled the naked and barren fields, beautifying them with ſeuerall ſorts of flowers; loading the Trees diſroabed and withering, with new buds and bloſſomes; the earth her ſelfe ſhooting forth her ſeeds long time buried in her womb, with the hope of a happie and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull increaſe, to the great ioy and conſolation of thy ſeruants: Grant, I beſeech thee, that wee being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed and borne againe by holy Baptiſme, and hauing caſt and throwne off the old man, may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come new creatures, neuer more to returne to our old ſinnes, but that by the ſweet aſſiſtance of thy holy Spirit, wee may increaſe in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall innocencie, and day by day, more and more bee adorned with the flowers of vertue, alwaies grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp in the knowledge of thy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie, that wee may receiue a bleſſing at thy hand to ſpread and
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:18914:118"/>
flouriſh, bringing forth good fruits of a quiet conſcience, and ſweete ſmelling ſauours of a pure zeale and charitable deuotion; euen for Ieſus Chriſts ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="78" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>78.</hi> A Prayer in Summer.</head>
                  <p>EVer-mouing time (O merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Father) deliuereth accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy beheſts, in their due ſeaſons, the foure quarters of the yeare, and from thy bountie we receiue their timely fruits; the Spring hath alreadie diſcharged and vnloaded himſelfe, beſtowing with a full hand, the ſmall ſtore he hath beene entruſted withall; leauing great hope of plentie and aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance: Proſper it (O Lord) and bring it along to maturitie and ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; for now that bleſſed and great Light which thou madeſt to rule
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:18914:119"/>
the day, ſheadeth his influence and comfort to all things mouing vpon the earth: The Hills leape and are ioyfull, the Flouds clap their hands, and all creatures growe buxome and liuely, hauing a feeling and ſenſe of thy bleſſing: Grant vnto vs (O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all goodneſſe) that we bee not more inſenſible then the beaſts, but that wee may giue thee honour and glorie in the acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thy innumerable and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matchable benefits; for whoſe one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeruice the Earth is thus gayly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parelled, the Trees thus plentifully enriched, and the wombe of the earth great, with aſſured expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a happie deliuerie. Let not (O Lord) the violent burning of the Sunne, ioyned with the locking vp thy heauenly Conduits, parch it and dry it to nothing profitable; nor the remiſneſſe or ſlackeneſſe, ioyned with an ouer-flowe of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:18914:119"/>
leaue it raw, and vnſeruiceable; but giue euerie fruit (O Lord) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity and perfection, that we may ioyfully receiue the bleſſing of it, and prayſe thee the beſtower and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="79" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>79.</hi> A Prayer to bee ſayd in Autumne.</head>
                  <p>THou haſt ſhowred (O Lord) fulneſſe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection vpon the fruites of the earth, and euerie growing thing laboureth with a happie increaſe; the rancke graſſe boweth itſelfe to the Mowers hand, the heauie loaden Trees acknowledging homage, offer themſelues to be gathered, and the fulneſſe of the Vine yeeldeth his iuice without the wine-preſſe, the ripe hanging eares liſten for a Sythe; and all the works of thy hand, which
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:18914:120"/>
thou haſt planted heere for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of man, acknowledge thy command, and are readie to bee taſted: All theſe (O Lord) obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to thy will, in the courſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, anſwere the ends of their crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, onely wee miſerable creatures following our ſences, and the luſts of the fleſh, refuſe thy holy inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and ſeduced by Satan, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our ſelues againſt thy reuealed will: New mould vs (O Lord) and breake our ſtubborne and ſtony hearts, that the ſeeds of thy Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell may take deepe roote in vs, and bring forth the fruits of a liuely faith, conſtant hope, and burning charitie, to thy Honour, and our owne ſaluation. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="80" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="199" facs="tcp:18914:120"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>80.</hi> A Prayer to bee ſaid in Winter.</head>
                  <p>THE yeere is waxen old as a garment, and all the freſh colours, which beautified the face of the earth, are withered and decayed; the Sun with-holdeth his influence, the heauens their brightnes, and the day his comfort, taken from him, by the vncomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table hand of deſolate Night. The Trees haue loſt their Ornament, the Fields their rayment, and all beaſts and cattell their vigour and liueli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; Man himſelfe is diſcomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the pooreneſſe and barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and the vnprouident man, who hath not laid vp, nor taken from the fruitfulneſſe of Summer, growes deſperate, certaine of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but periſhing: The Seaſon
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:18914:121"/>
affoording no worke, nor the day any continuance, the lately broad-leaued branches no ſhelter, nor the fields any ſuſtenance. Grant vs (O mercifull Father) warned by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of his extreme and vnredeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able miſeries, to labour in the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, and lay vp of our well-gotten ſtore againſt the vncomfortable day of ſickneſſe, or lateſt Age, when weakeneſſe and naturall infirmities giue vs no time, or thought to get in new prouiſion; and our vnchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableneſſe to our ſelues, take from vs the charitie of others, hardening their hearts againſt vs: Giue vs grace to watch and labour continually, ſupplying our Lamps daily with holy Oyle, leſt at the dead of night we be called on, and being vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, be left behind, or wander in the darkeneſſe aſtray, and comming late, be ſhut out for euer and euer, from all happineſſe and bleſſedneſſe;
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:18914:121"/>
confined to a place where there is nothing to be heard but perpetuall howling and gnaſhing of Teeth. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="81" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>81.</hi> A Prayer in Aduerſitie and Affliction.</head>
                  <p>LET not my enemies, (O Lord) triumph ouer mee, nor the hand of the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor preuaile againſt mee: Bee neere vnto me in the day of trouble, and ſay vnto my ſoule, I am thy helper; thou which mercifully redeemedſt <hi>Ioſeph</hi> from the hands of his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren (who cauſeleſly ſought his life) and turnedſt their hate to his glorie and promotion, deliuering him from the luſt of his Maſters wife, and her wilye accuſation; Thou which reſcuedſt thy people Iſrael by a mightie hand and ſtrong
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:18914:122"/>
arme, from the tyrannie of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh,</hi> and the vnequall Taxes of the hard Egyptians; Thou which ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt <hi>Iacob</hi> grace in the ſight of his brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> boyling againſt him, and threatning fire and deſtruction; planting a ſure ſhield before thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued ſeruant <hi>Dauid,</hi> to keepe him ſafe from the inuaſion of the terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Goliah,</hi> and a wiſe guard to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the plots of ſubtill <hi>Saul;</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming <hi>Suſanna</hi> innocent, conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly ſpotted by the poyſonous breath of the fore-ſworne Elders; Thou which raiſedſt thy glory from the three Children, condemned and throwne into the Furnace, whoſe fire and extreme heate came forth, and eate vp the Feeders, yet ſpared, and (againſt his nature) ſindged not the garments of thy ſeruants, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and ſinging euerlaſting and glorious Hymnes of thy Deitie in the midſt of it: Thou which neuer
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:18914:122"/>
forſakeſt any of thy ſeruants in their torments and perſecutions, giuing them either an vnconquered pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to ſuffer, or a glorious cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to ouercome all the temptations which hell can faſten: Bee pleaſed, Almighty, euer-liuing, and onely powerfull Iehouah, to be neere thy ſeruant in theſe his afflictions and troubles, and to ſtand by him in this day of his tryal, leſt he fall confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and ſinke vnder the heauy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of his tyrannous oppreſſions. Want (O Lord) in the loweſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, hath incompaſſed me, Shame and Ignominy in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, haue ſet me round about; Slanders oppoſe themſelues againſt me, and beare me downe face to face, and ill tongues in ſecret, at my back, oppreſſe me; my friends are fled, my acquaintance hath forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken me, and my kindred (dereſting my pouerty) deny my Allyance.
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:18914:123"/>
Where can I then plant my hope? Where ſhould I elſe ſeeke for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge and harbour, then of ſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull and all-louing a Father, and who, vpon ſub-miſſion, diſdaineth not his baſeſt and moſt riotous ſon? who came into the world to bee a Father to the fatherleſſe, an eye to the blinde, a ſtaffe to the lame, and a moſt heauenly and neuer-erring Phyſician to all that labour vnder a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſeaſe. <hi>Come vnto mee</hi> (ſaith our bleſſed Lord) <hi>all yee that are oppreſſed, and I will eaſe you.</hi> O mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull and generall comfort, as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to be done as it is ſpoken, I proſtrate my ſelfe humbly before thee, and deſire thee of thy infinite mercy, if ſuch be thy will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to let this tranſitorie and bitter cup paſſe from me; yet not my will, but thy bleſſed will bee done, who alone knoweſt what is fitteſt to tame my ſtubborne and rebellious affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:18914:123"/>
and to morrifie in me all vaine and aſpiring thoughts, that I may wholly deſire to bee diſſolued and liue with thee, where eternall and neuer-ending peace and piety haue their habitation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="82" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>82.</hi> A Prayer to our bleſſed Sauiour.</head>
                  <p>MOST mercifully louing Lord, Redeemer and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour of the world, I wretched and deteſtable ſinner, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prous all ouer, and more ſpotted with ſinne, then the bleſſed <hi>Iob</hi> with ſores, which no Poole can euer cure, all humble proſtrate my ſelfe before thee, not deſiring thee to lay thy bleſſed and happy-making hand vpon ſo vlcerous a creature, nor to caſt thy pittying and fauourable eye vpon ſo diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:18914:124"/>
and hatefull an obiect; but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (O Lord) if ſo poore and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy a worme, may aſpire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of ſo high and great a Deitie, one word from thy heauenly lips, to make me whole: but ſay the word (O Lord) and I ſhall paſſe the Snow in whiteneſſe, and caſt my ſicke and aged imperfections, renewing my ſelfe like the ſtrong Eagle: at thy command, whole Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions of ſinnes, which carry mee head-long to ruine and perdition, ſhall paſſe from mee, and I remaine prayſing and gloryfying thy holy name: the numneſſe and deadneſſe of my vncharitable hand, vpon thy Word, ſhall ſtretch it ſelfe forth, and bee exerciſed in deeds of loue and mercy; vpon thy Word, my wilfull and naturall blindneſſe ſhall bee taken away, and I reſtored to a perfect and good ſight, gloriouſly beholding thee in thy reuealed Wil,
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:18914:124"/>
and wonderfully in thy workes; vpon thy Word, I ſhall eaſily heare and fully vnderſtand thy Diuine and heauenly Myſteries, and lay them vp in my heart, for my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and conſolation. The Iewes (O Lord) had eares and heard not, eyes and ſaw not, hands and felt not thy apparant and aſtoniſhing miracles: they ſaw before their eyes the blind receiue their ſight, the dead reſtored to life; they heard with their eares, the dumbe ſpeake and glorifie thy holy Name; they felt thy naturall and heauenly begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Bodie, and yet beleeued not. Bleſſed are they which haue not ſeene, and haue beleeued; But ſay the word (O Lord) and I ſhall be made partaker of that heauenly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nediction, acknowledging thee the Son of the euer-liuing God, borne of the bleſſed Virgin, crucified vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> giuing ouer thy
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:18914:125"/>
life, buried, and riſing againe on the third day, for the redemption and ſaluation of mankinde, I ſhall lay hold of thy precious Paſſion, and bury all my miſdeeds in thy life-giuing wounds, to bee waſht away with thy vnualuable bloud; for euer will I kneele for this Word, for euer remaine a deuout and humble Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner, that all theſe things may bee done vnto mee, and I become a new creature, ſpirited anew, with thy holy Spirit, for euer prayſing and magnifying thy holy Name, louing it aboue my ſelfe, and adoring it, to the end, all generations may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue thy power, in the conqueſt of hell, death, and ſinne. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="83" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="209" facs="tcp:18914:125"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>83.</hi> A Prayer in time of Lent.</head>
                  <p>O Benigne and bountifull Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, our onely Aide, Comforter and Redeemer, the preſeruer of all Mankinde, the glorie and hope of all mortality, who whilſt thou wandredſt here amongſt vs, putting on perfect Humanity, ſufferedſt thy ſelfe to be carryed into the Wilderneſſe, and tempted of the deuil, gloriouſly ouercomming him by prayer &amp; faſting, to leaue vnto vs the ordinary &amp; ready meanes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt all his ſubtill ſuggeſtions, preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the ſame meanes to thy Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles for the diſpoſſeſſing Satan, and haſt alſo left vs many examples in thy holy Prophets &amp; bleſſed Fore-runner, who liued in the Woods on Locuſts and wilde Hony, giuing vs a liuely and perfect Patterne,
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:18914:126"/>
who didſt all for our example, of thy owne bleſſed abſtinence and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; Grant (O mercifull and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sauiour) that wee may this bleſſed and holy time of Lent, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend more eſpecially the ſpirituall food of our ſoules, chaſtiſing and ſubduing the luſts and heate of the fleſh, by temperate and thrifty dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, leſt of a ſeruant hee become a Maſter, rebelling againſt the Spirit. Mortifie in vs (O Lord) all wilde and looſe deſires, ranging and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered appetites, which ſowe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention betwixt me and thee, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king me fearefull to enter, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to ſtand in thy preſence; and plentifully enrich mee with thy grace, that I may do thy workes, ſeriouſly meditate on thy Paſſion, and take it to heart, deteſting and abandoning my ſinnes, the onely cauſe ſo great a Lord was ſo meane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intreated; ſo gentle a Sauiour, ſo
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:18914:126"/>
vngently vſed; and ſo mercifull and louing a Redeemer, ſo vnmercifully and hatefully tormented by his owne ſubiects and ſeruants, in the recouerie of their inheritance and freedome. And if the children of men, after the deceaſe of a louing father, expreſſe their griefe to the world, by putting on mourning garments, confining themſelues to their Chamber, and through an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of heart, forbearing their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie food; was euer a worthier cauſe, or a ſorrow better beſeeming the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> or a time more conuenient, then in the yeerely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing and celebrating the dayes of their Lord and Maſters torments and funeralls, who dyed, and was perſecuted for them? Grant vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (O Lord) we may faſt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly pray, bitterly lamenting our ſins and miſdeeds, which gaue thee vp to the death of the Croſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="84" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="212" facs="tcp:18914:127"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>84.</hi> A Prayer againſt temptation.</head>
                  <p>LEade vs not into temptation (O Lord) but deliuer vs from all euill: ſinne lyeth in waite to betray vs, and Satan baiteth vs with opportunity: he knoweth (O mercifull Father) our affections, and by our actions, gheſſeth at our thoughts; our inclinations he is cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in, and in ſubtilty who can ſurpaſſe him? He deceiued our firſt parents, whom thou hadſt endued with excellent and Angell-like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, colouring his malice with carefull pretences: many of thy choyſeſt ſeruants he hath beguiled, and triumphed, neither is his inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate and cankred enuy mitigated, his power abated, his knowledge decayed, or his delight in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, meaſured or leſſened: He is
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:18914:127"/>
mighty in perſwaſions, mighty in the meanes, and moſt cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in applying them; He hath conquered the world, that world our fleſh, and our fleſh vs: Who can ſuſpect ſo great offers for diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation or miſchiefe? And who ſo neere and inſeparable a friend which tendreth them? Thus are the wiſeſt (O bleſſed Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour) by a ſeeming ſhew of what is good, circumuented; thus the ſtrongeſt with their owne confidence ouerthrowne. Againſt ſo powerfull an enemie, ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully followed, but by thy neuer-yeelding grace, what hope of reſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance? Stay him (O Lord) in his ſwiftneſſe, and bring him back, leſt I fall and be confounded. Suffer him not to draw me to the incounter; for how can mortality hold out? all the glories of the earth are armed on his part, to bewitch ambitious ſpirits;
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:18914:128"/>
all the vanities in the world ſerue vnder his colours, to allure the ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter phantaſies. Am I a match for ſo infinite and puiſſant an Army? Leade me not into temptation (O Lord) but deliuer me from all euill. I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly confeſſe, and heartily beleeue, one word of thine is able to diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort all his Hoaſt, ſcatter them and make them in their haſtie flight ruin one another: he flyeth from thy preſence and trembleth, amazedly asking, What haue we to doe with thee, thou euer-liuing Son of God? com'ſt thou before thy time to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vs? But (O Father of all mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies) how can I deſerue thy aide, or ouertaken with ſhame, requeſt thy gracious aſſiſtance, hauing, from my cradle, beene a follower of his, if not contemning, yet neglecting thy often and lowde Callings? Can I hope, that haue refuſed to walke with Almightie God in ſecuritie
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:18914:128"/>
and ſafety, that hee will daigne to find out me in danger and ieopardy, and reskue me from the common enemie? Thy mercie (O Lord) is infinite, and hath beene infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſt to ingratefull humanitie; thy louing kindneſſes innumerable, vnable to be deliuered or ſet down; There is no end, I well know, of thy euerlaſting goodneſſe: bee plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed therefore (O mercifull Father) if ſo great a ſinner may hope for fauour, by the depth of all theſe, either to take from me the violence and rage of all forcible temptation, or elſe to giue me grace and ſtrength to reſiſt and withſtand them, leſt I be taken priſoner by them, and caſt to the bottomeleſſe dungeon, whence nothing reſoundeth, but the continuall acclamations and curſes of damned and deſperate perſons, euen for that holy and vertuous name of Ieſus, knowne mighty
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:18914:129"/>
in the ſaluation of thy people. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="85" type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>85.</hi> A Prayer for preparation againſt the day of Iudgement.</head>
                  <p>IF the righteous (O eternall and iuſt Iudge) ſhall ſcarſe be ſaued, what ſhall become of ſinners? And if the iuſt ſhall tremble to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the dreadfull ſignes which ſhall fore-run the day of Iudgement, in what terrour and amazement ſhall the wicked be? How earneſtly ſhall they cry out for the Hils to couer them, or to be hidden in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the Sea, that they may not ſee the angry countenance of the wrathfull Iudge! But alas, the Sea ſhall yeeld vp all her inhabitants, the graues their Tenants, and the Hils be laid plaine and conſumed to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, all ſhall be laid open, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:18914:129"/>
ſecret reuealed, the cloſeſt cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the heart ſhall be ſearcht into, and the priuatſt deed be proclaimed, the intent of the beſt actions exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, and the fouleſt and moſt miſchieuous in the hearing of all that haue beene borne ſince the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world, knowne and brought to tryall. What a terrour, what a horrour, what a confuſion, ſhall the Murtherer, Blaſphemer, and laſciuious perſon be in, at that day? All this we haue heard, nay and beleeue, and yet the moſt cunning and ſubtill Serpent, hauing nothing to ſay againſt the truth of thy Word, with his perſwaſions indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth vs to flatter our ſelues, that there is more eternitie in three-ſcore yeeres, the longeſt ſpan of our ſhort life, then in that Eternity of eternities, which ſhall follow it. But thou (O mercifull and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lord) which cameſt into the
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:18914:130"/>
world to ſaue ſinners from the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance prepared at this day, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that wee may repent and be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted. Giue vnto vs a liuely feeling of the danger of it, call it (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee) to our conſideration, as a thing certaine, ſo preſent, no ſoule being aſſured of her abode one mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute. Giue vs grace ſo to prouide our ſelues, that wee may make our account here, ſince after death no man returneth to recall or alter whatſoeuer is left amiſſe. Let vs enter into iudgement of our ſelues, that we be not iudged, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully weigh euery word, that wee be not found to haue reſpected none. Giue vs grace to begin heere while there is helpe, leſt we would helpe our ſelues when there is no beginning: for from hell there is no returning, and after death no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting: repinings are there the fruits of an ill-led life, and curſes of
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:18914:130"/>
our follies, all the conſolations of our puniſhment: from which, let thy mightie and all-redeeming Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion defend vs, which whoſoeuer faithfully layeth hold on, ſhall at that Day, with great ioy and alacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, behold thee, ſhewing thy ſelfe a ſeuere Iudge againſt thoſe who would not beleeue, nor entertaine that Peace-offering.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayers">
               <head>Certaine Eiaculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Spirit.</head>
               <p>O My moſt gentle and ſweet Sauiour, grant me (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee) pure thoughts, vndefiled actions, and a reſpect to thy glory in all my proceedings.</p>
               <p>Let me alwaies (O bleſſed Ieſu) remember that thou art in preſence,
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:18914:131"/>
that I may with feare and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence take account of my ſpeeches, ſettle my behauiour and all my acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as it beſeemeth a Lord of ſuch height and Maieſtie.</p>
               <p>Bee thou (O eternall and moſt meeke Lambe) the obiect of mine eyes, the Muſicke of mine eares, the food of my vnderſtanding, and the content and ſolace of all my ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, that putting wholly on my Sauiour Ieſus, I may bee armed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all temptations and aſſaults of the deuill.</p>
               <p>Ieſu, Lord of my life, Patron of my ſubſtance, Reconciler of my friends, Inſpirer of my ſoule, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruer of my renowne, and Maſter of my liberty, I commend them all to thy holy protection, diſpoſe of them to thy honour and glory.</p>
               <p>What part of me (O Lord) can challenge, or ſhew euidence for mine? My Soule is Heauens, my
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:18914:131"/>
Body Earths; both thy bleſſing: Take me (O Lord) as thy due, nouriſh me as thy charge, and loue me as thy childe.</p>
               <p>O God the giuer of all victorie, ſtand on my ſide in all temptations, powre of thine owne Bloud into my emptied veines; raiſe me, as thou didſt thy ſeruant <hi>Lazarus,</hi> to a new and better life, when I am dead to righteouſneſſe: turne not away from me, if I flye, and let me not bee confounded for euer, whoſe truſt hath beene alwaies in thee.</p>
               <p>Giue me (O Lord) a noble ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance in afflictions; lowlineſſe of Spirit in the height of honours; an vnmoued reſolution in all conflicts; and conqueſt ouer all my ſpirituall aduerſaries.</p>
               <p>Giue mee (mercifull Father) a vertuous ſhamefaſtneſſe, that I may bluſh, and ſhunne the companie of
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:18914:132"/>
wickedneſſe; an vnaffected car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, ſlow and deliberate ſpeeches, vncorrupted thoughts, and holy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours.</p>
               <p>Let thy Word (O Lord) be the light of mine eyes, the repaſt of my ſoule, the repoſe of my ſenſes, the apparell of my body, and my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence in all extremities.</p>
               <p>Lay thy holy hands (O Lord) ouer mine eyes, that I behold not vanity: ſtand at the gates of my eares, and turne aſide all euill and vncleane ſpeeches: Set a watch be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my lips, leſt I wander in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull diſcourſes: touch with thy holy hand all my ſenſes, to ſtay them from ryot and intemperance.</p>
               <p>Let my will, O Lord, reſigne it ſelfe to thy pleaſure, and bee go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned by thy prouidence, accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting whatſoeuer thou pleaſeſt to lay vpon me, as a portion left for me by a carefull and louing Father.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="223" facs="tcp:18914:132"/>Ieſu make me willing to doe good to mine enemies, ſorry to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe the worſt, milde in ſpeeches, modeſt in my behauiour, conſtant to my friends, and charitable to all.</p>
               <p>Giue mee (O Lord) a hearty and true ſorrow for my ſinnes, a firme reſolution of amendment, a conſtant intent to renew my good purpoſes, a perſeuerance to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue them euer, and an ardent deſire to beginne afreſh in thy ſeruice.</p>
               <p>Grant me (O ſweet Ieſu) an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained and humble repentance for my former tranſgreſſions, a hearty and zealous thankefulneſſe for thy preſent kindneſſes, a terrour of thy iuſtice, a doting on thy fauours, and an euer-mindfulneſſe of thy glorious preſence.</p>
               <p>Bleſſe (O Lord) with thy eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall prouidence, my going forth, and with thy holy aſſiſtance guide my comming in, that I may walke
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:18914:133"/>
in thy waies, and returne to thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and ſeruice.</p>
               <p>Let vs praiſe the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, who hath not forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten his ſeruants, but giuen them taſte of good things, recalled them wandring, ſtaid them ſliding, and with vnſpeakeable loue brought them to his euerlaſting Kingdome.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="225" facs="tcp:18914:133"/>
            <head>A Short Meditation vpon theſe words of <hi>PILATE,</hi> ECCE HOMO; Behold the Man.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ooke vp, O my ſoule, and if thine eye lids be not preſſed down with the two waights of ſhame and ſorrow, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold</hi> the Lord of all Maieſty and glorie, abaſed with the diſgraceful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt behauiour the ſcorne of the Iewes could lay vpon him: Behold that reuerent and beautifull counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:18914:134"/>
which the Angels adored, and God himſelfe was well pleaſed in, violently defaced with the vnmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull ſtrokes of his cruell perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; his modeſt Eyes in labour with the bloud which from the riuolets of his head, ouer-flowed all his face, ioyning with a Sea of bloud, which iſſued in euery place from his tender and delicate bodie. What vnuſed torments were theſe (O my ſoule?) What new inuented tyrannies? Was euer Innocence ſo rewarded, Vertue ſo glorified, and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſo exalted? But alas, as if they would out-goe themſelues in tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and ſtudy for vnheard off cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, they couple with theſe paines, the baſeſt and vnmanlieſt ſhames and diſgraces, that euer ſtories haue left vnto vs. Where is the ſacred Balme they apply to thy wounded Bodie? The precious oyntment they prouided wherewith to anoint
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:18914:134"/>
thy bruiſed face<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Is that coate of folly and robe of ignominie, the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinable Seare-cloth they wrap thy torne fleſh in? Is their irreuerent and defiled ſpittle (which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuouſly throw in thy face) the onely remedie they can affoord it? With the hemme of thy garment, (O Lord) thou ſtayedſt an iſſue of bloud; and with diſroabing thee, they open a Floud-gate of thine. With thy holy &amp; wonder-working ſpittle, thou gaueſt eyes to the blind; and they, prophane and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hallowed Rebels! with theirs, would take away thy ſight. Was euer King ſo entreated by his ſubiects? Was euer Maſter ſo abuſed by his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants? Was euer Father ſo tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by his owne children? O wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Subiects, diſobedient ſeruants, and vndutifull Children! What mercie can you expect? What free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome require; what portion hope
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:18914:135"/>
for? Come hither, all yee Kings and Princes of the earth, which account the enlarging of your Dominions, the onely propagation of your glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; the feare and trembling of your ſubiects, the teſtimonie of your Greatneſſe; and your vncontrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and vnlimited command, a roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie onely worthy the Maieſtie of a King: Looke downe from your ſtately and gorgeous Thrones, and <hi>Behold the Man,</hi> borne a King, whoſe Power and Title ſo amated <hi>Herod,</hi> enflamed with the ambition of gouernement, that onely to auoide his right, he gaue command for the cruell ſlaughter of many thouſand Innocents: To whom newly brought into the world, Kings came to offer &amp; bowe down; on whom the Starres awaited, and the Angels of the great and high God attended, like ſeruants: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider well what Crowne inuironeth
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:18914:135"/>
his ſacred Head; what Robe ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his Bodie, and what Scepter hee beareth in his royall Hand. Marke the obedience of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and ſuruey the largeneſſe of his Territories.</p>
            <p>Whurry to this place, yee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and honourable Perſonages; ſpare no treaſure, but purchaſe a ſtanding, to <hi>Behold the Man.</hi> You that dwell vpon ſuch nice and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectiue termes of honour, who rate a Lye at the price of a Life, and a Stroke aboue the value of your Soule; carefullier to be accounted valiant, then honeſt; and faſhiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, then Religious; who purchaſe vertues onely to ſell away your vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, rather forſaking God then your Miſtreſſe: Marke well, and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on the behauiour of this onely honourable, and all noble Lord: See him buffeted by ſlaues and vaſſall-miniſters, ſpit on by the raſcall
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:18914:136"/>
company; laſht, and ſcourged by inferiour and Vnder-officers, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, and with all humility, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going and ſubmitting himſelfe to all kinde of ſcornes and reproches, and eſteeme not the ſeruant of more worth then the Lord, who hath done all theſe things both for your redemption and example.</p>
            <p>Thruſt in among the Iewes, yee common and vnder-people, heere is a ſight worth gaping after, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and <hi>Behold the Man;</hi> you that groane vnder the Tyrannie of Pouerty, the exactions and cruell oppreſſions of biting Vſurers, and hard Land-lords; you, who in the ſhade of your fortunes are left com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe, and whom the night of darkeneſſe and deſolation hath ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly ouer-taken; Behold the Son of the euer-liuing God, diſplaying the beames of ioy and conſolation: and if euer fellowſhip in miſery
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:18914:136"/>
aſſawage the rancour of it, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany be a comfort; glory of ſo noble and vnmatched a partner, who co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with ſweate and duſt, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed with bloud and torments, cloathed with ſhame and contempt, is here made a laughing ſtocke to the people: and ſince God himſelfe ſo vnworthily ſubmitted himſelfe for mans offences; Let vs glory and be proud to become his fellow, and beare a ſhare with him in all troubles for righteouſneſſe ſake.</p>
            <p>O my Redeemer, was the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of thy lips, which in thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy falling as the melting honey from the Combes, aſtoniſhing all the great Doctors and Rabbins, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing them in the high and hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Myſteries of heauen, now in thy firmer age, thought folly, and vaine eloquence? Was that modeſt and beautifull countenance, ſtriking feare and reuerence in the behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:18914:137"/>
one looke whereof raiſed ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to bee glorious Saints, now buffeted and ſpit vpon?</p>
            <p>Were thy innocent and ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe hands, whoſe mightineſſe and vertue looſed the chaines of hell, leading captiuitie captiue, become priſoners to bondage, and fettered with baſe and ſeruile cords?</p>
            <p>What part of thee was vnfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and yeelded not comfort and bleſſings to this vngratefull people? Flowed not from thy tongue, the riuers of peace and euerlaſting happineſſe? Did not thy eye di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them in the way of ſaluation? Were not thy hands continually held vp, and in labour for their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and penitencie? Who followed thy foot-ſteps, could hee euer goe aſtray? Nay, walked they not ſafe in the ſhadow of thy bodie, from infirmities? And did not
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:18914:137"/>
thy outward garments recouer them of long and dangerous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes?</p>
            <p>Did not the Powers of heauen and earth acknowledge thee, and God himſelfe by crowning thee with the Holy Ghoſt, confirme thee for his Wel-beloued? Did not the great Goddeſſe Nature, goe back and alter at thy command? Did not the water turne into wine vpon thy word? The winde banniſh it ſelfe and appeare no more, and the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and rage of the waues lye ſtill and grumbled not? When thou waſt in preſence, was not hell affrighted, and the deuils themſelues aſtoniſhed, crying out on thy Omnipotencie, and deſiring leaue and ſufferance? Was not the frame of the world ſhaked, the Sunne muffled in clouds, the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple deuided, the graues of the dead, of themſelues opened and
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:18914:138"/>
yeelded vp their bodies, which in diuers apparitions were ſeene wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring in the Streetes, to <hi>Behold their Lord and Master,</hi> their Creator and Moouer, thus in himſelfe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided; by his afflictions ſhaked, muf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled with ſorrow, and his heart ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, yeelding all ioy and comfort; and yet miſerable man vnmooued, knowing and ſeeing; more ſtony then the Temple, and ſenſeleſſe as the graues, vnderſtood not pitty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not, felt not the pangs and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which our Sauiour here ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered. Could not all thy benefites (O deare and onely fauourable Lord) bind their ſauage hearts, nor all thy miracles mollifie their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, nor thy well-ordered and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent life ſaue thee from a ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and inglorious Death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (O my ſoule) that the ſtones wept, whilſt the Iewes reioyced; the Sunne of heauen put out his eye,
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:18914:138"/>
whilſt the ſonnes of men conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtared vpon his dreadfull maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre, and for certainty acknowledge, that the miſ-beliefe and perſecution of ſinners more terrified this bleſſed Lord, then all his torments and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable ſufferings. Art thou mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with pittie, and taken with compaſſion at the ſtory of a weake and old father, vndone by his rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous ſonne, hauing his lands exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, his goods ſeized on, himſelfe thrown forth of doores, and expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed poore and comfortleſſe to the mercy of the Streete, and fauour of the open Aire, hauing no annu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity left but the charity of well-deuoted people? And is not thy vnderſtanding crackt, thy memory loſt, thy will broken, ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with deſperate griefe, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ſorrow, to <hi>Behold this Man,</hi> the onely begotten Son of the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuing GOD, buffeted for thy
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:18914:139"/>
wildeneſſe, ſpit vpon for thy blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, reuiled for thy barbarouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, abaſed for thy pride, laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at and contemned for thy folly, ſcourged for thy laſciuiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, rifled and turned out of all, for thy ryot and diſſolution? not circumuented and drawne in by ſubtiltie, but carefully and moſt louingly, not enduring the hard im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, cruell handling, and euerlaſting bondage of his beloued children, came from his Palace enriched with all pleaſures and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, left his honour, and laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide his glory, and offered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vp into the hands of his cruell and vnmercifull enemies, for the deliuery and redemption of his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vnworthy, miſerable, condemned, and forſaken people. O vnſpeakeable charitie, and loue without example, vnimitable, vnmatchable! Man vnable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:18914:139"/>
it, vnworthy to deſerue it, and without his voluntarie and free proffer, vnequall to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted it.</p>
            <p>Dare a low and contemned Vaſſall, for whoredome and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury, runne into the contempt and cenſure of the Lawes, approach the Maieſtie of his King, entreating him to bee branded and ſcourged for him? It were mercie vnexpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to pardon him: but if hee ſhould diſcend from his glittering Throne, diſrobing himſelfe of all his royall and glorious ornaments, and in his owne perſon ſatisfie the rigour and iuſtice of the Law, for his poore and miſerable ſubiect; would not his goodneſſe and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie flie faſter then the Sunne? And further, would not all men admire, and bee enamored with his vertue, in loue with his compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and rauiſhed with his great
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:18914:140"/>
charity: but how would this poore man bee inflamed towards him? With what fire of deuotion would he praiſe him? With what longing deſires would he ſerue him? With what humility and ioy would hee obey him?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold the Man</hi> (O my ſoule) that hath out-done this ſimilitude, bettered the example of this ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, for thee duſt and aſhes, poore worme and ſlime of the earth; who waſt nothing but by him, art no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing without him, and ſhouldſt be happy to returne to nothing but for him.</p>
            <p>And yet behold a ſight of more wonder and aſtoniſhment, then to ſee the glory of heauen thus aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the purity of Angels thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed, vnpittying man taken with a deadneſſe all ouer of goodneſſe, hath no feeling of his owne deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate extremity, or his Lords infinite
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:18914:140"/>
mercy and meanes, vndertaken for his recouery.</p>
            <p>The bleſſed Apoſtle and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of our Lord, S. <hi>Peter,</hi> who firſt of all confeſt his Omnipotency and greatneſſe, and firſt of all in his frailty, denyed to haue knowne any ſuch Man, hearing him ſpeake of theſe things which ſhould happen to him, tooke him aſide, and (as the Scripture ſaith) rebuked him, ſaying, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſuffer theſe things to be done vnto thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the report of the Tragedie were ſo terrible; how killing was the Spectacle? And if the Storie that he ſhould ſuffer theſe torments, preuailed ſo with S. <hi>Peter,</hi> ouercome with an affectionate pittie, that hee rebuked his Lord; how much ought the certaine knowledge mooue vs, that hee hath ſuffered theſe cruel tyrannies for our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and the ſatisfaction of iuſtice!</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="240" facs="tcp:18914:141"/>It is a ſymptome in Phyſicke ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally diſlikt, when the ſicke par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty feeles not his owne weakeneſſe; and a danger, almoſt vnauoidable, when hee findeth not that it is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous; a lightning little before death, or a nimbleneſſe and agilitie of a woman great, the night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her trauell; their eſtates being indeed almoſt vncureable, that may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med they haue no need of curing: Sinne eaſily getting to a height when he is not perceiued to grow.</p>
            <p>The ſlie and ſubtill Serpent, let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting words of cheerefull loue fall off his tongue, when poyſon lies vnder it tempting loue, guilded ouer his perſwaſiue pill, with the appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencie of her owne excellency and profite, forcing a beliefe that ſhee ſhould bee as God; and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to <hi>Pilates</hi> wife in an appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the night before the Lambe was ſentenced and giuen vp to
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:18914:141"/>
ſlaughter, preuailed with her to moue her Husband to haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to doe with that Iuſt man.</p>
            <p>Beware, O fraile and fooliſh mortalitie, of this Hypocrite and deceiuer; who laying beautifull colours ouer his miſchieuous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, perſwadeth thee to haue nothing to doe with the Iuſt Man; and rather not to beleeue that ſuch things were ſuffered, then to haue that horrour in thy conſcience, that they were ſuffered for thy ſinnes and offences.</p>
            <p>This infection was from him throwne on our firſt Parents, which killed all their ioy of life, degraded them from their excellencie and vnderſtanding, and baniſhed them their earthly Paradiſe, and from thence hereditarie to vs, taking from vs the puritie and Innocencie of our Birth, and ſo, that vnleſſe wee be regenerated and borne anew of
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:18914:142"/>
water and the holy Ghoſt, wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enter into the Kingdome of heauen.</p>
            <p>Thus languiſhing, and labouring for eternall life, our moſt bleſſed and mercifullieſt Lord pittying our deſperate and death-like eſtate, deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended from heauen to cure vs, and whereas hee might, if it had pleaſed him, haue come in all pompe and glory, making himſelfe King of the earth, and finiſhed our Redemption with the word of his mouth; yet he to make it more auaileable to vs, and tye vs with a greater obligation, to lay hold of that which onely for our good was intended, ſubmitted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to all kinde of torments, ſhames and diſgraces, in the purchaſing of our Pardon, that wee might then willinglier and heartilier taken with the vnbounded loue of ſo excellent a Lord, in our humble obedience make our ſelues partakers of it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="243" facs="tcp:18914:142"/>
               <hi>Behold this Man, O my Soule:</hi> his whole life beeing a continuall Paſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the ſtubbornneſſe and rebellion of the ſtiffe-necked People, more wounding his noble heart, then the thought of his ſucceeding torments, which hee paſſionately expreſſes in his complaint ouer Ieruſalem, Oh, Ieruſalem, Ieruſalem, how often would I haue gathered you vnder my wings, as the Hen doth her Chickens, and ye would not! mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admoniſhing the ſoft-hearted women, who in the way towards his death, with teares lamented the ignobly barbarous vſage, the regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and cruell Iewes put vpon him, wiſhing them to weepe for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, not for him; ſtill teſtifying his ſorrow for them, aboue his owne ſuffering.</p>
            <p>Let this, O my ſoule, be thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall meditation: this the obiect of thy thoughts: this the ſubiect of
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:18914:143"/>
thy tongue. Let all thy ayme and ambition be, to purchaſe a little holy plot, neere to this bleſſed place, which thou maiſt ſow with penitent and heart-ſorrowing thoughts, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering them aboundantly, with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained and dayly teares, in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring duly, how the Lord of all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie and glory was here mangled and torne for the ſinnes and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of them, ſome of whom ſhall at the laſt day be found feaſting and making merry, hauing no thought of that precious and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valuable Bloud was here mercifully ſhed for them.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Meditation vpon the <hi>Reſurrection.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF the Angels reioyce more at the Conuerſion of one ſinner, then in the holy conuerſation of
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:18914:143"/>
all the righteous, and the carefull Shepheard, hauing charge of many a flocke, leaueth them all, and with great diligence ſearcheth after one that is ſtrayed, returning home if he finde him, bearing him on his back, accounting himſelfe leſſe burdened through the lightneſſe of his heart, then when hee went empty forth: What an vniuerſall ioy? what a height and fulneſſe of comfort and conſolation repleniſhed Heauen and Earth, and all the Powers of both, to behold their Lord and Creator lately ſo mangled, and cruelly torne? he ſcarce retained the ſhape of Man, this day, riſing in all brightneſſe and glory from the Graue, ſhining a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue Angels, bearing the Saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all the world on his Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſhoulders. If the Sunne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore withdrew himſelfe, as aſhamed to be a beholder, when hee could not bee a remedier of ſo horrible
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:18914:144"/>
a cruelty with a mourning vaile; muffling his moueable beauty, is it not to bee beleeued, that hee riſeth early this day freſh as a Bride-groome, putting on all his light and glory, to meete and reioyce with his Creator and Maker, from whom he borroweth his ſplendour and brightneſſe. The day of his Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Graues ſent forth their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, who met and frighted many in the holy Citie. The day of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, the heauens ſent forth their Angels, who with tunes of ioy and holy acclamations gladded the hearts of all the earths Inhabitants. The time of his Paſſion, Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> for feare denyed him to bee his Lord. The time of his Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, his guard for feare confeſſed him to be their Lord Inſenſible things at his Paſſion, witneſſed againſt the hardneſſe of the Iewes, in expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their owne ſorrow; and at the
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:18914:144"/>
time of his Reſurrection, the ſame things witneſſed againſt the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe of the Iewes, in confeſſing his omnipotencie. This day was God glorified: the Angels highly pleaſed: and Man infinitely exalted. At thy Birth the earth enioyed a ſecure peace in it ſelfe. But at thy Reſurrection, the earth enioyed peace from Heauen; not man with man, but God with man: not for a momentarie ſafety, but eternall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe: not onely for ſauing vs from hoſtilitie, but for infinite and innumerable benefites certaine, and laſting, on his behalfe neuer to bee broken, without our faithleſneſſe, and treaſon. In thy life time thou vndertookeſt for God, with men, ratifying it vnder thine owne hand, confirming it with many miracles, and ſealing it with thy bloud. At thy death, thou vndertookeſt for man with God, and at thy Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:18914:145"/>
gaueſt thy ſelfe a Pledge for performance: what liuing ſoule hath ſo paſt the bounds of all mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, not to bee all ouer-fired with bluſhes, in a thought of violating this holy league? what ſad iſſue of <hi>Cain</hi> ſo ſtony and barbarouſly minded hath the Diuel laid vp for miſchiefe, to be the Actor of ſo horrid a Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy? The Serpentine and Crocodile-like act of <hi>Iudas,</hi> in betraying his Maſters life, is not ſo high in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, as their back-ſliding, which breake his eternall word, to be Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of which, hee freely laid downe his life; yet <hi>Iudas</hi> deſpaired, brought backe the pieces, and hanged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. What calme and deathfull ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie, the fore-runner of imminent ruine, as Numneſſe before a dying Palſey, hath ſo poſſeſſed the bewit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> not to thinke of their deſperate eſtate? What in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanting Syren hath with her cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:18914:145"/>
diuiſion, ſet an euerlaſting diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in our vncertaine reſolutions? What voluptuous Circe hath tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed our hearts in the ſhapes of men, making vs carry the mindes of Beaſts, ſenſible of nothing but what pleaſeth the ſence; following onely Nature, yet moſt vnnaturall, for in her luſts we bury all our diſpoſition to goodneſſe? Wherein doe we em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy that admirable and excelling ornament of ſeeing, but in ſearching after vanities and idle pleaſures, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning it home loaden with volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſnes and ſin? wherin our eares but in liſtning after nouelties &amp; lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, ſtuffing them with wandring ſtories and laſciuious merriments? Wherein our taſte, but in palliating gluttony and drunkennes, ſurfeiting it with mis-called wines and meates, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ryot haſtning the intentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hath yet vnnamed? Wherin our feeling, but in thoſe enormities and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:18914:146"/>
which take away all feeling of God and goodnes, leauing no touch of a Chriſtian, hardly of a Man? When do we ſtay our ſelues, vnleſſe gorged? and then imploy all our ſtudy and care, to ſet a quicke edge on our dulled appetites, and procure freſh and new deſires. In this circle we wander and weary out our daies. In this Labyrinth we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle our ſelues, careleſſe of thy grace, which onely can returne vs. This is our life, theſe our actions. Thus wee runne contrarie to the end of our Creation. Thus we loſe the ineſtimable benefit of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. Thus are Chriſts tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments become our tormentors, and his Paſſion our perſecution, whileſt wee not looking on it, die for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. For as hee hath mercifully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed his Pardon, and ſacrificed himſelfe for all thoſe rebellious ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects that will come in, and take the
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:18914:146"/>
benefit of it, yeelding homage and obedience to his heauenly Father: ſo thoſe obſtinate and runnagate trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fident in their ſtrength, confirmed by their multitude, or ſeduced by example, ſtand out in that wilful refuſall of offred grace, ſhall in the Day of Tryal receiue their iuſtly deſerued Condemnation. Retire therefore into thy ſelfe, fooliſh mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie, and with great and ſerious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, take a ſuruay of thy owne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate. Let neither ſelfe loue flatter thee, that things are not ſo bad as they appeare, or childiſh feare, in tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling at thy cure, make thee ſlight thy Diſeaſe, euer remembring the ſore muſt needs be mortall, wherein the remedy is ſo dangerous, in which a little delay is eternall death. Search therefore ſodainely, and throughly, leſt onely pampering vp proud fleſh, thy malady feſter and growe incurable, when euery dreſſing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:18914:147"/>
woe vpon thy heart, &amp; that thou feeleſt an inward compunction and pricking, it is an infallible Symptome of a likely amendment: thou muſt forbeare all inflaming drinke, and high foode, vnquiet and diſtempered thoughts, idle &amp; much talke, vſing ſpare and thrifty dyet, inward and continuall meditation, ſo to abate the ſtrengthener and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of thy ſicknes; that hauing by good and holy meanes made a perfect and laſting cure, thou mayſt reioyce in Spirit.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
